<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Health on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/health/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Health on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: A longitudinal network study of Alzheimer’s and dementia care in relation to disparities and outcomes</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease and related dementia (AD/dementia) represent a looming public health crisis, affecting roughly 5 million people in the U.S. and 11% of older adults. As with other chronic conditions, racial/ethnic and socio-economic disparities exist in the prevalence and burden of illness. However, less is known about how disparities in access to care influence the care trajectories – i.e. the scope, frequency and sequence of services used across health care settings – of those with AD/dementia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Informatics Approaches to Biomedical Evidence Appraisal Using Public Data</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-informatics-approaches-to-biomedical-evidence-appraisal-using-public-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-informatics-approaches-to-biomedical-evidence-appraisal-using-public-data/</guid>
      <description>The quality of biomedical evidence can affect research sustainability, patient safety, and the public&amp;rsquo;s trust in biomedical research. However, often the quality of biomedical evidence remains opaque to the public. It is imperative to improve the transparency of evidence quality. This project aims to leverage the public data sources, including but not limited to The ClinicalTrials.gov, The PubMed database for biomedical literature, The National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) database, and so on, to develop and apply novel data mining and visualization methods for appraising the biomedical research evidence, uncovering implicit biases in clinical research designs at different levels, and presenting this information intuitively to the public.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visualization of continuous health data measurements</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</guid>
      <description>The ubiquity of current smart and IoT devices has the potential to transform healthcare. For example, current devices can measure continuously activity levels, heart rate, blood oxygen levels, and electrocardiogram. Our lab is developing new devices which can measure additional streams of health data which are currently not possible. The summer project will involve visualization of this entire set of data, machine learning, and multiparametric data analysis to extract trends that match health outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>