<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for student applications - DSI Scholars Summer 2018</title>
      <link>/2018/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce the launch of the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for the Inaugural Class of Summer 2018. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: A longitudinal network study of Alzheimer’s and dementia care in relation to disparities and outcomes</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease and related dementia (AD/dementia) represent a looming public health crisis, affecting roughly 5 million people in the U.S. and 11% of older adults. As with other chronic conditions, racial/ethnic and socio-economic disparities exist in the prevalence and burden of illness. However, less is known about how disparities in access to care influence the care trajectories – i.e., the scope, frequency and sequence of services used across healthcare settings – of those with AD/dementia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data Science and the regulation of financial markets (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The development of computational data science
techniques in natural language processing (NLP) and machine
learning (ML) algorithms to analyze large and complex textual
information opens new avenues to study intricate processes,
such as government regulation of financial markets, at a scale
unimaginable even a few years ago. This project develops scalable
NLP and ML algorithms (classification, clustering and
ranking methods) that automatically classify laws into various
codes/labels, rank feature sets based on use case, and induce
best structured representation of sentences for various types of
computational analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Enhancing self-directed learning opportunities</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analyze data from one of the following library applications/systems and create visualizations that highlight the most important findings pertaining to the support of self-directed learning:  Vialogues (TC Video Discussion Application), PocketKnowledge (TC Online Archive), DocDel (E-Reserve System), Pressible (Blogging Platform), Library Website and Mobile App.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Genomic and environmental predictor of preterm birth</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-genomic-and-environmental-predictor-of-preterm-birth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-genomic-and-environmental-predictor-of-preterm-birth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Predicting preterm birth in nulliparous women is challenging and our efforts to develop predictors for that condition from environmental variables produce insufficient classifier accuracy. Recent studies highlight the involvement of common genetic variants in length of pregnancy. This project involves the development of a risk score for preterm birth based on both genetic and environmental attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Global Interconnections Project (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-global-interconnections-project-application-closed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-global-interconnections-project-application-closed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Understand interconnected nature of global multi-national companies via their supply chain, product and services competition, co-investments and co-ownerships as well as other dependencies between operations and revenue streams. We would like to consider the way news on any company specifically propagate down the connection graph and impact other businesses that are related in a way that is not necessarily explicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Internships in DSI Center for Data, Media &amp; Society</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-internships-in-dsi-center-for-data-media-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-internships-in-dsi-center-for-data-media-society/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The DSI Center for Data, Media &amp;amp; Society is seeking undergraduate and masters students during the summer to work on projects at the intersection of Computer Science, Data Science, and the humanities.  These projects will combine domain expertise in the humanities with computer and data science techniques to tackle important societal and media problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Modeling Genomic Evolution with Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-modeling-genomic-evolution-with-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-modeling-genomic-evolution-with-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Fall 2018&lt;/strong&gt; internship is available in the Eaton lab to work on the development and application of machine learning approaches to historical evolutionary inference. Research will involve learning to use high performance distributed computing infrastructure, performing population genetic simulations, fitting machine learning models, and writing reproducible shareable code. The ideal candidate will have experience and interest in Python coding and a reasonable understanding of linear algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Neuronal Ensemble Detection with Temporal CRF (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-neuronal-ensemble-detection-with-temporal-crf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-neuronal-ensemble-detection-with-temporal-crf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given calcium imaging data of active neurons, can we detect groups of co-firing neurons, called neuronal ensembles? We have a number of datasets consisting of hundreds of neurons imaged for thousands of time steps, and seek to extend an existing CRF model to consider temporal relationships. The goal is to be able to detect neuronal ensembles that span multiple time steps, and that are not conditioned on external stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Real time observation and navigation of multitude of autonomous cars, in dense urban traffic intersections with many pedestrians</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-real-time-observation-and-navigation-of-multitude-of-autonomous-cars-in-dense-urban-traffic-intersections-with-many-pedestrians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-real-time-observation-and-navigation-of-multitude-of-autonomous-cars-in-dense-urban-traffic-intersections-with-many-pedestrians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Project components: (i) Monitoring of traffic intersections, using bird’s eye cameras, supported by ultra-low latency computational/communications hubs; (ii) Simultaneous video-based tracking of cars and pedestrians, and prediction of movement based on long-term observations of the intersection; (iii) Real-time computational processing, using deep learning, utilizing GPUs, in support of ii;  (iv) Sub-10ms latency communication between all vehicles and the computational/communication hub, to be used in support of autonomous vehicle navigation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Real-time brain state classification</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-real-time-brain-state-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-real-time-brain-state-classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using machine learning to conduct brain state classification at real-time on EEG/fNIRS/fMRI data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Statistical modeling for dynamic social networks</title>
      <link>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Networked systems are ubiquitous in modern society.  In a dynamic social or biological environment, the interactions among subjects can undergo large and systematic changes. Due to the rapid advancement of technology, a lot of social networks are observed with time information. Some examples include the email communication network between users, comments on Facebook, the retweet activities on Twitter, etc.  We aim to propose new statistical models and associated methodologies for various problems including community detection, change point detection and behavior prediction. The proposed methods will be evaluated on a wide range of network datasets in different areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact Info</title>
      <link>/page/contact-info/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/page/contact-info/</guid>
      <description>The best way to reach us would be by email.
 Data Science Institute: datascience@columbia.edu  Mail: Data Science Institute, 1401 Northwest Corner, Mail Code 4720, 550 West 120th Street, New York, NY 10027 Fax: 212-854-1599 Phone: 212-854-5660  The DSI scholars program: dsi-scholars@columbia.edu  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Analysis pipeline for strain-level microbiome shotgun sequencing</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-analysis-pipeline-for-strain-level-microbiome-shotgun-sequencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-analysis-pipeline-for-strain-level-microbiome-shotgun-sequencing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DNA sequence reads from a community of microbial genomes are currently processed without considering sequence variants. The project involves building a processing pipeline of such billions of short reads, identifying closest strains they might belong to, assembling them into specific clones, calling their variants, and analyzing the dynamic nature of these bacterial strains along sampling points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Healthcare data analytics internship</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-healthcare-data-analytics-internship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-healthcare-data-analytics-internship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently Columbia University, Cornell, and NewYork-Presbyterian have agreed to integrate their clinical (healthcare) and business IT systems onto one shared platform called Epic. The motivating factors to move to Epic are to enhance the patient experience, improve and integrate care, and give our physicians an integrated technology platform that supports the mission of an academic medical center. The intern will assist with developing the “operational” analytics capabilities of Columbia University Medical Center including financial, healthcare operations and healthcare quality analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Human peri-ictal single unit activity</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-human-peri-ictal-single-unit-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-human-peri-ictal-single-unit-activity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Microelectrode array recordings from patients undergoing surgical evaluation have captured typical clinical seizures.  Because of the extreme pathological conditions at these times, identifying single units from extracellular data is a particular challenge.  Our group has developed techniques for tracking neurons through the ictal transition. We are applying them to newly acquired data and addressing fundamental questions about the activity of different cell classes at seizure initiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Informatics approaches to biomedical evidence appraisal using public data</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-informatics-approaches-to-biomedical-evidence-appraisal-using-public-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-informatics-approaches-to-biomedical-evidence-appraisal-using-public-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The quality of biomedical evidence can affect research sustainability, patient safety, and the public&amp;rsquo;s trust in biomedical research. However, often the quality of biomedical evidence remains opaque to the public. It is imperative to improve the transparency of evidence quality. This project aims to leverage the public data sources, including but not limited to The ClinicalTrials.gov, The PubMed database for biomedical literature, The National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) database, and so on, to develop and apply novel data mining and visualization methods for appraising the biomedical research evidence, uncovering implicit biases in clinical research designs at different levels, and presenting this information intuitively to the public.  Students on this project will acquire or hone their skills in data mining, results presentation, and user interface designs and evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Political attitudes and social networks</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-political-attitudes-and-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-political-attitudes-and-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are collecting and analyzing survey data asking people about the political attitudes and other characteristics of their family, friends, and others in their social circles. Some of this work is described &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/unpublished/penumbra_paper_11_clean.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and we are also doing polling relevant to the 2018 midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visual-tactile geometric reasoning</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-visual-tactile-geometric-reasoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-visual-tactile-geometric-reasoning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robotic grasp planning based on raw sensory data is difficult due to occlusion and incomplete scene geometry.  Often one sensory modality does not provide enough context to enable reliable planning.  A single depth sensor image cannot provide information about occluded regions of an object, and tactile information is incredibly sparse spatially.  We are building a Deep Learning CNN that combines both 3D vision and tactile information to perform shape completion of an object seen from a single view only, and plan stable grasps on these completed models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visualization of continuous health data measurements</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ubiquity of current smart and IoT devices has the potential to transform healthcare. For example, current devices can measure continuously activity levels, heart rate, blood oxygen levels, and electrocardiogram. Our lab is developing new devices which can measure additional streams of health data which are currently not possible.  The summer project will involve visualization of this entire set of data, machine learning, and multiparametric data analysis to extract trends that match health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing Columbia DSI Scholars Inaugural Program of Summer 2018</title>
      <link>/2017/12/announcing-columbia-dsi-scholars-inaugural-class-of-summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/announcing-columbia-dsi-scholars-inaugural-class-of-summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;call-for-faculty-participation-december-2017&#34;&gt;Call for Faculty Participation. December 2017.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Institute is pleased to announce the launch of the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for the Inaugural Class of Summer 2018. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage undergraduate and master students to work with Columbia faculty through a data science research internship. The program’s unique enrichment activities will foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>