<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Education on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/education/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Education on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Liberal Arts: Creating an Index for Higher Education</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project works with a novel corpus of text-based school data to develop a multi-dimensional measure of the degree to which American colleges and universities offer a liberal arts education. We seek a data scientist for various tasks on a project that uses analysis of multiple text corpora to better understand the liberal arts. This is an ongoing three-year project with opportunities for future collaborations, academic publications, and developing and improving existing data science and machine learning skills. Tasks likely include: (1) Using Amazon Web Services to create and maintain cloud-based storage (SQL, S3 buckets) of the project&amp;rsquo;s expanding library of data. (2) Extracting information (named entities, times, places, books, and so on) from millions of plain-text syllabus records. (3) Merging multiple forms of data into a single dataset. (4) Scraping websites for relevant information (e.g., college course offerings, school rankings). Some pages may include dynamically created content that requires the use of a program such as Selenium.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Liberal Arts: Creating an Index for Higher Education</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project works with a novel corpus of text-based school data to develop a multi-dimensional measure of the degree to which American colleges and universities offer a liberal arts education. We seek a data scientist for various tasks on a project that uses analysis of multiple text corpora to better understand the liberal arts. This is an ongoing three-year project with opportunities for future collaborations, academic publications, and developing and improving existing data science and machine learning skills. Tasks likely include: (1) Using Amazon Web Services to create and maintain cloud-based storage (SQL, S3 buckets) of the project&amp;rsquo;s expanding library of data. (2) Extracting information (named entities, times, places, books, and so on) from millions of plain-text syllabus records. (3) Merging multiple forms of data into a single dataset. (4) Scraping websites for relevant information (e.g., college course offerings, school rankings). Some pages may include dynamically created content that requires the use of a program such as Selenium.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Enhancing Self-Directed Learning Opportunities Using Learning Analytics</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analyze data from one or more of the following Library Applications/Systems and create visualizations that highlight the most important findings related to our goal of supporting self-directed learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Learning Representations and Patterns in Mathematical Proofs </title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-learning-representations-and-patterns-in-mathematical-proofs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-learning-representations-and-patterns-in-mathematical-proofs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A common challenge for students in heavy proof-based courses is to come up with a long sequence of logical arguments from the problem statement to the final solution. In doing so, they can often skip steps leading to logical leaps or downright incorrect solutions. Ideally the instructor should identify these mis-steps and help students master such proof-based course material. Here we want to take a data-driven approach to address this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Measuring Liberal Arts: Creating an Index for Higher Education</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project works with a novel corpus of text-based school data to develop a multi-dimensional measure of the degree to which American colleges and universities offer a liberal arts education. We seek a data scientist for various tasks on a project that uses analysis of multiple text corpora to better understand the liberal arts. This is an ongoing three-year project with opportunities for future collaborations, academic publications, and developing and improving existing data science and machine learning skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Enhancing self-directed learning opportunities</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analyze data from one of the following library applications/systems and create visualizations that highlight the most important findings pertaining to the support of self-directed learning:  Vialogues (TC Video Discussion Application), PocketKnowledge (TC Online Archive), DocDel (E-Reserve System), Pressible (Blogging Platform), Library Website and Mobile App.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
