<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Closed Fall 2022 on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/closed-fall-2022/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Closed Fall 2022 on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/closed-fall-2022/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Using causal inference to understand health disparities and discrimination in pregnancy treatment and outcomes</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/09/project-using-causal-inference-to-understand-health-disparities-and-discrimination-in-pregnancy-treatment-and-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/09/project-using-causal-inference-to-understand-health-disparities-and-discrimination-in-pregnancy-treatment-and-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adverse pregnancy outcomes (APOs), such as preeclampsia and preterm birth, are common and devastating. The human and economic costs of APOs are tremendous, and the United States has among the highest APO rates among developed nations. APOs are especially common in non-White and low-income communities. For example, in the United States Black women are 50% more likely to deliver preterm compared to White women. Research has shown that the increased risk of adverse outcomes in overburdened populations is not fully explained by socioeconomic status or other socio-demographic factors. In addition to having elevated risk for adverse outcomes, non-White women in the United States may be less likely to receive certain interventions, such as treatment for postpartum depression, but are more likely to receive others, such as cesarean section, suggesting that there may be unwarranted and discriminatory variation in pregnancy care.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
