<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Closed Fall 2022 on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/closed-fall-2022/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Closed Fall 2022 on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/closed-fall-2022/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Neuro-DBER: A flexible neuroscience- and technology-driven framework for Discipline-Based Education Research</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/09/project-neuro-dber-a-flexible-neuroscience-and-technology-driven-framework-for-discipline-based-education-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/09/project-neuro-dber-a-flexible-neuroscience-and-technology-driven-framework-for-discipline-based-education-research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What predicts successful learning? Many variables complicate the collaborative paradigm of learning or skills acquisition, and while the relative contribution of those variables has been studied in isolation, a comprehensive understanding of their synergistic effects remains elusive. The objective of this project is  to specifically establish a framework allowing neurofeedback training in the classroom to help students’ performance. This project aims to develop a flexible neuroscience and technology-driven framework for Discipline-Based Education Research (Neuro-DBER) to revolutionize teaching and learning. Our system merges cognitive neuroscience, education, and innovative technology to enable investigations of the relationships between subjective experience, body language, real-time learning, and neural measures of attentional engagement. Neuro-DBER is a flexible technological framework suitable to any field of study to address critical questions about learning experiences, such as the gap between a student&amp;rsquo;s subjective feelings versus objective measures of content retention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
