<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Summer 2020 on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/summer-2020/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Summer 2020 on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/summer-2020/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Student Applications - Spring-Summer 2020</title>
      <link>/2020/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce that the Data Science Institute (DSI) and Data For Good Scholars programs for Spring-Summer 2020 are open for application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia University&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master&amp;rsquo;s students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data For Good Scholars program connects student volunteers to organizations and individuals working for the social good whose projects have developed a need for data science expertise. As &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; problems with real world data, these projects are excellent opportunities for students to learn how data science is practiced outside of the university setting and to learn how to work effectively with people for whom data science sits outside of their subject area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Undergraduate Summer Interns in Statistical Research (Department of Statistics)</title>
      <link>/2020/01/undergraduate-summer-interns-in-statistical-research-department-of-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/undergraduate-summer-interns-in-statistical-research-department-of-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia&amp;rsquo;s Department of Statistics is running a summer research internship program for Columbia undergraduate students to work with its faculty on cutting-edge statistical research. This year,
the internship will be during the first summer session (May 26, 2020 - July 2nd, 2020). Interns receive a stipend of $3,000 and are housed in undergraduate dormitories during the internship period.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A multi-omic map of human aging</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-a-multi-omic-map-of-human-aging/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-a-multi-omic-map-of-human-aging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project builds on a novel cellular model of human aging (Sturm et al. Epigenomics 2019) where we can investigate trajectories of multiple molecular features of aging over long time periods. The underlying multi-omic dataset includes epigenomic (DNA methylation), proteomic (protein abundance), bioenergetics (mitochondrial respiration), telomere length, and various secreted factors. A major challenge for the DSI Fellow will be to integrate the multi-omic dataset to capture dynamic signatures of mitochondrial dysfunction and cellular aging, working collaboratively with other scientists. The existing project is expected to result in one or more publications. Possibility to continue work for pay over the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A system for exploratory data analysis in neuroscience</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-a-system-for-exploratory-data-analysis-in-neuroscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-a-system-for-exploratory-data-analysis-in-neuroscience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Advances in data collection technologies in neuroscience has resulted in a deluge of high-quality data that needs to be analyzed, and presented to the experimentalist in a meaningful way. Usually the “data analysis and visualization”-pipeline is built from scratch for each new experiment resulting in a significant amount of code duplication and wasted effort in rebuilding the analysis tools. There is a growing need for a unified system to automate much of the repetitive tasks and aid biologists in understanding their data more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced data science methods to improve spinal electrical stimulation for paralysis</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-advanced-data-science-methods-to-improve-spinal-electrical-stimulation-for-paralysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-advanced-data-science-methods-to-improve-spinal-electrical-stimulation-for-paralysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We aim to augment recovery in spinal cord (SC) injured patients. Electrical stimulation of the SC can facilitate recovery, but the mechanisms are not yet understood. One knowledge gap lies in the exact pathways that are recruited by stimulation. To close this gap, we have tested the effects of SC stimulation in people undergoing clinically indicated surgery. By testing the distribution and size of muscle responses to SC stimulation, we can infer which circuits are activated. We are also examining how SC injury changes those responses. We propose to use Bayesian methods to understand the  interaction between muscle responses to stimulation and the MRI indicated pattern of damage. The project will involve construction of models linking multiple data modalities that predict muscle activity, followed by the modification of these models to account for patterns of damage. Construction of such models would enable a deeper understanding of SC stimulation  leading to more effective stimulation paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COSMOS Smart Intersections, Cloud-Connected Vehicles</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-cosmos-smart-intersections-cloud-connected-vehicles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-cosmos-smart-intersections-cloud-connected-vehicles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Research on: (i) COSMOS cloud connected vehicles, (ii) Monitoring of traffic intersections, using bird’s eye cameras, supported by ultra-low latency computational/communications hubs; (iii) Simultaneous video-based tracking of cars and pedestrians, and prediction of movement based on long-term observations of the intersection; (iv) Real-time computational processing, using deep learning, utilizing GPUs, in support of COSMOS applications; (v) Sub-10ms latency communication between all vehicles and the edge cloud computational/communication hub, to be used in support of autonomous vehicle navigation. The research is performed using the pilot node of project COSMOS infrastructure &lt;a href=&#34;https://cosmos-lab.org/&#34;&gt;https://cosmos-lab.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combining in vivo calcium imaging datasets and deep learning networks for video analysis (DeepLabCut) to identify novel brain regulators of fine motor learning in mice</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-combining-in-vivo-calcium-imaging-datasets-and-deep-learning-networks-for-video-analysis-deeplabcut-to-identify-novel-brain-regulators-of-fine-motor-learning-in-mice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-combining-in-vivo-calcium-imaging-datasets-and-deep-learning-networks-for-video-analysis-deeplabcut-to-identify-novel-brain-regulators-of-fine-motor-learning-in-mice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to use deep learning networks to understand which neurons in the brain encode fine motor movements in mice. We collected large datasets entailing calcium imaging data of active neurons and high-resolution videos when mice perform motor tasks. We want to use recent advances in deep learning to (1) estimate the poses of mouse body parts at a high spatiotemporal resolution (2) extract behaviorally-relevant information and (3) align them with neural activity data. Behavioral video analysis is made possible by transfer learning, the ability to take a network that was trained on a task with a large supervised dataset and utilize it on a small supervised dataset. This has been used e.g. in a human pose–estimation algorithm called DeeperCut. Recently, such algorithms were tailored for use in the laboratory in a Python-based toolbox known as DeepLabCut, providing a tool for high-throughput behavioral video analysis. The project has three parts: (1) Train neural networks through frame extraction and posture annotation using DeepLabCut, (2) Apply network to large datasets using DeepLabCut and extract behaviorally-relevant information using Python/Matlab custom-written scripts, (3) Align behavioral data with neural activity data and perform cross-correlations using Python or Matlab custom-written scripts. Ultimately this project will allow to understand the relationship between motor function and neural activity in specific cell-types in the brain. The data science tools acquired by the student have multiple applications, either in circuit neuroscience (e.g. animal behavior, deep brain imaging) or in computer vision (eg animal or human pose/posture estimation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community-Based Environmental Impact Tracking for Bauxite Mining in Guinea</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-community-based-environmental-impact-tracking-for-bauxite-mining-in-guinea/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-community-based-environmental-impact-tracking-for-bauxite-mining-in-guinea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This position is associated with a new research project co-funded by the Earth Institute Frontiers seed funding and the UN Development Programme in Guinea. Its goal is to develop remote sensing technologies to track environmental impact from bauxite mining in rural communities and to help establish protocols for their use. We seek a research assistant who can (1)  develop image classification to be applied to satellite imagery to determine extent and abundance of bauxite dust within specific communities in the Boké region (2 develop methods to make classified images available for download to smartphones in the field and (3) adapt existing application technologies to allow users in the field to upload field photographs and locations of potential impacts they identify. The resulting map would represent a composite of satellite imaged areas of impact verified in the field and documentation of other areas of impact not visible by satellite but already identified in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating accurate and equitable data resources for precision public health using machine learning tools</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-creating-accurate-and-equitable-data-resources-for-precision-public-health-using-machine-learning-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-creating-accurate-and-equitable-data-resources-for-precision-public-health-using-machine-learning-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The objective of this project is to construct linkages across disparate public health data systems using machine learning tools and assess them for bias and equitable representation of subpopulations defined by demographic and socioeconomic factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Data Analysis for a Just Transition in Energy for Thermal Comfort</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-data-analysis-for-a-just-transition-in-energy-for-thermal-comfort/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-data-analysis-for-a-just-transition-in-energy-for-thermal-comfort/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;42% of New York City greenhouse gas emissions result from on-site fossil fuel combustion in residential and commercial buildings; space heating is, by far, the majority contributor. Both New York State and NYC have policies to dramatically reduce emissions that will require a transformation in the way buildings are heated, including major efforts in existing buildings. This transition is inextricably linked to existing energy equity issues that we believe significantly overlap across NYC (and elsewhere). These include unreliable heating in the winter, susceptibility to extreme heat (an increasing occurrence with climate change) and struggles to afford energy needs. Various known data sources for NYC are available, though they are disparate and have not been analyzed holistically. Further, we believe there are potential engineering and policy solutions to these challenges. In this project, the DSI scholar will access (and search for where not yet known to qSEL researchers) relevant data sets, analyze those data sets to identify communities exposed to all or a subset of these issues, and assist qSEL researchers in developing models to evaluate possible solutions. The project has the possibility of extending through Summer 2020, subject to fundraising efforts and the success of the Spring 2020 project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding the dynamics of mouse behavior that predict exploring and remembering.</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-decoding-the-dynamics-of-mouse-behavior-that-predict-exploring-and-remembering/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-decoding-the-dynamics-of-mouse-behavior-that-predict-exploring-and-remembering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Decoding behavioral signifiers for choice and memory can have far reaching implications for understanding actions and identifying disease. We use a four arm maze where we are able to observe choices and infer memory in mice, but have access to very few pre-determined behavioral signifiers. Several recent publications implemented computer vision to extract a variety of previously unreachable aspects of behavioral analysis, including animal pose estimation (Mathis et al., 2018) and distinguishable internal states (Calhoun et al., 2019). These descriptions allowed for the identification and characterization of dynamics, which then revealed an unprecedented richness to the behaviors that determine decision making. Applying such computational approaches to examine behavior in our maze in the context of behaviors that have been validated to measure choice and memory can reveal dimensions of behavior that predict or even determine these psychological constructs. DSI scholars would use pose estimation analysis to evaluate behavioral signifiers for choice and memory and relate it to our real time concurrent measures of neural activity and transmitter release. The students would also have opportunity to examine the effect of disease models known to impair performance on our maze task on any identified signifier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning for tracking single molecules and proteins</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-deep-learning-for-tracking-single-molecules-and-proteins/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-deep-learning-for-tracking-single-molecules-and-proteins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project will be focused on creating a deep learning framework for tracking individual molecules and proteins as they move within a cell under various conditions. Using total internal reflection (TIRF) microscopy, we have accumulated more than 10 million trajectories over dozens of experimental preparations with differences in both the imaging approaches as well as the biological context. In our experiments we have captured particles under a wide variety of conditions including increased protein expression level, and a range of drug concentrations. Our biggest challenge is being able to stably track the movement of a particle as it passes by other particles or groups of particles, and to do this in a way that generalizes over novel conditions. The Data Science Institute Scholar chosen for this project would work with scientists in the Javitch laboratory and others across the Columbia campus to conceive of an approach for efficiently and effectively tracking particles. The resulting work would be of great interest to an increasing number of scientists working in this field who currently rely on methods based on feature engineering that are often inaccurate or inflexible compared to modern deep learning methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering latent structure in human information demand</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-discovering-latent-structure-in-human-information-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-discovering-latent-structure-in-human-information-demand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All complex behaviors require animals to coordinate their perception and actions. To successfully achieve a goal, a decision maker (DM; be it a human, animal, or artificial agent) must determine which action to take and, faced with much more information than she can fully process, must decide which source of information to consult to best guide that action. But in contrast with natural tasks, traditional research has focused primarily on action selection but eschewed the process of information demand. We aim to fill this gap by investigating the factors that motivate people to become curious and seek information.  We are collecting behavioral data from a large sample of participants on a battery of online tasks testing various aspects of curiosity, and seek a DSI scholar who can quantitatively analyze the data. The scholar will be supervised by two co-PIs: Jacqueline Gottlieb, in Columbia&amp;rsquo;s Neuroscience Department and Zuckerman Institute, and Vince Dorie, in the DSI. The scholar will obtain training with advanced data analytic methods and the opportunity to co-author what is expected to be a high impact paper with interdisciplinary appeal in economics, neuroscience, and psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of genes associated with progression of bladder cancer</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have been studying bladder cancer in a mouse model of the disease and we are seeking to understand the molecular features of the mouse models as they relate to human bladder cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficient representations and prediction of multidimensional time series data</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-efficient-representations-and-prediction-of-multidimensional-time-series-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-efficient-representations-and-prediction-of-multidimensional-time-series-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Big data with temporal dependence brings unique challenges in effective prediction and data analysis. The complex high-dimensional interactions between observations in such data brings unique challenges which standard off-the-shelf machine learning algorithms cannot handle. Even basic tasks of clustering, visualization and identification of recurring patterns are difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining The Synergistic Effects Of Cannabis And Prescription Opioid Policies On Chronic Pain, Opioid Prescribing, And Opioid Overdose</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-examining-the-synergistic-effects-of-cannabis-and-prescription-opioid-policies-on-chronic-pain-opioid-prescribing-and-opioid-overdose/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-examining-the-synergistic-effects-of-cannabis-and-prescription-opioid-policies-on-chronic-pain-opioid-prescribing-and-opioid-overdose/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The funded study examines policies that regulate the PO supply, including those related to prescription drug monitoring programs, pain management clinic laws, and prescribing limits. In this supplement, we add a set of complementary opioid policies that affect access to treatment for opioid use disorder (e.g., Medicaid coverage of medication for opioid use disorder). Two challenges emerge when studying the impact of PO policies: (1) the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heating Decarbonization Model Data Visualization and Analysis</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-heating-decarbonization-model-data-visualization-and-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-heating-decarbonization-model-data-visualization-and-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Quadracci Sustainable Engineering Lab (qSEL) has several research efforts related to the low-carbon energy transition, including pathways to decarbonize building space heating. Recent work has produced large model data sets that have supported recent journal articles. Several maps have been produced using QGIS and data has been made public, but user functionality is limited. While we continue to build on these efforts, we also want to make our results and data available more widely for other researchers and policymakers. The large data sets (10 years of hourly data for more than 72,000 census tracts and six scenarios) and different spatial aggregations (e.g. states and electricity planning/operating regions) present challenges. In this project, the DSI Scholar would first work with qSEL researchers to develop an interactive web interface to display maps of relevant analyses and allow users to produce time series data from the underlying models. Additional research would include further analysis at a regional level – likely New York State – to refine the current model based on additional intraregional and energy source data. The project has the possibility of extending through Summer 2020, subject to fundraising efforts and the success of the Spring 2020 project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Quality Video Streaming over Wireless</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-high-quality-video-streaming-over-wireless/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-high-quality-video-streaming-over-wireless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The amount of video content that is being distributed over the Internet is increasing. Video providers rely on HTTP adaptive streaming approaches to deliver video clips to users. Complementary to the video provider, the service provider must determine the priority of each network stream. As part of the project, students will explore wireless network assisted strategies for http adaptive streaming by use of TOS/DSCP. This includes using machine-learning tools to analyze network video traffic and the design of reinforcement learning algorithms to improve users&amp;rsquo;  video Quality of Experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying disease subtypes by comorbidity clustering using structured data from electronic health records</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-identifying-disease-subtypes-by-comorbidity-clustering-using-structured-data-from-electronic-health-records/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-identifying-disease-subtypes-by-comorbidity-clustering-using-structured-data-from-electronic-health-records/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major challenge to implementing precision medicine arises from patients who share a clinical diagnosis but have different biological causes of disease. Disease subtypes that arise from obscure etiological heterogeneity create inefficiencies in healthcare and attenuate power in clinical trials and research studies. The ability to stratify patients into biologically homogenous subgroups improves the potential for translational research by allowing us to design more powerful studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusionary Zoning in Paris and New York: Antidote to Gentrification or Trojan&#39;s Horse?</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-inclusionary-zoning-in-paris-and-new-york-antidote-to-gentrification-or-trojans-horse/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-inclusionary-zoning-in-paris-and-new-york-antidote-to-gentrification-or-trojans-horse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The research project examines how Inclusionary Zoning (IZ) impacts the housing markets of neighborhoods where it is implemented. The study focuses on the impacts of IZ in New York City and Paris, two cities at the forefront of adopting IZ in their respective countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of past brain state on future perception</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-influence-of-past-brain-state-on-future-perception/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-influence-of-past-brain-state-on-future-perception/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are constantly exposed to inputs from the outside world, but we do not perceive everything we are exposed to. Some inputs are rather weak: we might perceive them at one point in time, but not at another. The state of our brains right before we receive such sensory inputs influences whether or not we perceive them. Brain oscillations are proposed to play a key role in setting these brain states; however, how exactly these brain rhythms influence our perception remains a topic of active research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linking State Medicaid and Clinical Registry Data to Assess Long-Term Outcomes for Children with Congenital Heart Disease</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-linking-state-medicaid-and-clinical-registry-data-to-assess-long-term-outcomes-for-children-with-congenital-heart-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-linking-state-medicaid-and-clinical-registry-data-to-assess-long-term-outcomes-for-children-with-congenital-heart-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Scholars would assist with Aim 1 of a new R01 working with our lab and the Health Evaluation and Analytics Laboratory at NYU Wagner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congenital heart defects (CHDs) are the most common and resource intensive birth defects managed in the United States (US), affecting ~40,000 births per year in the US.1  One-year mortality for these children is &amp;gt;10%.  It is &amp;gt;30% for children requiring neonatal surgery.2  Yet there are currently limited data on long-term outcomes and health expenditures for these children.  Due to marked heterogeneity in disease subtypes and treatments among CHD patients, the power of single-center studies is limited.  Multi-center data are siloed in diagnostic or procedural registries or in-patient databases, or are the product of individual investigations.11  Administrative data may lack clinical precision, as ICD codes for this population are not based on physiology.  Further, data on costs and value typically rely on cost-to-charge ratio based costs, which are highly influenced by hospital accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Tax Evasion using Twitter Feeds</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-measuring-tax-evasion-using-twitter-feeds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-measuring-tax-evasion-using-twitter-feeds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tax evasion is one of the main sources of informal economic activity and has drastic effects on different macroeconomic variables. However, due to various reasons, it is difficult to directly measure the extent of tax evasion. This project aims to develop a novel way of measuring aggregate tax evasion in national economies using Twitter feeds. To this end, using carefully selected keywords in different national languages, we will collect country and regional level data from Twitter feeds in different frequencies for a large cross section of economies and then construct a measure of tax evasion using the collected data. In addition to fully describing the collected dataset, the project will also examine the evolution of the constructed series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single cell RNA-seq analysis of eye development and disease</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-single-cell-rna-seq-analysis-of-eye-development-and-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-single-cell-rna-seq-analysis-of-eye-development-and-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Single cell sequencing has generated unprecedented insight into the cellular complexity of normal and diseased organ. We are interested in using this technique to understand the mechanisms of eye development, disease and regeneration. We also would like to compare the transcriptomic signatures between mouse models and human tissues. This project involves analysis of large amount of data from single cell sequencing. It requires understanding of statistical analysis and proficient programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analyses of Siamese fighting fish aggressive behavior</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-statistical-analyses-of-siamese-fighting-fish-aggressive-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-statistical-analyses-of-siamese-fighting-fish-aggressive-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Project: analyze behavior of Siamese fighting fish (Betta splendens) as part of a collaboration between the Bendesky and Cunningham labs of the Zuckerman Institute (NeuroTheory Center)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Superior Longitudinal Fasciculi abnormalities associated with the attentional deficit in schizophrenia</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-superior-longitudinal-fasciculi-abnormalities-associated-with-the-attentional-deficit-in-schizophrenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-superior-longitudinal-fasciculi-abnormalities-associated-with-the-attentional-deficit-in-schizophrenia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Individuals with schizophrenia shows a wide range of cognitive deficits, and lack in the ability to control the variety of inputs (whether internal or external) to create a unitary “self”. This problem has been often associated with a supramodal attentional deficit, but its causes are yet unknown. In the past twenty years, the quest to identify brain regions or networks showing abnormal functioning in schizophrenia has been unproductive; but one question is left unanswered: is it possible that it is the white matter tracts supporting attention (i.e., the superior longitudinal fasciculi I, II, and III) to be compromised in this psychiatric disorder? The present project will attempt to dissect the fronto-parietal branches with DTI by analyzing over 400 images from the Open Access SchizConnect.Org repository (data already available to the PI). Funds will be used to support the work of a junior or senior-year undergraduate student (possibly from URMs) to conduct the data analysis during the summer of AY2020. Results will be made available with the scientific community and published in open access peer-review journals (e.g.,  Schizophrenia Research). Co-mentoring of the undergraduate student will be done by Dr. Henrietta Howells (&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.it/citations?user=nudmODkAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;oi=ao&#34;&gt;https://scholar.google.it/citations?user=nudmODkAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;oi=ao&lt;/a&gt;), opening the student to an international collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Evolution of the Smallest Galaxies in the Universe</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-the-evolution-of-the-smallest-galaxies-in-the-universe/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-the-evolution-of-the-smallest-galaxies-in-the-universe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Milky Way swarms with orbiting satellite dwarf galaxies of astounding diversity. Some galaxies continue to form stars while others stop and dim in brightness. In computer simulations, the evolutionary history of each dwarf galaxy that leads to these differences is known. Galaxies can lose gas and stop forming stars due to early exposure to stellar radiation (reionization), interaction with the hot gas of the host (ram-pressure stripping), or gravitational interactions with the host/dwarf galaxies (tidal effects).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Urban Lead Atlas</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-the-urban-lead-atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-the-urban-lead-atlas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Urban Lead Atlas is a collaborative community-based research initiative to create the nations’ first crowd-sourced open online map identifying toxic lead hazards located within the homes, schools, landscape, and lead service lines for water in American cities. The project will begin by integrating data from a small set of cities – New York, Philadelphia, Washington D.C. and Newark -  including housing enforcement and lead service line datasets, data on lead dust in schools, and the results of soil lead tests in parks and backyards, on the websites of Columbia University’s Center for Sustainable Urban Development. Ultimately, the goal of the Urban Lead Atlas is to create and populate a fully open online platform that is capable of integrating data from “citizen scientists” and residents regarding the sites of lead hazards in their city’s environment and buildings. This research is important, as experts estimate that over nine million US children have lead blood levels which may cause sub-clinical effects and permanent adverse health, cognitive, and behavior outcomes. The Lead Atlas is intended as the first model for a national effort, the American Lead Atlas project, which seeks to create a national online collaborative map of lead hazards within American cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using machine learning and topology to phenotype mouse behavior</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-using-machine-learning-and-topology-to-phenotype-mouse-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-using-machine-learning-and-topology-to-phenotype-mouse-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A central issue facing systems neuroscience is defining the rich naturalistic behavioral repertoire that mice engage in under psychiatrically relevant situations. Recent advances in deep learning (e.g., DeepLabCut) have made frame by frame detailed pose estimation possible. However, this dense behavioral data requires new techniques for defining the ethogram (full description of behavior). To date, researchers have used frequency based time series approaches to tackle this problem, with significant limitations. An alternative approach would be to take advantage of new topology methods (persistent homology and directed algebraic topology) to characterize the shapes formed by mouse limb trajectories. Such an approach would have broad application in systems neuroscience. For this project, the student will use machine learning to label animal body parts, then topology to characterize the ethogram and compare the results to existing approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Faculty Participation --- DSI Scholars Spring-Summer 2020</title>
      <link>/2019/12/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;call-for-faculty-participation-december-2019&#34;&gt;Call for Faculty Participation. December 2019.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Institute is pleased to call for Faculty Participation in the Spring and/or Summer 2020 sessions of the 3rd cohort of Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage undergraduate and master students to work with Columbia faculty, through a data science research internship. Last year, we worked with 47 projects and received more than 400 unique applications from Columbia Students. The program’s unique enrichment activities will foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>