<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nlp on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/nlp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nlp on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/nlp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Classifying drug patents</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-classifying-drug-patents/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-classifying-drug-patents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Taking out multiple patents on different aspects of a drug in order to cordon off competitors is standard practice in pharmaceuticals. In addition to primary patents, firms commonly attempt to acquire secondary patents on alternative forms of molecules, different formulations, dosages, and compositions, and new uses Policymakers in the U.S. and globally have raised concerns that these secondary patents can raise drug prices and restrict access to medicines. One challenge to assessing the impact of these patents is it is difficult and costly to know if a given patent is &amp;ldquo;primary&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;secondary.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: ArXivLab: A Platform for Developing and Evaluating Exploratory Tools for the Scientific Literature</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-arxivlab-a-platform-for-developing-and-evaluating-exploratory-tools-for-the-scientific-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-arxivlab-a-platform-for-developing-and-evaluating-exploratory-tools-for-the-scientific-literature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Through ArXivLab we aim to develop the next generation recommender systems for the scientific literature using statistical machine learning approaches. In collaboration with ArXiv we are currently developing a new scholarly literature browser which will be able to extract knowledge implicit in the mathematical and scientific literature, offer advanced mathematical search capabilities and provide personalized recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Measuring Liberal Arts: Creating an Index for Higher Education</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project works with a novel corpus of text-based school data to develop a multi-dimensional measure of the degree to which American colleges and universities offer a liberal arts education. We seek a data scientist for various tasks on a project that uses analysis of multiple text corpora to better understand the liberal arts. This is an ongoing three-year project with opportunities for future collaborations, academic publications, and developing and improving existing data science and machine learning skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Project ToxicDocs</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-project-toxicdocs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-project-toxicdocs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We house the world&amp;rsquo;s largest dataset of once-secret documents on industrial pollution, unleashed from the vaults of corporations like DuPont, Dow, and Monsanto in toxic tort litigation. We are applying data science methods to analyze and render this material useable to a broad audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data Science and the regulation of financial markets (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The development of computational data science
techniques in natural language processing (NLP) and machine
learning (ML) algorithms to analyze large and complex textual
information opens new avenues to study intricate processes,
such as government regulation of financial markets, at a scale
unimaginable even a few years ago. This project develops scalable
NLP and ML algorithms (classification, clustering and
ranking methods) that automatically classify laws into various
codes/labels, rank feature sets based on use case, and induce
best structured representation of sentences for various types of
computational analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>