<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Fall 2021 on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/categories/open-fall-2021/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Fall 2021 on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/open-fall-2021/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>@Dear Pandemic, a social media-based science communication project targeting the COVID-19 infodemic</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-dear-pandemic-a-social-media-based-science-communication-project-targeting-the-covid-19-infodemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-dear-pandemic-a-social-media-based-science-communication-project-targeting-the-covid-19-infodemic/</guid>
=======
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/open-fall-2021/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>@Dear Pandemic, a social media-based science communication project targeting the COVID-19 infodemic</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-dear-pandemic-a-social-media-based-science-communication-project-targeting-the-covid-19-infodemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-dear-pandemic-a-social-media-based-science-communication-project-targeting-the-covid-19-infodemic/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The WHO has identified scientific misinformation as a public health crisis, calling it an “infodemic.” Social media allows misinformation to spread quickly and out-compete scientifically grounded information. Dear Pandemic is an innovative, multidisciplinary, social media-based science communication project led by women scientists across several institutions around the US and the UK. The mission is to educate and empower individuals to successfully navigate the overwhelming amount of information. The goals are: 1) To disseminate trustworthy, comprehensive, and timely scientific content about the pandemic to lay audiences, and 2) To promote media and health literacy, equipping readers to better manage the COVID-19 infodemic within their own networks. More than one year after launch, the project has a combined monthly reach of &amp;gt; 5 million people across 4 social media channels (2 Facebook pages in English and Spanish; Instagram; and Twitter).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A traffic map for the Internet</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-a-traffic-map-for-the-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-a-traffic-map-for-the-internet/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-a-traffic-map-for-the-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-a-traffic-map-for-the-internet/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The impact of an outage, congestion, hijacking, and many other Internet phenomena depends on how many users or how much traffic use the route, but researchers lack visibility into how important routes are, and, distressingly, seem to have lost hope of obtaining this information without proprietary datasets or privileged viewpoints. We believe that there is hope &amp;ndash; new measurement methods and changes in Internet structure make it possible to construct an “Internet Traffic Map” identifying the locations (logical and perhaps geographical) of Internet users and major services, the paths between users and major services, and the relative activity levels (traffic, queries, or number of users) routed along these paths. We will construct this map. The realization of an Internet Traffic Map will be an Internet-scale effort that will have Internet-scale consequences that reach far beyond the research community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Associations between specific antibiotic classes and risk for Clostridioides difficile infection within the MarketScan database</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-associations-between-specific-antibiotic-classes-and-risk-for-clostridioides-difficile-infection-within-the-marketscan-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-associations-between-specific-antibiotic-classes-and-risk-for-clostridioides-difficile-infection-within-the-marketscan-database/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-associations-between-specific-antibiotic-classes-and-risk-for-clostridioides-difficile-infection-within-the-marketscan-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-associations-between-specific-antibiotic-classes-and-risk-for-clostridioides-difficile-infection-within-the-marketscan-database/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Clostridioides difficile infection (CDI) is highly associated with antibiotic exposure, but it is uncertain which classes of antibiotics confer the greatest risk for CDI.  This project will use the MarketScan database, a large commercial insurance billing database containing 40 million patient records, outpatient antibiotic prescription data, and ICD-based disease information, to test for associations between specific antibiotic classes and risk for CDI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biomarker discovery for cancer immunotherapy</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Immune checkpoint blockade therapy has shown successful clinical outcomes in the treatment of various solid tumors such as head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC), melanoma, non- small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) and others. However, immune checkpoint inhibitors work best in patients who exhibit certain tumor biomarkers. In a collaboration with the Department of Hematology Oncology, the Department of Systems Biology, and the Mailman School of Public Health at Columbia University we aim to identify biomarkers which are associated with treatment outcome in patients with solid tumors who underwent immunotherapy. The project includes bioinformatic analysis of sequencing data. Mentoring and training will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <title>Blockchain Prediction Platform &amp; DeFi Applications</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-blockchain-prediction-platform-defi-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-blockchain-prediction-platform-defi-applications/</guid>
=======
      <title>Blockchain Prediction Platform and DeFi Applications</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-blockchain-prediction-platform-and-defi-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-blockchain-prediction-platform-and-defi-applications/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are 2 projects under consideration- the first one is well underway.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Body composition and cardiovascular health among women</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-body-composition-and-cardiovascular-health-among-women/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-body-composition-and-cardiovascular-health-among-women/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-body-composition-and-cardiovascular-health-among-women/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-body-composition-and-cardiovascular-health-among-women/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We would like a student to assist with conducting linear and logistic regression analyses using SAS, along with preparing charts, tables, and graphs of the data from our prospective cohort study.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chemical and genomic approaches to restore MHC expression in cancer</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-chemical-and-genomic-approaches-to-restore-mhc-expression-in-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-chemical-and-genomic-approaches-to-restore-mhc-expression-in-cancer/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-chemical-and-genomic-approaches-to-restore-mhc-expression-in-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-chemical-and-genomic-approaches-to-restore-mhc-expression-in-cancer/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Small molecule modulators have been transformative in immune-oncology, revealing the functional role of numerous immune pathways. The current paradigm for immunotherapy, however, excludes cancers such as PDA where MHC-I is not effectively expressed at the membrane. In this application, we combine an innovative chemical proteomic screening platform with genome wide CRISPR screening in advanced PDA models. The lead compounds and protein targets discovered herein should provide launching points for drug development programs to remove PDA’s cloak of invisibility from the immune system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complex genome rearrangements in a unicellular model organism</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-complex-genome-rearrangements-in-a-unicellular-model-organism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-complex-genome-rearrangements-in-a-unicellular-model-organism/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-complex-genome-rearrangements-in-a-unicellular-model-organism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-complex-genome-rearrangements-in-a-unicellular-model-organism/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Landweber Lab is looking for a computational student to work with us to analyze long-read DNA sequence datasets from Oxford Nanopore and PacBio (so-called third generation sequencing platforms). These datasets were collected across a time-course while single cells of the genus Oxytricha are undergoing RNA-guided natural genome editing. This process leads to a completely different &amp;ldquo;output&amp;rdquo; product genome from the precursor &amp;ldquo;input&amp;rdquo; or germline genome, and has been compared to a cellular computer. The goal will be to capture and classify long reads in these DNA datasets that represent the intermediate steps in genome rearrangements, when chromosomes mix and match hundreds of thousands of precursor building blocks to assemble a mature genome of 18,000 new chromosomes during programmed nuclear development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 Evidence Retrieval and Synthesis Using PubMed Abstracts</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-covid-19-evidence-retrieval-and-synthesis-using-pubmed-abstracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-covid-19-evidence-retrieval-and-synthesis-using-pubmed-abstracts/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-covid-19-evidence-retrieval-and-synthesis-using-pubmed-abstracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-covid-19-evidence-retrieval-and-synthesis-using-pubmed-abstracts/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Evidence-based Medicine (EBM) is the conscientious, explicit and judicious use of current best evidence in making decisions about the care of individual patients. The key difference between evidence-based medicine and traditional medicine is not that EBM considers the evidence while the latter does not, but rather that EBM demands better evidence. Given the exponential growth of the medical literature and the free text format of this big body of literature that hampers efficient evidence computing, researchers, patients and clinicians face significant challenges in evidence retrieval, appraisal, and synthesis. Our long-term goal is to develop natural language processing and text summarization methods to overcome these challenges. Our short-term goal is to build a computable evidence base for COVID-19 and to enable evidence synthesis and reasoning over COVID-19 study findings. Currently we have a database of structured data elements for PubMed abstracts for randomized controlled trials published within the past 20 years. For this scholar project, we expect the participating students to develop methods to analyze the evidence in our evidence base, to build COVID-19 knowledge graphs, and to enable evidence synthesis and appraisal at scale. On this basis, we will also compare the evidence in the literature to the evidence derived from the real world data of COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <title>Data For Good: The Cost of Human Rights Violations</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-dfg-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-dfg-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</guid>
=======
      <title>Data For Good: Poverty Research Cartagena</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-dfg-poverty-research-cartagena/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-dfg-poverty-research-cartagena/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is an exciting opportunity to work with FEM, a non-profit that aims to address social rights issues among rural communities in Colombia. The team is currently working with the mayor’s office in Cartagena, Colombia to access multiple datasets and data sources to establish who and where the extreme poor in Cartagena live. Her team piloted a smartphone-based collection strategy during IOTA Hurricane and obtained data on 4845 households in a very vulnerable area. The first data science challenge was to wrangle and analyze these data to better characterize the population and their needs. This part of the project was conducted in the Spring and Summer of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: The Cost of Human Rights Violations</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-dfg-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-dfg-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rights CoLab is working with the Sustainability Accounting Standards Board (SASB) to define a strengthened set of disclosure standards that investors can use to persuade companies to improve labor rights for both their workforce and workers in supply chains. The project has two components: 1) a data science project, and 2) an Expert Group.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Facial Asymmetry using Computer Vision for Detection of Ischemic Stroke</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-detection-of-facial-asymmetry-using-computer-vision-for-detection-of-ischemic-stroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-detection-of-facial-asymmetry-using-computer-vision-for-detection-of-ischemic-stroke/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-detection-of-facial-asymmetry-using-computer-vision-for-detection-of-ischemic-stroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-detection-of-facial-asymmetry-using-computer-vision-for-detection-of-ischemic-stroke/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stroke is devastating when left untreated. Early treatment significantly improves outcomes, and can be reliably detected using the FAST exam, which specifically assesses facial asymmetry, arm weakness, and speech deficits for signs of stroke. Our project aims to use smartphone technology to build a stroke detection algorithm based on this exam. We have collected video data of hospitalized stroke patients performing aspects of the standard neurology exam, which includes the factors previously mentioned. The next step is to build an algorithm that can detect facial asymmetry using this data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Speech Deficits for Detection of Ischemic Stroke</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-detection-of-speech-deficits-for-detection-of-ischemic-stroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-detection-of-speech-deficits-for-detection-of-ischemic-stroke/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-detection-of-speech-deficits-for-detection-of-ischemic-stroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-detection-of-speech-deficits-for-detection-of-ischemic-stroke/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stroke is devastating when left untreated. Early treatment significantly improves outcomes, and can be reliably detected using the FAST exam. The exam looks for facial asymmetry, arm weakness, and speech deficits as signs of stroke. Our research project aims to use smartphone technology to build a stroke detection algorithm based on the FAST exam. We have collected speech data of hospitalized stroke patients. The next step is to build an algorithm that can detect abnormal speech.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovery and rescue of rare sperm cell from semen samples</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-discovery-and-rescue-of-rare-sperm-cell-from-semen-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-discovery-and-rescue-of-rare-sperm-cell-from-semen-samples/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-discovery-and-rescue-of-rare-sperm-cell-from-semen-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-discovery-and-rescue-of-rare-sperm-cell-from-semen-samples/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While an normal semen sample contains hundreds of millions of sperm, men with azospermia have no sperm seen and azospermia represents an important cause of infertility. Men with azospermia typically have to use donor sperm in order to have a child.  However, extended manual search of semen samples in men with azospermia reveal single-digit numbers of sperm in ~80% of cases. These few sperm are sufficient to fertility eggs in the IVF lab and allow the men to be biological fathers.  Unfortunately, the manual search for sperm is only performed in a couple of sites in the world because of the enormous cost associated with having a specially trained andrologist search a sperm sample for roughly 8 hours. In this project, we aim to apply the semen sample to the custom designed microfluidics chip at a fixed flow rate. Next, several thousands of images will be captured at frame rate ranging between 4,000-40,000 fps using a high definition microscope camera as the sample flows through the microfluidics device. We will then build a training dataset of images with and without the rare cells of interest. These training datasets will be used to build an artificial intelligence (AI) model with high accuracy to detect rare cells of interest. The model will be tested for its accuracy on the ‘true’ sample containing rare cells. The Data Science Institute Scholar is expected to have basic programming skills (preferably in Python). Thus, if successful, there will literally be countless babies born as a result of this project.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Timing and Compliance of Arginine-Supplemented Immunonutrition on Surgical Outcomes for Major Cancer Operations</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-effects-of-timing-and-compliance-of-arginine-supplemented-immunonutrition-on-surgical-outcomes-for-major-cancer-operations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-effects-of-timing-and-compliance-of-arginine-supplemented-immunonutrition-on-surgical-outcomes-for-major-cancer-operations/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-effects-of-timing-and-compliance-of-arginine-supplemented-immunonutrition-on-surgical-outcomes-for-major-cancer-operations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-effects-of-timing-and-compliance-of-arginine-supplemented-immunonutrition-on-surgical-outcomes-for-major-cancer-operations/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We performed a prospective, non-randomized trial of patients undergoing surgical management of gastrointestinal, gynecologic, and urologic malignancies between 2017 and 2021 . Participants were instructed to take immunonutrition formula three times daily for five days before and after surgery once cleared by the surgeon for clear liquid diet. The dietician tracked their adherence. We are looking to perform statistical analysis to look at the impact of immunonutrition intake on unadjusted and adjusted postoperative surgical outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the impact of telemedicine on chronic disease outcomes</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-evaluating-the-impact-of-telemedicine-on-chronic-disease-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-evaluating-the-impact-of-telemedicine-on-chronic-disease-outcomes/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-evaluating-the-impact-of-telemedicine-on-chronic-disease-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-evaluating-the-impact-of-telemedicine-on-chronic-disease-outcomes/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Center for Behavioral Cardiovascular Health has been at the forefront of developing virtual interventions (e.g., home BP telemonitoring, iHeart enhanced depression screening app, and COVID remote care program) to improve the management of hypertension, depression, and COVID. We are looking for motivated mentees to help us organize and analyze a wide-breadth of patient data from the Columbia-New York Presbyterian data warehouse to understand the impact of the interventions on patient outcomes. The mentee would work alongside highly experienced biostatisticians and our Center&amp;rsquo;s professionalized data team managers. The mentee will develop expertise in analyzing health system data and will inform decisions to modify, sustain, or de-implement existing programs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring unsupervised learning methods to phenotype sleep disturbance patterns in marginalized adults</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-exploring-unsupervised-learning-methods-to-phenotype-sleep-disturbance-patterns-in-marginalized-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-exploring-unsupervised-learning-methods-to-phenotype-sleep-disturbance-patterns-in-marginalized-adults/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-exploring-unsupervised-learning-methods-to-phenotype-sleep-disturbance-patterns-in-marginalized-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-exploring-unsupervised-learning-methods-to-phenotype-sleep-disturbance-patterns-in-marginalized-adults/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The aims of this project are two-fold. We seek to: 1) better understand the associations of discrimination with sleep and cardiovascular health among LGBTQ+ adults, and 2) compare various unsupervised learning techniques on their performance on clustering sleep patterns using actigraphy data. We have multiple datasets for conducting our analyses to delineate the pattern of associations between sleep and other variables. We will also explore various modeling techniques to quantify the within- and between-person variability in sleep patterns. We aim to complete multiple analyses in the Fall and Spring semesters to develop conference abstracts and manuscripts to be submitted in Spring 2022. Since our DSI seed grant is still ongoing, during the Fall semester the Scholar will work on data wrangling and analyses, in addition to data management from existing data collected from our Precision in Symptom Self-Management pilot studies. In January 2022, we will begin analyzing data from our DSI seed grant. We hope to collaborate with a student who is interested in machine learning, sleep, and/or health disparities. The Scholar will have the opportunity to contribute to all of these aspects of the project. The Scholar will also be able to propose and lead additional analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freedom School Workshops at the Malcolm X &amp; Dr. Betty Shabazz Center</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-freedom-school-workshops-at-the-malcolm-x-dr.-betty-shabazz-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-freedom-school-workshops-at-the-malcolm-x-dr.-betty-shabazz-center/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-freedom-school-workshops-at-the-malcolmx-and-dr-betty-shabazz-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-freedom-school-workshops-at-the-malcolmx-and-dr-betty-shabazz-center/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is a collaboration between Columbia scholars and students and leadership at the Malcolm X  &amp;amp; Dr. Betty Shabazz Center. The goal is to create programming and intellectual resources inspired by the legacy of Dr. Shabazz and Malcolm X through public events, workshops and data science activities. Part of this work will involve using computational methods to analyze existing publications around Malcolm X&amp;rsquo;s work, as well as develop a corpus of research materials by effectively digitizing the contents of the publicly-available FBI files about his life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <title>Identification of gene networks regulated by the  ASD risk gene CHD8</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-identification-of-gene-networks-regulated-by-the-asd-risk-gene-chd8/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-identification-of-gene-networks-regulated-by-the-asd-risk-gene-chd8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The focus of our research is on autism spectrum disorder (ASD) and the neural pathways, neurodevelopment, and genes implicated in ASD.  We will be focusing on the gene CHD8, which is a regulatory gene expressed in the early fetal brain. The aim of this research is to map CHD8 cell-type specific networks in the cortex.  We will be using chromatin immunoprecipitation followed by sequencing (bioChIP-seq) to identify the cell type and lineage specific regulatory networks controlled by CHD8 that are critical for neurodevelopment and ASD risk.  We will perform bioChIP-seq using an epitope-tagged Chd8-3XFLAG-Avi transgenic mouse by crossing the mouse with a conditionally activated biotin ligase called BirA to generate mouse line Chd8-3XFLAG-Avi; neo-BirA. This mouse can be crossed with Cre driver lines to activate biotinylation of tagged Chd8 in specific cell types. Following bioChIP-seq, we will use the program HOMER to determine statistically significant target sites found in CHD8-3XFLAG-Avi-Biotin complexes in comparison with bioChIP-seq performed using non-biotinylated tagged Chd8.  The identified peaks will then be matched to genes and this data will be used to generate a cell-type specific regulatory network of genes and enhancers bound by Chd8 that will be assessed for additional genetic risk factors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
=======
      <title>Health Behaviors and Cardiovascular Risk</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-health-behaviors-and-cardiovascular-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-health-behaviors-and-cardiovascular-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project will include conducting analyses on lifestyle behaviors, namely diet and sleep, in relation to cardiovascular health. Analyses will be completed within NHANES (National Health and Nutrition Examination Surveys). Analyses will also be completed using data from a 24/7 sleep and activity tracker in relation to blood pressure. The student will contribute to data management and statistical analyses and will be a co-author on manuscripts submitted for publication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the effects of pre- and post-natal exposures and trajectories of maternal depression in shaping long-term health outcomes</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-investigating-the-effects-of-pre-and-post-natal-exposures-and-trajectories-of-maternal-depression-in-shaping-long-term-health-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-investigating-the-effects-of-pre-and-post-natal-exposures-and-trajectories-of-maternal-depression-in-shaping-long-term-health-outcomes/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-investigating-the-effects-of-pre-and-post-natal-exposures-and-trajectories-of-maternal-depression-in-shaping-long-term-health-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-investigating-the-effects-of-pre-and-post-natal-exposures-and-trajectories-of-maternal-depression-in-shaping-long-term-health-outcomes/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the effects of environmental exposures on child health and development is crucial to promote positive health outcomes in adulthood. To advance knowledge in this area, our lab is part of the NIH-funded Environmental influences on Child Health Outcomes (ECHO) Program. As of April 2021, the cohorts have collected data from over 90,000 participants which includes over 57,000 children. The selected student(s) will be involved in projects investigating the relationship between a variety of prenatal and postnatal exposures and physiological variables. Specifically, we aim to build multidimensional associative and predictive models to investigate the effects of prenatal maternal drinking and smoking on development of cardiac and neural systems non-invasively assessed at 4-, 5-, 7-, 9- and 11-years of age. We will advance prior work on the relationship of maternal depression and child development by including depression measures at 1 and 4 years post-delivery and prospective assessment of multiple domains of child development and applying machine learning methods for trajectory identification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning and causal inference for traffic safety assessment</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-machine-learning-and-causal-inference-for-traffic-safety-assessment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-machine-learning-and-causal-inference-for-traffic-safety-assessment/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-machine-learning-and-causal-inference-for-traffic-safety-assessment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-machine-learning-and-causal-inference-for-traffic-safety-assessment/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traffic safety has become an emerging issue in the city of New York since the pandemic. This project aims to use causal inference methods to investigate how traffic safety countermeasures (including adding more bike lanes) that have been deployed by the city affect traffic fatalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <title>Mapping NYPD Subway Fare Evasion Enforcement</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-mapping-nypd-subway-fare-evasion-enforcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-mapping-nypd-subway-fare-evasion-enforcement/</guid>
=======
      <title>Mapping and disrupting business email compromise criminal networks</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-mapping-and-disrupting-business-email-compromise-criminal-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-mapping-and-disrupting-business-email-compromise-criminal-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Business email compromise (BEC) is a prevalent cyber attack, where the attacker impersonates a figure of authority or legitimacy (e.g., the CEO, a business associate), and asks the target to wire money to a bank account by the attacker. Based on FBI estimates, in the past several years, attackers have been able to steal over $22B in fraudulent wire transfers. Such attacks have affected a very wide range of individuals and institutions, from the world&amp;rsquo;s largest and most sophisticated companies (e.g., Google, Facebook), to government and public entities, and even individuals whose house down payment was stolen by an attacker pretending to be their mortgage broker.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping NYPD Subway Fare Evasion Enforcement</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-mapping-nypd-subway-fare-evasion-enforcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-mapping-nypd-subway-fare-evasion-enforcement/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is the next phase in ongoing research to document how the MTA and NYPD use public resources to criminalize poverty at the subway turnstile, especially in Black and Brown communities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <title>Multi-class probabilistic clustering of the human gut microbiome</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-multi-class-probabilistic-clustering-of-the-human-gut-microbiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-multi-class-probabilistic-clustering-of-the-human-gut-microbiome/</guid>
=======
      <title>Meta-analysis of single-cell genomic data to define cellular heterogeneity and dynamics in atherosclerotic vasculature</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-meta-analysis-of-single-cell-genomic-data-to-define-cellular-heterogeneity-and-dynamics-in-atherosclerotic-vasculature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-meta-analysis-of-single-cell-genomic-data-to-define-cellular-heterogeneity-and-dynamics-in-atherosclerotic-vasculature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Atherosclerosis, a chronic inflammatory disease of the artery wall, is the underlying cause of human coronary heart diseases. Single-cell genomics have catalyzed the revolution in understanding of cellular heterogeneity and dynamics in atherosclerotic vasculature. The goal of the project is to leverage published and our own single-cell genomic data and perform a meta-analysis. Meta-analysis allows integrated analysis of much larger cell numbers and helps resolve the full spectrum of cellular heterogeneity and dynamics in atherosclerotic vessels and facilitate therapeutic translation. The DSI scholar will: (1) use the latest bioinformatic pipeline to integrate the existing scRNA-seq, CITE-seq, and scATAC-seq datasets; (2) analyze the integrated datasets using R/Bioconductor packages (e.g. Seurat); (3) interpret the data using pathway and network analysis. Some relevant workflows are available through the &amp;ldquo;Resources&amp;rdquo; page of our lab website at &lt;a href=&#34;https://hanruizhang.github.io/zhanglab/&#34;&gt;https://hanruizhang.github.io/zhanglab/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-class probabilistic clustering of the human gut microbiome</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-multi-class-probabilistic-clustering-of-the-human-gut-microbiome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-multi-class-probabilistic-clustering-of-the-human-gut-microbiome/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the structure and function of the human gut microbiome is expected to revolutionize healthcare due to its many associations with human disease. A critical step in microbiome analysis involves a clustering stage, where genomic sequences of unknown origin are assigned to latent genomes present in the sample. Current clustering methods rely on mixture-models, yet these fail to correctly model the features of genomic sequences shared across multiple genomes. These sequences are of great importance, often encoding antibiotic resistance genes that drive resistant outbreaks. This project&amp;rsquo;s goal is to develop a clustering algorithm that will effectively cluster both shared and unique genomic sequences. We have developed two probabilistic models, both based around hierarchical Poisson factorization, that have already produced promising results. The project&amp;rsquo;s goal will be to refine these models: This will involve robustly evaluating the current models, determining their limitations, and designing new models that improve upon the current. A successful project will enable for the first time, scalable, and comprehensive reconstruction of bacterial genomes. In turn, this will enable a large-scale analysis of antimicrobial resistance in the context of the human gut microbiome. We anticipate a successful project to result in an exciting publication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Natural Language Processing of social media data on COVID-19 travel pattern analysis</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-natural-language-processing-of-social-media-data-on-covid-19-travel-pattern-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-natural-language-processing-of-social-media-data-on-covid-19-travel-pattern-analysis/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-natural-language-processing-of-social-media-data-on-covid-19-travel-pattern-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-natural-language-processing-of-social-media-data-on-covid-19-travel-pattern-analysis/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has transformed people’s lives in every aspect. Travel patterns and work patterns are also changed. This project aims to leverage social media data (e.g., tweets, facebook posts, Reddit posts) to mine people’s travel patterns and the timeline of telecommute using Natural Language Processing (NLP). Research questions are:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting gene expression from sequencing in Alzheimers Disease</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-predicting-gene-expression-from-sequencing-in-alzheimers-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-predicting-gene-expression-from-sequencing-in-alzheimers-disease/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-predicting-gene-expression-from-sequencing-in-alzheimers-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-predicting-gene-expression-from-sequencing-in-alzheimers-disease/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to evaluate algorithms that predict gene expression directly from sequencing data. With the availability of large scale sequencing data in ADSP and progress made in machine learning methods, it is possible to model long range interactions in the DNA sequence to infer intermediate phenotypes such as gene expression. First, we will test a deep learning based method called Enformer that is able to integrate long-range interactions (such as promoter-enhancer interactions) in the genome and predict gene expression from sequence. Using available RNA-sequencing on a small number of samples (e.g. ROSMAP cohort), we will optimize the algorithm to improve accuracy of prediction. Secondly, inferred expression in the ADSP cohorts will be used to test association with Alzheimer’s Disease and related endophenotypes. Finally, we will incorporate datasets that will become available in future such as cell-type specific ATAC-seq and disease-specific gene expression to re-train learning models to improve gene-expression prediction directly from sequencing data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Race, Ethnicity, and Air pollution in COVID-19 Hospitalization OUTcomes (REACH OUT Study)</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-race-ethnicity-and-air-pollution-in-covid-19-hospitalization-outcomes-reach-out-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-race-ethnicity-and-air-pollution-in-covid-19-hospitalization-outcomes-reach-out-study/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-race-ethnicity-and-air-pollution-in-covid-19-hospitalization-outcomes-reach-out-study/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-race-ethnicity-and-air-pollution-in-covid-19-hospitalization-outcomes-reach-out-study/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The REACH OUT study is a multi-institutional collaboration funded by the Health Effects Institute to determine if populations who have been chronically exposed to higher levels of air pollution are at greater risk of severe COVID-19 outcomes. The project will involve working with a harmonized repository of electronic health record data from multiple healthcare institutions in NYC that will be linked at the zip code level to city-wide air pollution data and neighborhood-level census variables. The project aims are:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Randomized algorithms for plasma fusion data analysis</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-randomized-algorithms-for-plasma-fusion-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-randomized-algorithms-for-plasma-fusion-data-analysis/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-randomized-algorithms-for-plasma-fusion-data-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-randomized-algorithms-for-plasma-fusion-data-analysis/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tokamak fusion reactors produce vast amounts of information rich data. Traditional approaches to data analysis struggle to cope with the scale of the data produced. In this project we aim to apply techniques from randomized numerical to beat the curse of dimensionality. Interested students should have a solid understanding of linear algebra, probability, and be happy coding in MATLAB or Python.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement learning for vehicle routing</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-reinforcement-learning-for-vehicle-routing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-reinforcement-learning-for-vehicle-routing/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-reinforcement-learning-for-vehicle-routing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-reinforcement-learning-for-vehicle-routing/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vehicle routing has been extensively studied in optimization problems. With the advance of AI and big data, this project aims to solve vehicle routing problems (VRP) using reinforcement learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <title>The Language of Vaccine Hesitancy on Social Media</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-the-language-of-vaccine-hesitancy-on-social-media/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-the-language-of-vaccine-hesitancy-on-social-media/</guid>
=======
      <title>Representation learning for the identification of bacterial non-coding RNAs</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-representation-learning-for-the-identification-of-bacterial-non-coding-rnas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-representation-learning-for-the-identification-of-bacterial-non-coding-rnas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Computational methods for identifying protein coding genes can leverage the conserved translational mapping of triplet codons to amino acids. However, non-coding genes, that are transcribed into RNAs but do not code for proteins, lack this structure, hindering their identification. Deep neural networks have shown tremendous promise in learning useful representations of unstructured data, including genomic data. Our lab is investigating the application of deep learning and natural language processing to the learning of representations useful for non-coding gene identification in bacterial genomes. We are seeking a student to contribute to this work. The goals of this project include 1) the identification and application of neural network architectures useful for identifying different classes of non-coding RNAs, 2) the interrogation of well-performing models in order to identify features of non-coding RNAs, and 3) the design of robust test cases which enable the comparison of these novel methods to existing methods for non-coding RNA identification in bacterial genomes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spanish-Language Misinformation</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-spanish-language-misinformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-spanish-language-misinformation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I will use Twitter data to assess the popularity and reach of false claims affecting Latinos regarding Covid-19, the 2020 election, and the Biden presidency. I also plan to characterize these data using text analysis methods in order to recover general themes or topics, and how they varied as a function of geography, time, and user characteristics. I have access to the Twitter academic API.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>startup pivoting</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-startup-pivoting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-startup-pivoting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;use data science with historical version of startup websites to identify when do they pivot to new strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Language of Vaccine Hesitancy on Social Media</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-the-language-of-vaccine-hesitancy-on-social-media/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-the-language-of-vaccine-hesitancy-on-social-media/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project seeks to analyze a large corpus of vaccine (dis)information collected online, using NLP and other machine learning tools. Of particular interest is vaccine hesitancy among people of color, immigrant and religious communities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The market for highly-skilled labor: Evidence from professional sports</title>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <link>/2021/09/project-the-market-for-highly-skilled-labor-evidence-from-professional-sports/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-the-market-for-highly-skilled-labor-evidence-from-professional-sports/</guid>
=======
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-the-market-for-highly-skilled-labor-evidence-from-professional-sports/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-the-market-for-highly-skilled-labor-evidence-from-professional-sports/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project, we will study historical player transfer data from European professional football (n &amp;gt; 1,000,000 transfers). To supplement this analysis, we will also exploit data on player and team performance, team ownership and management, team finances, and player agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <title>Using speech and language to identify patients at risk for hospitalizations and emergency department visits in homecare</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-using-speech-and-language-to-identify-patients-at-risk-for-hospitalizations-and-emergency-department-visits-in-homecare/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-using-speech-and-language-to-identify-patients-at-risk-for-hospitalizations-and-emergency-department-visits-in-homecare/</guid>
=======
      <title>The Value of Data</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-the-value-of-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-the-value-of-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many scholars and policymakers view establishing functioning data markets as essential for the digital economy to bring prosperity and stability to society at large. A key challenge is to determine the value of an individual&amp;rsquo;s specific data. Is one buyer’s data more valuable than another’s for an e-commerce platform? How much should each be paid?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using speech and language to identify patients at risk for hospitalizations and emergency department visits in homecare</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-using-speech-and-language-to-identify-patients-at-risk-for-hospitalizations-and-emergency-department-visits-in-homecare/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-using-speech-and-language-to-identify-patients-at-risk-for-hospitalizations-and-emergency-department-visits-in-homecare/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This study is the first step in exploring an emerging and previously understudied data stream - verbal communication between healthcare providers and patients. In partnership between Columbia Engineering, School of Nursing, Amazon, and the largest home healthcare agency in the US, the study will investigate how to use audio-recorded routine communications between patients and nurses to help identify patients at risk of hospitalization or emergency department visits. The study will combine speech recognition, machine learning and natural language processing to achieve its goals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
<<<<<<< Updated upstream
      <title>Volatile solubility laws in melts and magmas; an adaptative and universal Bayesian approach</title>
      <link>/2021/09/project-volatile-solubility-laws-in-melts-and-magmas-an-adaptative-and-universal-bayesian-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/09/project-volatile-solubility-laws-in-melts-and-magmas-an-adaptative-and-universal-bayesian-approach/</guid>
=======
      <title>Volatile solubility laws in melts and magmas: an adaptative and universal Bayesian approach</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-volatile-solubility-laws-in-melts-and-magmas-an-adaptative-and-universal-bayesian-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-volatile-solubility-laws-in-melts-and-magmas-an-adaptative-and-universal-bayesian-approach/</guid>
>>>>>>> Stashed changes
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All volcanoes on earth are driven by the degassing of volatile elements, mostly H2O and CO2 from their host magma. To model the degassing process, one needs to know the solubility laws of these volatile. To that end, petrologists have been performing high-pressure high-temperature experiments for sixty years to determine how much water and CO2 dissolves in magma as a function of Pressure, Temperature, Melt composition (12 oxides) and oxidation state. To model how these fifteen parameters affect solubility laws petrologist have then relied on empirical interpolation between experimental data points and some extrapolations using classical thermodynamic theory to infer the expected behavior beyond experimental calibration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement learning for vehicle routing</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-reinforcement-learning-for-vehicle-routing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-reinforcement-learning-for-vehicle-routing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vehicle routing has been extensively studied in optimization problems. With the advance of AI and big data, this project aims to solve vehicle routing problems (VRP) using reinforcement learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
