<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Neuroscience on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/neuroscience/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Neuroscience on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/neuroscience/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Discovering the cost function optimized by the primate visual system&#39;s deep hierarchical architecture</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-discovering-the-cost-function-optimized-by-the-primate-visual-system-s-deep-hierarchical-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-discovering-the-cost-function-optimized-by-the-primate-visual-system-s-deep-hierarchical-architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The visual cortex has a distinctive deep hierarchical organization as a result of ontogenetic and phylogenetic optimization. It is unclear what the factors are that shape this particular hierarchical organization. One factor is the compositional and hierarchical nature of our world’s appearance, which may be optimally processed by a hierarchical visual system. Another factor is the need for space and energy efficiency, which constrains the number of neurons and connections. The project will employ computational modeling to understand the contribution of these constraints to shaping the combination of breadth, depth, and skipping connections employed by primate visual cortex.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Training a deep neural network on large-scale brain imaging and cognition data.</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-training-a-deep-neural-network-on-large-scale-brain-imaging-and-cognition-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-training-a-deep-neural-network-on-large-scale-brain-imaging-and-cognition-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to develop and validate a deep neural network that predicts a child&amp;rsquo;s emotion and cognition. DSI scholars will implement 3D convolutional neural networks on brain imaging data from thousands of children to predict cognitive, emotional, and socio-developmental variables. Statistical evaluation of the model performance will be conducted. The scalable deep neural network analysis will help find brain underpinnings of cognition and emotion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Breaking the neural code of a cnidarian</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-breaking-the-neural-code-of-a-cnidarian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-breaking-the-neural-code-of-a-cnidarian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the relation between the activity of all the neurons in the cnidarian hydra and its behavioral repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Neuronal Ensemble Detection with Temporal CRF (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-neuronal-ensemble-detection-with-temporal-crf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-neuronal-ensemble-detection-with-temporal-crf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given calcium imaging data of active neurons, can we detect groups of co-firing neurons, called neuronal ensembles? We have a number of datasets consisting of hundreds of neurons imaged for thousands of time steps, and seek to extend an existing CRF model to consider temporal relationships. The goal is to be able to detect neuronal ensembles that span multiple time steps, and that are not conditioned on external stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Human peri-ictal single unit activity</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-human-peri-ictal-single-unit-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-human-peri-ictal-single-unit-activity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Microelectrode array recordings from patients undergoing surgical evaluation have captured typical clinical seizures.  Because of the extreme pathological conditions at these times, identifying single units from extracellular data is a particular challenge.  Our group has developed techniques for tracking neurons through the ictal transition. We are applying them to newly acquired data and addressing fundamental questions about the activity of different cell classes at seizure initiation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>