<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Visualization on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/visualization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Visualization on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/visualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: A longitudinal network study of Alzheimer’s and dementia care in relation to disparities and outcomes</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease and related dementia (AD/dementia) represent a looming public health crisis, affecting roughly 5 million people in the U.S. and 11% of older adults. As with other chronic conditions, racial/ethnic and socio-economic disparities exist in the prevalence and burden of illness. However, less is known about how disparities in access to care influence the care trajectories – i.e., the scope, frequency and sequence of services used across healthcare settings – of those with AD/dementia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Enhancing self-directed learning opportunities</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analyze data from one of the following library applications/systems and create visualizations that highlight the most important findings pertaining to the support of self-directed learning:  Vialogues (TC Video Discussion Application), PocketKnowledge (TC Online Archive), DocDel (E-Reserve System), Pressible (Blogging Platform), Library Website and Mobile App.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Internships in DSI Center for Data, Media &amp; Society</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-internships-in-dsi-center-for-data-media-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-internships-in-dsi-center-for-data-media-society/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The DSI Center for Data, Media &amp;amp; Society is seeking undergraduate and masters students during the summer to work on projects at the intersection of Computer Science, Data Science, and the humanities.  These projects will combine domain expertise in the humanities with computer and data science techniques to tackle important societal and media problems.  Projects can vary from documenting human rights violations, providing rural farmers with financial safety-nets, analyzing the sources of social media popularity, and more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visualization of continuous health data measurements</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ubiquity of current smart and IoT devices has the potential to transform healthcare. For example, current devices can measure continuously activity levels, heart rate, blood oxygen levels, and electrocardiogram. Our lab is developing new devices which can measure additional streams of health data which are currently not possible.  The summer project will involve visualization of this entire set of data, machine learning, and multiparametric data analysis to extract trends that match health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>