<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Closed Flexible Timeline on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/closed-flexible-timeline/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Closed Flexible Timeline on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/closed-flexible-timeline/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Using causal inference to understand health disparities and discrimination in pregnancy treatment and outcomes</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/09/project-using-causal-inference-to-understand-health-disparities-and-discrimination-in-pregnancy-treatment-and-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/09/project-using-causal-inference-to-understand-health-disparities-and-discrimination-in-pregnancy-treatment-and-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adverse pregnancy outcomes (APOs), such as preeclampsia and preterm birth, are common and devastating. The human and economic costs of APOs are tremendous, and the United States has among the highest APO rates among developed nations. APOs are especially common in non-White and low-income communities. For example, in the United States Black women are 50% more likely to deliver preterm compared to White women. Research has shown that the increased risk of adverse outcomes in overburdened populations is not fully explained by socioeconomic status or other socio-demographic factors. In addition to having elevated risk for adverse outcomes, non-White women in the United States may be less likely to receive certain interventions, such as treatment for postpartum depression, but are more likely to receive others, such as cesarean section, suggesting that there may be unwarranted and discriminatory variation in pregnancy care.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards a combined geopolitical and technical understanding of regional Internet</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-towards-a-combined-geopolitical-and-technical-understanding-of-regional-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/09/project-towards-a-combined-geopolitical-and-technical-understanding-of-regional-internet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This research project aims at exploring and developing methods to improve and diversify the visualizations of the interactions between the Internet and the topographical and geopolitical space (i.e. space and the political actors that rule over it) through the case study of a region of interest (could be virtually any region that would be of interest for the student). The main intend of the project is to produce a set of maps and visualizations (including infographics where relevant), as comprehensive and diverse as possible, combining Internet mapping with the geographical and geopolitical context of that region. We will build on top of existing techniques for visualizations of the Internet and discuss potential capacities to further model the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
