<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Big Data on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/big-data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Big Data on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/big-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Project: Blockchain Anomaly Detection</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-blockchain-anomaly-detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-blockchain-anomaly-detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project has collected a large set of data (&amp;gt;200GB) from a cryptocurrency block chain.  It is developing methods for detecting anomalies in transactions based on newer Social Networks, Graph Analysis and Machine Learning methods. The work involves data cleaning/wrangling and creation and implementation of various algorithms and analyzing the transactions for identifying different set of anomalies and manipulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: A longitudinal network study of Alzheimer’s and dementia care in relation to disparities and outcomes</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease and related dementia (AD/dementia) represent a looming public health crisis, affecting roughly 5 million people in the U.S. and 11% of older adults. As with other chronic conditions, racial/ethnic and socio-economic disparities exist in the prevalence and burden of illness. However, less is known about how disparities in access to care influence the care trajectories – i.e., the scope, frequency and sequence of services used across healthcare settings – of those with AD/dementia.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
