<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Student Applications - Summer 2020</title>
      <link>/2020/05/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-summer-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-summer-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given the COVID-19 environment and the increasing requests for additional support for projects, the Data Science Institute is pleased to announce a second wave of summer research projects through the Data Science Scholars and Data For Good programs. Please note that this is on a compressed timeline and student applications are due &lt;strong&gt;Friday, May 22nd&lt;/strong&gt;, 2020 at &lt;strong&gt;11:59pm&lt;/strong&gt; Eastern time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia University&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master&amp;rsquo;s students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data For Good Scholars program connects student volunteers to organizations and individuals working for the social good whose projects have developed a need for data science expertise. As &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; problems with real world data, these projects are excellent opportunities for students to learn how data science is practiced outside of the university setting and to learn how to work effectively with people for whom data science sits outside of their subject area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Supervised Topic Models</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-advanced-supervised-topic-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-advanced-supervised-topic-models/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project we&amp;rsquo;ll be expending on existing family of supervised topic models. These models extend LDA to document collections where for each document we observe additional labels or values of interest. More specifically, one of the goals of this project, is to use additional document level data, such as author information, to develop better exploratory data tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis and processing of GIS data in assessing international development</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-analysis-and-processing-of-gis-data-in-assessing-international-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-analysis-and-processing-of-gis-data-in-assessing-international-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We need someone with strong data wrangling capabilities, to be able to determine quick ways to clean and merge data. The format of the data is spatial (GIS) but it could also be manipulated in tabular format. GRID3 is a program within &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ciesin.org/&#34;&gt;CIESIN&lt;/a&gt; which is a research center located at the Lamont-Doherty Campus (with office space on the morningside campus) and is part of Columbia&amp;rsquo;s Earth Institute.  Candidates can learn more about the program at the GRID3 &lt;a href=&#34;https://grid3.org/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the relationship between sleep and cardiometabolic risk in NYC women</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-assessing-the-relationship-between-sleep-and-cardiometabolic-risk-in-nyc-women/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-assessing-the-relationship-between-sleep-and-cardiometabolic-risk-in-nyc-women/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This was a 1-year prospective observational study to examine the relation between sleep and cardiometabolic risk among 506 women in the NYC area.  All of the data has been collected and entered int a Redcap database, has been cleaned, and is ready for analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bacterial and viral genomic epidemiology</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-bacterial-and-viral-genomic-epidemiology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-bacterial-and-viral-genomic-epidemiology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial and viral genomic epidemiology. Ongoing and new projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 and commuting: How will Columbia cope?</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-covid-19-and-commuting-how-will-columbia-cope/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-covid-19-and-commuting-how-will-columbia-cope/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to mitigate the risks of commuting for Columbia employees when they will have to return to work after the state-on-pause is over from May 15. As Columbia has been preparing for ramping up labs with an emphasis on social distancing within campus, higher risks could arise when the employees have to commute between home and campus. It is estimated approximately one in five residents in NYC might have been infected by COVID-19 . With the fear of exposing to coronavirus, commuters have shifted from transit to individual cars or bikes, leading to a significant drop in subway ridership , more speeding tickets , surging bike traffic , and more crashes with cyclist injuries . On the other hand, low-income people of color, who have been hit the hardest by the coronavirus , could be in a more disadvantaged position after the state “un-pause”, because: (1) they lack accessibility to other travel modes than public transit; (2) they usually live far from their workplace for an affordable accommodation and have to commute a long way; and (3) many of them take night shift but most transportation options are shut down at night after the pandemic. This project aims to address travel safety and equity concerns of essential workers and provide a responsible and safe transportation solution for the Columbia community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing network behavior in phishing emails</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-characterizing-network-behavior-in-phishing-emails/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-characterizing-network-behavior-in-phishing-emails/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Targeted phishing is one of the most common and damaging cybersecurity attacks, incurring tens of billions of dollars in losses a year. In order to increase the success of the phishing emails, attackers often craft emails that impersonate real people or legitimate online services, and send them from networks and hosting sites that have a high reputation. This leads major email security services, including Outlook and Gmail, to often misclassify these emails as legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good Project: The Cost of Human Rights Violations</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Under United States securities laws corporations must disclose material risks to their operations. Human rights issues, especially in authoritarian countries, rarely show up in the information that data providers offer to investors, in part due to the risks to those subject to these abuses. The result is a dearth of data on human rights materiality and the tendency of investors to overlook human rights risks of the companies that they finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Stick2PrEP - Analysis of adherence for Pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) against HIV in observational and RCT interventions</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-data-for-good-stick2prep---analysis-of-adherence-for-pre-exposure-prophylaxis-prep-against-hiv-in-observational-and-rct-interventions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-data-for-good-stick2prep---analysis-of-adherence-for-pre-exposure-prophylaxis-prep-against-hiv-in-observational-and-rct-interventions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) has been shown to be extremely effective in reducing the acquisition of HIV.  However, achieving the population-level impact of this intervention is contingent on the identification and linkage of appropriate candidates and ongoing engagement in care throughout periods of high and low risk.  Pre-COVID we had a suite of active studies looking at engagement in PrEP care.  These included  our PrEP database, Get2PrEP (studying individuals with positive STI tests but no PrEP engagement), Back2PrEP (evaluating patients who dropped out of care and re-engaged), Lost2PrEP (survey of individuals who have been out of care for 6 months or more), and our major study Stick2PrEP2.0 a randomized-control trial of text message based feedback to individuals receiving PrEP care and evaluating engagement.  At the time of the COVID pandemic we had just started to perform interim analysis on Stick2PrEP2.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental effects on Job mobility</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-environmental-effects-on-job-mobility/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-environmental-effects-on-job-mobility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are studing the level and nature of gender and racial discrimination at different stages of the employment relationship among US firms, and how the environment affects job mobility of employees. We are using company reviews data and employee resume databases from employment-related websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine-learning based methods to extract river flow information from satellite imagery</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-machine-learning-based-methods-to-extract-river-flow-information-from-satellite-imagery/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-machine-learning-based-methods-to-extract-river-flow-information-from-satellite-imagery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Humanity thrives along major rivers – this is as true now as it was ages ago. Our dependence on rivers for agriculture and electricity, as well as the need to control its flow because of our proximity, has  resulted in dramatic changes to the nature of the rivers. What were once great perennial rivers are now mere trickles during the summer months. This puts the livelihood of many people, especially poor farmers, in jeopardy. How can we monitor and document changes to the flow through rivers over time? Since river gauge measurements are rare or non-existent, any way in which we can use freely available satellite imagery (Landsat, Sentinel) to determine the changes in flow patterns of rivers over time would be extremely useful. One such tool is Rivamap – it uses OpenCV to analyze satellite imagery to extract information about rivers, especially for large rivers. What about smaller ones – it does not seem to work as well. In this project, the student(s) will have to develop machine-learning based methods  (or extend the capabilities of Rivamap) to study satellite images to extract information about the path and dimensions of rivers of different flow rates and flow patterns. Comparison with ground-truth data will be needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multilanguage analysis of book titles</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-multilanguage-analysis-of-book-titles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-multilanguage-analysis-of-book-titles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;data visualization, statistics, and analysis of translation entries online. More details will be furnished upon request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multilanguage analysis of search results</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-multilanguage-analysis-of-search-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-multilanguage-analysis-of-search-results/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The talent students will be given search entries, topics, or terms and will be required to analyze the algorithms of search results across various engines, languages.  More information and details upon request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phenotyping COVID-19 patients using NLP and clinical notes</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-phenotyping-covid-19-patients-using-nlp-and-clinical-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-phenotyping-covid-19-patients-using-nlp-and-clinical-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our lab is using clinical notes to phenotype COVID patient outcomes. The aim is to better understand the sequela of COVID-19 from clinical notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social media echo chambers enhancing anxiety and depression: the effects of COVID19</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-social-media-echo-chambers-enhancing-anxiety-and-depression-the-effects-of-covid19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-social-media-echo-chambers-enhancing-anxiety-and-depression-the-effects-of-covid19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The question we ask is whether online echo-chambers on social media networks enhance the anxiety and depression of individuals during the COVID19 outbreak. More specifically we want to measure the intensity of the communication about COVID19 within the echo-chamber of individuals on Twitter and investigate the impact on their subsequent tweets in terms of the level of anxiety and signs of depressive language in their Tweets.  We measure echo-chambers by the number of users in the social network that tweeted about COVID19. We build on an extensive dataset of Twitter users for whom we have identified a large number of demographic and geographic variables (such as the gender, age, ethnicity, location by state, political affiliation) as well as their social network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analysis of radiation dose parameters for interventional neuroradiology procedures</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-statistical-analysis-of-radiation-dose-parameters-for-interventional-neuroradiology-procedures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-statistical-analysis-of-radiation-dose-parameters-for-interventional-neuroradiology-procedures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From May 2018 to September 2019, we prospectively recorded radiation exposure parameters for 634 neuro-procedures performed at a single, academic medical center. Procedures were performed with a biplane angiographic system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Studies Lifestyle Behaviors (Diet, Sleep, and Circadian rest-activity rhythms in relation) to Cardiometabolic Outcomes</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-studies-lifestyle-behaviors-diet-sleep-and-circadian-rest-activity-rhythms-in-relation-to-cadiometabolic-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-studies-lifestyle-behaviors-diet-sleep-and-circadian-rest-activity-rhythms-in-relation-to-cadiometabolic-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I  am conducting studies on lifestyle behaviors, in particular diet, sleep behaviors, and circadian rest-activity rhythms in relation to cardiometabolic outcomes (hypertension, type 2 diabetes, and obesity). Sample sizes of my studies range from n=100 to n=16,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Template matching and image processing in educational development</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-template-matching-and-image-processing-in-educational-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-template-matching-and-image-processing-in-educational-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Template-matching, image-processing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter sentiment in NYC parks after COVID-19</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-twitter-sentiment-in-nyc-parks-after-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-twitter-sentiment-in-nyc-parks-after-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the period 2017-2019 the Earth Institute Urban Design Lab (UDL) in collaboration with  Data Science faculty and students was engaged in a studio of Twitter-based sentiment analysis that explored correlation of indicators of “well-being” within New York City parks in comparison with outside, published as “Twitter sentiment in New York City parks as measure of well-being” in Landscape and Urban Planning Volume 189, September 2019, Pages 235-246.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using machine learning identify trends in HIV incidence, treatment disruption and risk factors in the PHIA multi-country population-based HIV Impact Assessment survey</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-using-machine-learning-identify-trends-in-hiv-incidence-treatment-disruption-and-risk-factors-in-the-phia-multi-country-population-based-hiv-impact-assessment-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-using-machine-learning-identify-trends-in-hiv-incidence-treatment-disruption-and-risk-factors-in-the-phia-multi-country-population-based-hiv-impact-assessment-survey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The PHIA project is a multi-country population-based HIV Impact Assessment survey which has interviewed and tested for HIV over 450,000 people of all ages in Africa. We are also currently conducting a second round of surveys in many countries, and hope to use best practices in big data management to generate a combined dataset across all countries. We want to combine this data with environmental, mobility and social media data and then use machine learning to identify trends in HIV incidence, treatment disruption and risk factors. We would also be interested in looking at other ways to use environmental data to predict potential zoonotic outbreaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supplementary Call for Student Applications - Spring-Summer 2020</title>
      <link>/2020/02/supplementary-call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/supplementary-call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have two additional projects (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/02/project-cryptocurrency-analytics-identifying-bad-actors/&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/02/project-understanding-orientation/&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;) and are thus opening another round of applications. You can apply for these projects &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.gle/xA5ZCXuUr6Jgh2Zk9&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The deadline for this application is &lt;strong&gt;Friday, February 28th at 11:59pm&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you applied previously, the original application &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.gle/FirneensvXgZGE6HA&#34;&gt;form&lt;/a&gt; has been unlocked so that you can access your application materials. Do not use this form to resubmit - it will be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cryptocurrency Analytics: Identifying Bad Actors</title>
      <link>/2020/02/project-cryptocurrency-analytics-identifying-bad-actors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/project-cryptocurrency-analytics-identifying-bad-actors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many of the cryptocurrency transactions have involved fraudulent activities including ponzi schemes, ransomware as well money-laundering. The objective is to use Graph Machine Learning methods to identify the miscreants on Bitcoin and Etherium Networks. There are many challenges including the amount of data in 100s of Gigabytes, creation and scalability of algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Orientation</title>
      <link>/2020/02/project-understanding-orientation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/02/project-understanding-orientation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Orienting to a novel event is a rapid shift in attention to a change in one’s surroundings that appears to be a fundamental biological mechanism for survival and essentially functions as a &amp;ldquo;what is it&amp;rdquo; detector. Orienting appears to play a central role in human learning and development, as it facilitates adaptation to an ever-changing environment.  Thus, orienting can be viewed as an allocational mechanism in which attention sifts through the complex multi-sensory world and selects relevant stimuli for further processing.  The selection of stimuli for further processing has implications for what will be encoded into memories and how strong those memory traces will be.  The ability to differentiate between relevant and irrelevant input, to inhibit the processing of irrelevant stimuli, and to sustain attention requires control, and inhibitory processes that improve with age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Student Applications - Spring-Summer 2020</title>
      <link>/2020/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce that the Data Science Institute (DSI) and Data For Good Scholars programs for Spring-Summer 2020 are open for application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia University&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master&amp;rsquo;s students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data For Good Scholars program connects student volunteers to organizations and individuals working for the social good whose projects have developed a need for data science expertise. As &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; problems with real world data, these projects are excellent opportunities for students to learn how data science is practiced outside of the university setting and to learn how to work effectively with people for whom data science sits outside of their subject area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Undergraduate Summer Interns in Statistical Research (Department of Statistics)</title>
      <link>/2020/01/undergraduate-summer-interns-in-statistical-research-department-of-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/undergraduate-summer-interns-in-statistical-research-department-of-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia&amp;rsquo;s Department of Statistics is running a summer research internship program for Columbia undergraduate students to work with its faculty on cutting-edge statistical research. This year,
the internship will be during the first summer session (May 26, 2020 - July 2nd, 2020). Interns receive a stipend of $3,000 and are housed in undergraduate dormitories during the internship period.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A multi-omic map of human aging</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-a-multi-omic-map-of-human-aging/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-a-multi-omic-map-of-human-aging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project builds on a novel cellular model of human aging (Sturm et al. Epigenomics 2019) where we can investigate trajectories of multiple molecular features of aging over long time periods. The underlying multi-omic dataset includes epigenomic (DNA methylation), proteomic (protein abundance), bioenergetics (mitochondrial respiration), telomere length, and various secreted factors. A major challenge for the DSI Fellow will be to integrate the multi-omic dataset to capture dynamic signatures of mitochondrial dysfunction and cellular aging, working collaboratively with other scientists. The existing project is expected to result in one or more publications. Possibility to continue work for pay over the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A system for exploratory data analysis in neuroscience</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-a-system-for-exploratory-data-analysis-in-neuroscience/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-a-system-for-exploratory-data-analysis-in-neuroscience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Advances in data collection technologies in neuroscience has resulted in a deluge of high-quality data that needs to be analyzed, and presented to the experimentalist in a meaningful way. Usually the “data analysis and visualization”-pipeline is built from scratch for each new experiment resulting in a significant amount of code duplication and wasted effort in rebuilding the analysis tools. There is a growing need for a unified system to automate much of the repetitive tasks and aid biologists in understanding their data more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced data science methods to improve spinal electrical stimulation for paralysis</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-advanced-data-science-methods-to-improve-spinal-electrical-stimulation-for-paralysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-advanced-data-science-methods-to-improve-spinal-electrical-stimulation-for-paralysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We aim to augment recovery in spinal cord (SC) injured patients. Electrical stimulation of the SC can facilitate recovery, but the mechanisms are not yet understood. One knowledge gap lies in the exact pathways that are recruited by stimulation. To close this gap, we have tested the effects of SC stimulation in people undergoing clinically indicated surgery. By testing the distribution and size of muscle responses to SC stimulation, we can infer which circuits are activated. We are also examining how SC injury changes those responses. We propose to use Bayesian methods to understand the  interaction between muscle responses to stimulation and the MRI indicated pattern of damage. The project will involve construction of models linking multiple data modalities that predict muscle activity, followed by the modification of these models to account for patterns of damage. Construction of such models would enable a deeper understanding of SC stimulation leading to more effective stimulation paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COSMOS Smart Intersections, Cloud-Connected Vehicles</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-cosmos-smart-intersections-cloud-connected-vehicles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-cosmos-smart-intersections-cloud-connected-vehicles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Research on: (i) COSMOS cloud connected vehicles, (ii) Monitoring of traffic intersections, using bird’s eye cameras, supported by ultra-low latency computational/communications hubs; (iii) Simultaneous video-based tracking of cars and pedestrians, and prediction of movement based on long-term observations of the intersection; (iv) Real-time computational processing, using deep learning, utilizing GPUs, in support of COSMOS applications; (v) Sub-10ms latency communication between all vehicles and the edge cloud computational/communication hub, to be used in support of autonomous vehicle navigation. The research is performed using the pilot node of project &lt;a href=&#34;https://cosmos-lab.org/&#34;&gt;COSMOS&lt;/a&gt; infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combining in vivo calcium imaging datasets and deep learning networks for video analysis (DeepLabCut) to identify novel brain regulators of fine motor learning in mice</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-combining-in-vivo-calcium-imaging-datasets-and-deep-learning-networks-for-video-analysis-deeplabcut-to-identify-novel-brain-regulators-of-fine-motor-learning-in-mice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-combining-in-vivo-calcium-imaging-datasets-and-deep-learning-networks-for-video-analysis-deeplabcut-to-identify-novel-brain-regulators-of-fine-motor-learning-in-mice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to use deep learning networks to understand which neurons in the brain encode fine motor movements in mice. We collected large datasets entailing calcium imaging data of active neurons and high-resolution videos when mice perform motor tasks. We want to use recent advances in deep learning to (1) estimate the poses of mouse body parts at a high spatiotemporal resolution (2) extract behaviorally-relevant information and (3) align them with neural activity data. Behavioral video analysis is made possible by transfer learning, the ability to take a network that was trained on a task with a large supervised dataset and utilize it on a small supervised dataset. This has been used e.g. in a human pose–estimation algorithm called DeeperCut. Recently, such algorithms were tailored for use in the laboratory in a Python-based toolbox known as DeepLabCut, providing a tool for high-throughput behavioral video analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community-Based Environmental Impact Tracking for Bauxite Mining in Guinea</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-community-based-environmental-impact-tracking-for-bauxite-mining-in-guinea/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-community-based-environmental-impact-tracking-for-bauxite-mining-in-guinea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This position is associated with a new research project co-funded by the Earth Institute Frontiers seed funding and the UN Development Programme in Guinea. Its goal is to develop remote sensing technologies to track environmental impact from bauxite mining in rural communities and to help establish protocols for their use. We seek a research assistant who can (1) develop image classification to be applied to satellite imagery to determine extent and abundance of bauxite dust within specific communities in the Boké region (2) develop methods to make classified images available for download to smartphones in the field and (3) adapt existing application technologies to allow users in the field to upload field photographs and locations of potential impacts they identify. The resulting map would represent a composite of satellite imaged areas of impact verified in the field and documentation of other areas of impact not visible by satellite but already identified in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating accurate and equitable data resources for precision public health using machine learning tools</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-creating-accurate-and-equitable-data-resources-for-precision-public-health-using-machine-learning-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-creating-accurate-and-equitable-data-resources-for-precision-public-health-using-machine-learning-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The objective of this project is to construct linkages across disparate public health data systems using machine learning tools and assess them for bias and equitable representation of subpopulations defined by demographic and socioeconomic factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Data Analysis for a Just Transition in Energy for Thermal Comfort</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-data-analysis-for-a-just-transition-in-energy-for-thermal-comfort/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-data-analysis-for-a-just-transition-in-energy-for-thermal-comfort/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;42% of New York City greenhouse gas emissions result from on-site fossil fuel combustion in residential and commercial buildings; space heating is, by far, the majority contributor. Both New York State and NYC have policies to dramatically reduce emissions that will require a transformation in the way buildings are heated, including major efforts in existing buildings. This transition is inextricably linked to existing energy equity issues that we believe significantly overlap across NYC (and elsewhere). These include unreliable heating in the winter, susceptibility to extreme heat (an increasing occurrence with climate change) and struggles to afford energy needs. Various known data sources for NYC are available, though they are disparate and have not been analyzed holistically. Further, we believe there are potential engineering and policy solutions to these challenges. In this project, the DSI scholar will access (and search for where not yet known to qSEL researchers) relevant data sets, analyze those data sets to identify communities exposed to all or a subset of these issues, and assist qSEL researchers in developing models to evaluate possible solutions. The project has the possibility of extending through Summer 2020, subject to fundraising efforts and the success of the Spring 2020 project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: The Consequences of Language Policing</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-the-consequences-of-language-policing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-the-consequences-of-language-policing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Contestation over language use is an unavoidable feature of American politics. Yet, despite the rise of language policing on both sides of the aisle, we know surprisingly little about how ordinary citizens respond to norms governing language use from both in-group and out-group members. Following Munger (2017), I would like to leverage social media platforms such as Reddit and Twitter to evaluate whether injunctions to use particular words (e.g., undocumented immigrant, Latinx) are effective. I plan to use an experimental approach, where conditional on mentions of &amp;ldquo;illegal alien&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Hispanic/Latino,&amp;rdquo; users are randomly assigned to receive a &amp;ldquo;language correction.&amp;rdquo; Outcome measures would include subsequent use of corrected terms, valence of user responses, and upvoting/liking/RTing behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding the dynamics of mouse behavior that predict exploring and remembering</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-decoding-the-dynamics-of-mouse-behavior-that-predict-exploring-and-remembering/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-decoding-the-dynamics-of-mouse-behavior-that-predict-exploring-and-remembering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Decoding behavioral signifiers for choice and memory can have far reaching implications for understanding actions and identifying disease. We use a four arm maze where we are able to observe choices and infer memory in mice, but have access to very few pre-determined behavioral signifiers. Several recent publications implemented computer vision to extract a variety of previously unreachable aspects of behavioral analysis, including animal pose estimation (Mathis et al., 2018) and distinguishable internal states (Calhoun et al., 2019). These descriptions allowed for the identification and characterization of dynamics, which then revealed an unprecedented richness to the behaviors that determine decision making. Applying such computational approaches to examine behavior in our maze in the context of behaviors that have been validated to measure choice and memory can reveal dimensions of behavior that predict or even determine these psychological constructs. DSI scholars would use pose estimation analysis to evaluate behavioral signifiers for choice and memory and relate it to our real time concurrent measures of neural activity and transmitter release. The students would also have opportunity to examine the effect of disease models known to impair performance on our maze task on any identified signifier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding the human genome with interpretable deep learning </title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-decoding-the-human-genome-with-interpretable-deep-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-decoding-the-human-genome-with-interpretable-deep-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The function for much of the 3 billion letters in the human genome remain to be understood. Advances in DNA sequencing technology have generated enormous amount of data, yet we don’t have the tool to extract rules of how the genome works. Deep learning holds great potential in decoding the genome, in particular due to the digital nature of DNA sequences and the ability to handle large data sets. However, like many other applications, the interpretability of deep learning models hampers its ability to help understand the genome. We are developing deep learning architectures embedded with the principles of gene regulation and we will be leveraging billions of existing measurements of gene activity to learn a mechanistic model of gene regulation in human cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning for tracking single molecules and proteins</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-deep-learning-for-tracking-single-molecules-and-proteins/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-deep-learning-for-tracking-single-molecules-and-proteins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project will be focused on creating a deep learning framework for tracking individual molecules and proteins as they move within a cell under various conditions. Using total internal reflection (TIRF) microscopy, we have accumulated more than 10 million trajectories over dozens of experimental preparations with differences in both the imaging approaches as well as the biological context. In our experiments we have captured particles under a wide variety of conditions including increased protein expression level, and a range of drug concentrations. Our biggest challenge is being able to stably track the movement of a particle as it passes by other particles or groups of particles, and to do this in a way that generalizes over novel conditions. The Data Science Institute Scholar chosen for this project would work with scientists in the Javitch laboratory and others across the Columbia campus to conceive of an approach for efficiently and effectively tracking particles. The resulting work would be of great interest to an increasing number of scientists working in this field who currently rely on methods based on feature engineering that are often inaccurate or inflexible compared to modern deep learning methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering latent structure in human information demand</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-discovering-latent-structure-in-human-information-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-discovering-latent-structure-in-human-information-demand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All complex behaviors require animals to coordinate their perception and actions. To successfully achieve a goal, a decision maker (DM; be it a human, animal, or artificial agent) must determine which action to take and, faced with much more information than she can fully process, must decide which source of information to consult to best guide that action. But in contrast with natural tasks, traditional research has focused primarily on action selection but eschewed the process of information demand. We aim to fill this gap by investigating the factors that motivate people to become curious and seek information.  We are collecting behavioral data from a large sample of participants on a battery of online tasks testing various aspects of curiosity, and seek a DSI scholar who can quantitatively analyze the data. The scholar will be supervised by two co-PIs: Jacqueline Gottlieb, in Columbia&amp;rsquo;s Neuroscience Department and Zuckerman Institute, and Vince Dorie, in the DSI. The scholar will obtain training with advanced data analytic methods and the opportunity to co-author what is expected to be a high impact paper with interdisciplinary appeal in economics, neuroscience, and psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of genes associated with progression of bladder cancer</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have been studying bladder cancer in a mouse model of the disease and we are seeking to understand the molecular features of the mouse models as they relate to human bladder cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficient representations and prediction of multidimensional time series data</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-efficient-representations-and-prediction-of-multidimensional-time-series-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-efficient-representations-and-prediction-of-multidimensional-time-series-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Big data with temporal dependence brings unique challenges in effective prediction and data analysis. The complex high-dimensional interactions between observations in such data brings unique challenges which standard off-the-shelf machine learning algorithms cannot handle. Even basic tasks of clustering, visualization and identification of recurring patterns are difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Reconstructions of the Ocean Carbon Sink</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-evaluating-reconstructions-of-the-ocean-carbon-sink/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-evaluating-reconstructions-of-the-ocean-carbon-sink/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ocean significantly mitigates climate change by absorbing fossil fuel carbon from the atmosphere. Cumulatively since the preindustrial times, the ocean has absorbed 40% of emissions. To understand past changes, diagnose ongoing changes, and to predict the future behavior of the ocean carbon sink, we must understand its spatial and temporal variability. However, the ocean is poorly sampled and so we cannot do this from direct measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining The Synergistic Effects Of Cannabis And Prescription Opioid Policies On Chronic Pain, Opioid Prescribing, And Opioid Overdose</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-examining-the-synergistic-effects-of-cannabis-and-prescription-opioid-policies-on-chronic-pain-opioid-prescribing-and-opioid-overdose/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-examining-the-synergistic-effects-of-cannabis-and-prescription-opioid-policies-on-chronic-pain-opioid-prescribing-and-opioid-overdose/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The funded study examines policies that regulate the PO supply, including those related to prescription drug monitoring programs, pain management clinic laws, and prescribing limits. In this supplement, we add a set of complementary opioid policies that affect access to treatment for opioid use disorder (e.g., Medicaid coverage of medication for opioid use disorder).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group Decision Making and Communication in Limitless Space</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-group-decision-making-and-communication-in-limitless-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-group-decision-making-and-communication-in-limitless-space/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The introduction of a new technology provides individuals and organizations with a large, unowned, and limitless space for communication and organization. How do individuals use or misuse this space in their decision making? Using online discussion platforms, we will analyze what types of discussions thrive - those with depth of discussion or topical complexity or those with cohesive contours? We’ll ask, are there high status actors who are particularly good at recognizing topic gaps which need new conversations? Using social psychological theories with a large-scale archival dataset, we’ll learn more about the impact of new technologies on group decision-making processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heating Decarbonization Model Data Visualization and Analysis</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-heating-decarbonization-model-data-visualization-and-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-heating-decarbonization-model-data-visualization-and-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Quadracci Sustainable Engineering Lab (qSEL) has several research efforts related to the low-carbon energy transition, including pathways to decarbonize building space heating. Recent work has produced large model data sets that have supported recent journal articles. Several maps have been produced using QGIS and data has been made public, but user functionality is limited. While we continue to build on these efforts, we also want to make our results and data available more widely for other researchers and policymakers. The large data sets (10 years of hourly data for more than 72,000 census tracts and six scenarios) and different spatial aggregations (e.g. states and electricity planning/operating regions) present challenges. In this project, the DSI Scholar would first work with qSEL researchers to develop an interactive web interface to display maps of relevant analyses and allow users to produce time series data from the underlying models. Additional research would include further analysis at a regional level – likely New York State – to refine the current model based on additional intraregional and energy source data. The project has the possibility of extending through Summer 2020, subject to fundraising efforts and the success of the Spring 2020 project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Quality Video Streaming over Wireless</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-high-quality-video-streaming-over-wireless/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-high-quality-video-streaming-over-wireless/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The amount of video content that is being distributed over the Internet is increasing. Video providers rely on HTTP adaptive streaming approaches to deliver video clips to users. Complementary to the video provider, the service provider must determine the priority of each network stream. As part of the project, students will explore wireless network assisted strategies for http adaptive streaming by use of TOS/DSCP. This includes using machine-learning tools to analyze network video traffic and the design of reinforcement learning algorithms to improve users&amp;rsquo; video Quality of Experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying disease subtypes by comorbidity clustering using structured data from electronic health records</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-identifying-disease-subtypes-by-comorbidity-clustering-using-structured-data-from-electronic-health-records/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-identifying-disease-subtypes-by-comorbidity-clustering-using-structured-data-from-electronic-health-records/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major challenge to implementing precision medicine arises from patients who share a clinical diagnosis but have different biological causes of disease. Disease subtypes that arise from obscure etiological heterogeneity create inefficiencies in healthcare and attenuate power in clinical trials and research studies. The ability to stratify patients into biologically homogenous subgroups improves the potential for translational research by allowing us to design more powerful studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusionary Zoning in Paris and New York: Antidote to Gentrification or Trojan&#39;s Horse?</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-inclusionary-zoning-in-paris-and-new-york-antidote-to-gentrification-or-trojans-horse/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-inclusionary-zoning-in-paris-and-new-york-antidote-to-gentrification-or-trojans-horse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The research project examines how Inclusionary Zoning (IZ) impacts the housing markets of neighborhoods where it is implemented. The study focuses on the impacts of IZ in New York City and Paris, two cities at the forefront of adopting IZ in their respective countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Influence of past brain state on future perception</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-influence-of-past-brain-state-on-future-perception/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-influence-of-past-brain-state-on-future-perception/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are constantly exposed to inputs from the outside world, but we do not perceive everything we are exposed to. Some inputs are rather weak: we might perceive them at one point in time, but not at another. The state of our brains right before we receive such sensory inputs influences whether or not we perceive them. Brain oscillations are proposed to play a key role in setting these brain states; however, how exactly these brain rhythms influence our perception remains a topic of active research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linking State Medicaid and Clinical Registry Data to Assess Long-Term Outcomes for Children with Congenital Heart Disease</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-linking-state-medicaid-and-clinical-registry-data-to-assess-long-term-outcomes-for-children-with-congenital-heart-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-linking-state-medicaid-and-clinical-registry-data-to-assess-long-term-outcomes-for-children-with-congenital-heart-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Scholars would assist with Aim 1 of a new R01 working with our lab and the Health Evaluation and Analytics Laboratory at NYU Wagner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congenital heart defects (CHDs) are the most common and resource intensive birth defects managed in the United States (US), affecting ~40,000 births per year in the US. (1) One-year mortality for these children is &amp;gt;10%.  It is &amp;gt;30% for children requiring neonatal surgery. (2) Yet there are currently limited data on long-term outcomes and health expenditures for these children.  Due to marked heterogeneity in disease subtypes and treatments among CHD patients, the power of single-center studies is limited.  Multi-center data are siloed in diagnostic or procedural registries or in-patient databases, or are the product of individual investigations.  Administrative data may lack clinical precision, as ICD codes for this population are not based on physiology.  Further, data on costs and value typically rely on cost-to-charge ratio based costs, which are highly influenced by hospital accounting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Tax Evasion using Twitter Feeds</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-measuring-tax-evasion-using-twitter-feeds/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-measuring-tax-evasion-using-twitter-feeds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tax evasion is one of the main sources of informal economic activity and has drastic effects on different macroeconomic variables. However, due to various reasons, it is difficult to directly measure the extent of tax evasion. This project aims to develop a novel way of measuring aggregate tax evasion in national economies using Twitter feeds. To this end, using carefully selected keywords in different national languages, we will collect country and regional level data from Twitter feeds in different frequencies for a large cross section of economies and then construct a measure of tax evasion using the collected data. In addition to fully describing the collected dataset, the project will also examine the evolution of the constructed series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single cell RNA-seq analysis of eye development and disease</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-single-cell-rna-seq-analysis-of-eye-development-and-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-single-cell-rna-seq-analysis-of-eye-development-and-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Single cell sequencing has generated unprecedented insight into the cellular complexity of normal and diseased organ. We are interested in using this technique to understand the mechanisms of eye development, disease and regeneration. We also would like to compare the transcriptomic signatures between mouse models and human tissues. This project involves analysis of large amount of data from single cell sequencing. It requires understanding of statistical analysis and proficient programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Startup Cartography Project: Data and quality support</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-startup-cartography-project-data-and-quality-support/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-startup-cartography-project-data-and-quality-support/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are looking for talented data scientists to support the data processing and learning in the Startup Cartography Project and its follow-on project, the Artificial Intelligence in Entrepreneurship Lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analyses of Siamese fighting fish aggressive behavior</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-statistical-analyses-of-siamese-fighting-fish-aggressive-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-statistical-analyses-of-siamese-fighting-fish-aggressive-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Project: analyze behavior of Siamese fighting fish (Betta splendens) as part of a collaboration between the Bendesky and Cunningham labs of the Zuckerman Institute (NeuroTheory Center)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Superior Longitudinal Fasciculi abnormalities associated with the attentional deficit in schizophrenia</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-superior-longitudinal-fasciculi-abnormalities-associated-with-the-attentional-deficit-in-schizophrenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-superior-longitudinal-fasciculi-abnormalities-associated-with-the-attentional-deficit-in-schizophrenia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Individuals with schizophrenia shows a wide range of cognitive deficits, and lack in the ability to control the variety of inputs (whether internal or external) to create a unitary “self”. This problem has been often associated with a supramodal attentional deficit, but its causes are yet unknown. In the past twenty years, the quest to identify brain regions or networks showing abnormal functioning in schizophrenia has been unproductive; but one question is left unanswered: is it possible that it is the white matter tracts supporting attention (i.e., the superior longitudinal fasciculi I, II, and III) to be compromised in this psychiatric disorder? The present project will attempt to dissect the fronto-parietal branches with DTI by analyzing over 400 images from the Open Access SchizConnect.Org repository (data already available to the PI). Funds will be used to support the work of a junior or senior-year undergraduate student (possibly from URMs) to conduct the data analysis during the summer of AY2020. Results will be made available with the scientific community and published in open access peer-review journals (e.g.,  Schizophrenia Research). Co-mentoring of the undergraduate student will be done by Dr. Henrietta Howells (&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.it/citations?user=nudmODkAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;oi=ao&#34;&gt;https://scholar.google.it/citations?user=nudmODkAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;oi=ao&lt;/a&gt;), opening the student to an international collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Evolution of the Smallest Galaxies in the Universe</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-the-evolution-of-the-smallest-galaxies-in-the-universe/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-the-evolution-of-the-smallest-galaxies-in-the-universe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Milky Way swarms with orbiting satellite dwarf galaxies of astounding diversity. Some galaxies continue to form stars while others stop and dim in brightness. In computer simulations, the evolutionary history of each dwarf galaxy that leads to these differences is known. Galaxies can lose gas and stop forming stars due to early exposure to stellar radiation (reionization), interaction with the hot gas of the host (ram-pressure stripping), or gravitational interactions with the host/dwarf galaxies (tidal effects).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Urban Lead Atlas</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-the-urban-lead-atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-the-urban-lead-atlas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Urban Lead Atlas is a collaborative community-based research initiative to create the nations’ first crowd-sourced open online map identifying toxic lead hazards located within the homes, schools, landscape, and lead service lines for water in American cities. The project will begin by integrating data from a small set of cities – New York, Philadelphia, Washington D.C. and Newark - including housing enforcement and lead service line datasets, data on lead dust in schools, and the results of soil lead tests in parks and backyards, on the websites of Columbia University’s Center for Sustainable Urban Development. Ultimately, the goal of the Urban Lead Atlas is to create and populate a fully open online platform that is capable of integrating data from “citizen scientists” and residents regarding the sites of lead hazards in their city’s environment and buildings. This research is important, as experts estimate that over nine million US children have lead blood levels which may cause sub-clinical effects and permanent adverse health, cognitive, and behavior outcomes. The Lead Atlas is intended as the first model for a national effort, the American Lead Atlas project, which seeks to create a national online collaborative map of lead hazards within American cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using machine learning and topology to phenotype mouse behavior</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-using-machine-learning-and-topology-to-phenotype-mouse-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-using-machine-learning-and-topology-to-phenotype-mouse-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A central issue facing systems neuroscience is defining the rich naturalistic behavioral repertoire that mice engage in under psychiatrically relevant situations. Recent advances in deep learning (e.g., DeepLabCut) have made frame by frame detailed pose estimation possible. However, this dense behavioral data requires new techniques for defining the ethogram (full description of behavior). To date, researchers have used frequency based time series approaches to tackle this problem, with significant limitations. An alternative approach would be to take advantage of new topology methods (persistent homology and directed algebraic topology) to characterize the shapes formed by mouse limb trajectories. Such an approach would have broad application in systems neuroscience. For this project, the student will use machine learning to label animal body parts, then topology to characterize the ethogram and compare the results to existing approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Faculty Participation --- DSI Scholars Spring-Summer 2020</title>
      <link>/2019/12/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;call-for-faculty-participation-december-2019&#34;&gt;Call for Faculty Participation. December 2019.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Institute is pleased to call for Faculty Participation in the Spring and/or Summer 2020 sessions of the 3rd cohort of Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage undergraduate and master students to work with Columbia faculty, through a data science research internship. Last year, we worked with 47 projects and received more than 400 unique applications from Columbia Students. The program’s unique enrichment activities will foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Student Applications - Fall 2019</title>
      <link>/2019/09/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-fall-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-fall-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce that the Data Science Institute (DSI) and Data For Good Scholars programs for Fall 2019 are open for application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia University&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master&amp;rsquo;s students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data For Good Scholars program connects student volunteers to organizations and individuals working for the social good whose projects have developed a need for data science expertise. As &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; problems with real world data, these projects are excellent opportunities for students to learn how data science is practiced outside of the university setting and to learn how to work effectively with people for whom data science sits outside of their subject area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cryptocurrency Analytics: Identifying Bad Actors</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-cryptocurrency-analytics-identifying-bad-actors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-cryptocurrency-analytics-identifying-bad-actors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many of the cryptocurrency transactions have involved fraudulent activities including ponzi schemes, ransomware as well money-laundering. The objective is to use Graph Machine Learning methods to identify the miscreants on Bitcoin and Etherium Networks. There are many challenges including the amount of data in 100s of Gigabytes, creation and scalability of algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good Project: African North Americans Database</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-african-north-americans-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-african-north-americans-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is the first comprehensive examination of African North Americans who crossed one of the U.S.-Canada borders, going either direction, after the Underground Railroad, in the generation alive roughly 1865-1930. It analyzes census and other records to match individuals and families across the decades, despite changes or ambiguities in their names, ages, &amp;ldquo;color,&amp;rdquo; birthplace, or other details. The main difficulty in making these matches is that the census data for people with a confirmed identity does not stay uniform decade after decade. Someone might be recorded not with their given name but instead a nickname (Elizabeth to Betsy); women can marry or get remarried and change their names; racial measures by a census taker may change (black to mulatto, or mulatto to white); someone might say they are from Canada, even when they were born in Kentucky, depending on how the question was asked; people who were estimating their ages might be 35 in 1870 and 40 in 1880 and 50 in 1890, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good Project: The Cost of Human Rights Violations</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Under United States securities laws corporations must disclose material risks to their operations. Human rights issues, especially in authoritarian countries, rarely show up in the information that data providers offer to investors, in part due to the risks to those subject to these abuses. The result is a dearth of data on human rights materiality and the tendency of investors to overlook human rights risks of the companies that they finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decoding the human genome with interpretable deep learning</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-decoding-the-human-genome-with-interpretable-deep-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-decoding-the-human-genome-with-interpretable-deep-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The function for much of the 3 billion letters in the human genome remain to be understood. Advances in DNA sequencing technology have generated enormous amount of data, yet we don&amp;rsquo;t have the tool to extract rules of how the genome works. Deep learning holds great potential in decoding the genome, in particular due to the digital nature of DNA sequences and the ability to handle large data sets. However, like many other applications, the interpretability of deep learning models hampers its ability to help understand the genome. We are developing deep learning architectures embedded with the principles of gene regulation and we will be leveraging millions of existing whole genome measurements of gene activity to learn a mechanistic model of gene regulation in human cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing Fair Representations with Provable Guarantees</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-designing-fair-representations-with-provable-guarantees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-designing-fair-representations-with-provable-guarantees/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Designing high quality prediction models while maintaining social equity (in terms of ethnicity, gender, age, etc.) is critical in today&amp;rsquo;s world. Most recent research in algorithmic fairness focuses on developing fair machine learning algorithms such as fair classification, fair regression, or fair clustering. Nevertheless, it can sometimes be more useful to simply preprocess the data so as to &amp;ldquo;remove&amp;rdquo; sensitive information from the input feature space, thus minimizing potential discrimination in subsequent prediction tasks. We call this a &amp;ldquo;fair representation&amp;rdquo; of the data. A key advantage of using a fair data representation is that a practitioner can simply run any off-the-shelf algorithm and still maintain social equity without having to worry about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing effective prediction models via kernel random projections</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-designing-effective-prediction-models-via-kernel-random-projections/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-designing-effective-prediction-models-via-kernel-random-projections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mixture models are a popular technique for clustering and density estimation due to their simplicity and ease of use. However the success of these models relies crucially on specific assumptions these models make about the underlying data distribution. Gaussian mixture models, for instance, assume that the subpopulations within the data are Gaussians-like, and can thus lead to poor predictions on datasets with more complex intrinsic structures. A common approach in such situations is to resort to more complex data models. An interesting sparsely explored alternative is to find feature transformations that maintain the salient cluster information while simplifying the subpopulation structure, in effect making mixture models highly effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development of unsupervised feature extraction methods for analysis of large earthquake data sets</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-development-of-unsupervised-feature-extraction-methods-for-analysis-of-large-earthquake-data-sets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-development-of-unsupervised-feature-extraction-methods-for-analysis-of-large-earthquake-data-sets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are requesting a DSI Scholar position for an undergraduate to work with myself and my collaborator Ben Holtzman (Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory, LDEO). We have been collaborating on the development of novel machine learning applications to seismology, specifically unsupervised feature extraction in spectral properties of large numbers of small earthquakes. Our first application was published in Science Advances last year (Holtzman, Pate, Paisley, Waldhauser, Repetto, &amp;ldquo;Machine learning reveals cyclic changes in seismic source spectra in Geysers geothermal field.&amp;rdquo; Science Advances 4, eaao2929. doi:10.1126/sciadv.aao2929, 2018). Currently we are building a synthetic dataset to better understand the features that control clustering behavior, and compare different clustering methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Identification and Risk Analysis of Tailings Dam Failure for Mining Operations</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-dynamic-identification-and-risk-analysis-of-tailings-dam-failure-for-mining-operations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-dynamic-identification-and-risk-analysis-of-tailings-dam-failure-for-mining-operations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, there have been multiple failures of large tailings dams that store mining wastes, around the world, with devastating impacts (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brumadinho_dam_disaster&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brumadinho_dam_disaster&lt;/a&gt;). These dams are unique in that they continue to be raised as waste piles up and can get as tall as 400m. The risk and impact of failure increases as the dam gets taller.  There are several thousand such dams around the world. The concept of the project is to develop a continuous status monitoring and risk analysis of these dams, automatically, using globally available satellite data from multiple bands, as well as regularly updated climate data products. Overtopping of the dam during an intense or persistent rainfall event is the leading mode of failure. Foundation failure which leads to a liquefaction or deformation of the dam is the second leading failure mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficiently representing genetic diversity from thousands of microbiome samples</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-efficiently-representing-genetic-diversity-from-thousands-of-microbiome-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-efficiently-representing-genetic-diversity-from-thousands-of-microbiome-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The microbiome comprises a heterogeneous mix of bacterial strains, many with strong association to human diseases. Recent work has shown that even the same bacteria could have differences in their genomes across multiple individuals. Such differences, termed structural variations, are strongly associated with host disease risk factors [1]. However, methods for their systematic extraction and profiling are currently lacking. This project aims to make cross-sample analysis of structural variants from hundreds of individual microbiomes feasible by efficient representation of metagenomic data. The colored De-Bruijn graph (cDBG) data structure is a natural choice for this representation [2]. However, current cDBG implementations are either fast at the cost of a large space, or highly space efficient but either slow or lacking valuable practical features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Healthcare machine learning and text mining (NimbleMiner)</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-healthcare-machine-learning-and-text-mining-nimbleminer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-healthcare-machine-learning-and-text-mining-nimbleminer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our lab develops an open-source text mining software called NimbleMiner (&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/mtopaz/NimbleMiner&#34;&gt;http://github.com/mtopaz/NimbleMiner&lt;/a&gt;). We will work on improving the software using the latest machine learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrated Traffic-Communication Simulator for COSMOS testbed</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-integrated-traffic-communication-simulator-for-cosmos-testbed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-integrated-traffic-communication-simulator-for-cosmos-testbed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vehicle-to-Vehicle (V2V) has received increasing attention with the development of autonomous driving technology. It is believed that multi-vehicular and multi-informative algorithm is the direction of the autonomous driving technology. However, the stability and liability of the communication prevents the future from extensively embracing V2V-based transportation. Rigorous test is required before V2V can actually hit the road.  Compared with the costly field test, simulation tests are more economical and feasible.  To simulate the V2V communication and evaluate the robustness of current V2V-based algorithm, we are therefore developing a simulation platform integrating different commercial software like SUMO, Veins and OMNET++. These software simulate on the actual New York map, and simulate the vehicular communication in different scenarios and platoon configurations.  Our next step is to use this platform to test our own V2V-based algorithms. The output of this research will eventually provide an open platform which would automatically evaluate personally designed algorithm with least manual work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning the most crucial features of the galaxy merger histories</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-learning-the-most-crucial-features-of-the-galaxy-merger-histories/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-learning-the-most-crucial-features-of-the-galaxy-merger-histories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Galaxies in our universe form hierarchically, continuously merging and absorbing smaller galaxies over cosmic time. In this project we aim to identify the most important features of, as well as generate efficient new features from, the merger histories of galaxies. Namely, features that predict (or physically speaking, determine) the properties of galaxies, e.g. their shape or color. This will be done using the results from a large cosmological simulation, IllustrisTNG (www.tng-project.org). We will begin with identifying ways to represent the rich information in the merger history. We will then compare various ML methods oriented towards feature selection or importance analysis: random forests or gradient boosted trees, L1SVM, neural networks (through analysis of e.g. saliency maps). More advanced models can also be applied, such as neural network models designed for feature selection. Finally, we wish to apply / develop methods that can build &amp;lsquo;interpretable&amp;rsquo; new features by constructing them as algebraic formulas from original input features (inspired by e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/324/5923/81&#34;&gt;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/324/5923/81&lt;/a&gt;). The overarching goal is to understand better what in the merger history is most crucial in determining a galaxy&amp;rsquo;s present-day properties, an answer to which can be widely applicable to problems in galaxy formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Locally advanced primary colon, rectosigmoid and rectal cancers: Perioperative outcomes and survival with multivisceral resection</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-locally-advanced-primary-colon-rectosigmoid-and-rectal-cancers-perioperative-outcomes-and-survival-with-multivisceral-resection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-locally-advanced-primary-colon-rectosigmoid-and-rectal-cancers-perioperative-outcomes-and-survival-with-multivisceral-resection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Locally advanced colorectal cancers that invade adjacent organs (i.e., T4 primary tumors) without evidence of distant metastasis account for approximately 5-15% of new colorectal cancers.  There are limited multi-institutional study describing the perioperative complication rates and long-term survival of patients undergoing single organ resection after neoadjuvant chemotherapy and/or radiation versus multivisceral resections for patients with T4 colorectal cancers.  Using the American College of Surgeons National Cancer Database (NCDB), we seek to analyze differential outcomes (perioperative complications and overall survival) by procedure performed, tumor details, pathological findings, chemo-radiotherapy regimens, patient demographics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Liberal Arts: Creating an Index for Higher Education</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project works with a novel corpus of text-based school data to develop a multi-dimensional measure of the degree to which American colleges and universities offer a liberal arts education. We seek a data scientist for various tasks on a project that uses analysis of multiple text corpora to better understand the liberal arts. This is an ongoing three-year project with opportunities for future collaborations, academic publications, and developing and improving existing data science and machine learning skills. Tasks likely include: (1) Using Amazon Web Services to create and maintain cloud-based storage (SQL, S3 buckets) of the project&amp;rsquo;s expanding library of data. (2) Extracting information (named entities, times, places, books, and so on) from millions of plain-text syllabus records. (3) Merging multiple forms of data into a single dataset. (4) Scraping websites for relevant information (e.g., college course offerings, school rankings). Some pages may include dynamically created content that requires the use of a program such as Selenium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poverty Eradication by 2020 in China: Evidence from Big Data</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-poverty-eradication-by-2020-in-china-evidence-from-big-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-poverty-eradication-by-2020-in-china-evidence-from-big-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the Chinese government launched its grand initiative to eradicate rural poverty by 2020. The initiative has made great progress since then, yet little rigorous empirical evidence is available due to data limitations. This project aims to use big data through both official and social media to analyze the trends, achievements, and challenges of this initiative and offer implications for the future and from a comparative perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-Cell Transcriptome Profiling in Atherosclerosis</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-single-cell-transcriptome-profiling-in-atherosclerosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-single-cell-transcriptome-profiling-in-atherosclerosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Atherosclerosis—a chronic inflammatory disease of the artery wall—is the underlying cause of human coronary heart diseases. Cells within atherosclerotic lesions are heterogeneous and dynamic. Their pathological features have been characterized by histology and flow cytometry and more recently, by bulk-tissue omics profiling. Despite this progress, our knowledge of cell types and their roles in atherogenesis remains incomplete because of masking of differences across cells when using genomic measurement at bulk level. Single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) has catalyzed a revolution in understanding of cellular heterogeneity in organ systems and diseases. This project applies scRNA-seq to define the genetic influences on cell subpopulations and functions in atherosclerotic lesion of transgenic mice for candidate risk genes of human coronary heart diseases as inspired by human genomic discoveries. The students involved in this project are expected to work on: (1) analysis of scRNA-seq data using R/Bioconductor packages; (2) Interpretation of the data using pathway and network analysis. Some relevant workflows are available through the &amp;ldquo;Resources&amp;rdquo; page of our lab website at &lt;a href=&#34;https://hanruizhang.github.io/zhanglab/&#34;&gt;https://hanruizhang.github.io/zhanglab/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal simulation and forecasting of renewable energy</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-spatiotemporal-simulation-and-forecasting-of-renewable-energy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-spatiotemporal-simulation-and-forecasting-of-renewable-energy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major obstacle to the decarbonization of the electricity production systems is the multi scale (space and time) variability of wind, solar and hydro energy sources. Much work is being done to understand the high frequency variations in these sources from the perspective of grid integration. However, as with rainfall and other natural systems, these variables can exhibit log-log fractal scaling in space and time, such that the variance of the process increases with temporal duration and with spatial scale. Focusing on high frequency variations thus grossly understates the systemic risk that is associated with these sources. Appropriate national grid design including electricity storage allocation, needs to consider both the periodic annual cycle variations and quasi-periodic inter-annual variability which have larger variance, and the phase lags in these variations across space. The proposed project would explore the development of a multi-level, hierarchical spatio-temporal model for wind or solar using data from the continental USA and its subregions to explore stochastic simulations and multi-scale predictions of the associated risk to inform system design and financial instruments development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waymo &amp; Lyft Driverless Car Data Analysis and Driving Modeling</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-waymo-lyft-driverless-car-data-analysis-and-driving-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-waymo-lyft-driverless-car-data-analysis-and-driving-modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Autonomous driving is developing rapidly. A lot of breakthroughs of autonomous driving have emerged in both academy and industry. However, many traffic accidents related to autonomous driving also occur and cause people’s concern on the safety issue of AV. To ensure safety and reliability, rigorous test and simulation is required before AV can really drive on road. For AV test and simulation, realistic data is an essential component. Comprehensive, multi-regime and sufficient self-driving data would definitely help the AV development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Data for Good” Scholars - a new DSI Scholars initiative</title>
      <link>/2019/03/data-for-good-scholars-a-new-dsi-scholars-initiative/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/data-for-good-scholars-a-new-dsi-scholars-initiative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce a new initiative under the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program: &amp;ldquo;Data for Good&amp;rdquo; undergraduate scholars who will work on projects with societal impacts. For the program&amp;rsquo;s inaugural term, Spring-Summer 2019, we are calling for applications from Columbia and Barnard undergraduate students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for student applications - Spring-Summer 2019</title>
      <link>/2019/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce that the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for Spring-Summer 2019 is open for application. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia University&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master&amp;rsquo;s students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Classifying drug patents</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-classifying-drug-patents/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-classifying-drug-patents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Taking out multiple patents on different aspects of a drug in order to cordon off competitors is standard practice in pharmaceuticals. In addition to primary patents, firms commonly attempt to acquire secondary patents on alternative forms of molecules, different formulations, dosages, and compositions, and new uses Policymakers in the U.S. and globally have raised concerns that these secondary patents can raise drug prices and restrict access to medicines. One challenge to assessing the impact of these patents is it is difficult and costly to know if a given patent is &amp;ldquo;primary&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;secondary.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: A Data-driven Approach for Improving the User Experience of Internet Users</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-a-data-driven-approach-for-improving-the-user-experience-of-internet-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-a-data-driven-approach-for-improving-the-user-experience-of-internet-users/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our lives are heavily reliant on Internet-connected devices and services. However, to deliver the desired user experience over the Internet, network operators need to detect and diagnose various network events (e.g., disruption, outage, misconfiguration, etc.) as well as resolve them in real-time. We have developed an Internet-wide measurement infrastructure that collects performance metrics (e.g., latency, jitter, throughput, packet loss rate, signal strength, etc.) from vantage points deployed by real users (mobile phones, WiFi access points, etc.) at regular intervals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Advancing Public Health Monitoring and Analytics in New York City through Development of a Master Person Index</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-advancing-public-health-monitoring-and-analytics-in-new-york-city-through-development-of-a-master-person-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-advancing-public-health-monitoring-and-analytics-in-new-york-city-through-development-of-a-master-person-index/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Data is central to the NYC Department of Health’s mission to protect and promote the health of all New Yorkers. The agency’s many programs often require large scale record linkages that integrate data from individuals across multiple public health data systems and disease registries. We are implementing a Master Person Index (MPI) system in order to centralize, optimize and standardize matching methodology for administrative data across the Department of Health.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Analysis and Prediction of Opioid Outbreak Clusters</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-analysis-and-prediction-of-opioid-outbreak-clusters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-analysis-and-prediction-of-opioid-outbreak-clusters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are interested in investigating how deaths and hospitalizations resulting from opioid overdoses cluster across space and time in the US. This analysis will be conducted with the aid of two comprehensive databases: 1) detailed mortality data across the US; and 2) a stratified sample of all hospitalizations in the US, which can be subset to select for opioid overdoses. Analyses will be extended to drug type (prescription drugs, fentanyl etc.) and subject demographics (age, race, etc.). We have previously conducted similar cluster analysis for other health phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: ArXivLab: A Platform for Developing and Evaluating Exploratory Tools for the Scientific Literature</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-arxivlab-a-platform-for-developing-and-evaluating-exploratory-tools-for-the-scientific-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-arxivlab-a-platform-for-developing-and-evaluating-exploratory-tools-for-the-scientific-literature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Through ArXivLab we aim to develop the next generation recommender systems for the scientific literature using statistical machine learning approaches. In collaboration with ArXiv we are currently developing a new scholarly literature browser which will be able to extract knowledge implicit in the mathematical and scientific literature, offer advanced mathematical search capabilities and provide personalized recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Discover novel regulators of macrophage efferocytosis by genome-wide CRISPR screen</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-discover-novel-regulators-of-macrophage-efferocytosis-by-genome-wide-crispr-screen/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-discover-novel-regulators-of-macrophage-efferocytosis-by-genome-wide-crispr-screen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Defective efferocytosis, the phagocytic clearance of apoptotic cells, by macrophages is the cause of many human diseases including tumor, autoimmune diseases and atherosclerosis. Enhancing efferocytosis has potential therapeutic benefits. Many key regulators of efferocytosis have been identified, but a systematic approach to map regulators of efferocytosis in an unbiased manner on a genome-wide scale is missing. This project applies innovative genome-wide CRISPR screen to discover novel regulators of macrophage efferocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Discovering the cost function optimized by the primate visual system&#39;s deep hierarchical architecture</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-discovering-the-cost-function-optimized-by-the-primate-visual-system-s-deep-hierarchical-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-discovering-the-cost-function-optimized-by-the-primate-visual-system-s-deep-hierarchical-architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The visual cortex has a distinctive deep hierarchical organization as a result of ontogenetic and phylogenetic optimization. It is unclear what the factors are that shape this particular hierarchical organization. One factor is the compositional and hierarchical nature of our world’s appearance, which may be optimally processed by a hierarchical visual system. Another factor is the need for space and energy efficiency, which constrains the number of neurons and connections. The project will employ computational modeling to understand the contribution of these constraints to shaping the combination of breadth, depth, and skipping connections employed by primate visual cortex.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Discovery of genes associated with progression of bladder cancer</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have been studying bladder cancer in a mouse model of the disease and we are seeking to understand the molecular features of the mouse models as they relate to human bladder cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Distance Metric Learning in Hyperbolic Spaces</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-distance-metric-learning-in-hyperbolic-spaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-distance-metric-learning-in-hyperbolic-spaces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Effective representations and analyses of symbolic data, such as lexical data (words) and networks (graphs), have become of great interest in recent years, due both to advancements in data collection in Natural Language Processing (NLP), and the ubiquity of social networks. Such data often has no natural numerical representation, and is typically described in terms relational expressions or as pairwise similarities. It turns out that finding numerical representations of such data in “Hyperbolic” spaces&amp;mdash;rather than into the more familiar Euclidean spaces&amp;mdash;is a more effective way to preserve valuable relational information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Enhancing Self-Directed Learning Opportunities Using Learning Analytics</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analyze data from one or more of the following Library Applications/Systems and create visualizations that highlight the most important findings related to our goal of supporting self-directed learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Finding Electromagnetic Counterparts to Cosmic Gravitational Wave Sources</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-finding-electromagnetic-counterparts-to-cosmic-gravitational-wave-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-finding-electromagnetic-counterparts-to-cosmic-gravitational-wave-sources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finding the exact counterpart galaxies to merging black hole binaries detected in gravitational waves is one of the most pressing problems in cosmology. The redshift of the host galaxy (which has to be measured from its electromagnetic emission) combined with the luminosity distance to the gravitational wave source allows for a direct measurement of the expansion history of the Universe, an approach commonly referred to as the &amp;lsquo;Standard Siren&amp;rsquo; method. To date, there are no proven techniques for accomplishing this goal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Injury-Disease Interactions in Older Adults</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-injury-disease-interactions-in-older-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-injury-disease-interactions-in-older-adults/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Injury, such as falls, motor vehicle crashes, and drug overdose, is a major source of morbidity and mortality.  The interaction between injury and disease is complex and mutually causative.  For instance, patients with Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease or Parkinson&amp;rsquo;s Disease are known to be at heightened risk of hip fracture from falls and in turn injurious falls among these patients can drastically alter the trajectory of the disease.  So far, research on injury-disease interaction has been scant and fragmented.  The proposed project is aimed at uncovering the gestalt of the relations between different injuries and different diseases through a data science approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Machine learning of clouds</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-machine-learning-of-clouds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-machine-learning-of-clouds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The objective is to use new large cloud-resolving simulations to try and better represent cloud processes in coarse-resolution climate models (~100km in horizontal resolution). Those simulations are global (spanning the entire globe) at 2km resolution and 30-minute output. The data will be hosted on google cloud platform (Pangeo) (the data size is about 50TB). We will in particular evaluate the impact of using Constitutional Neural Network (in time and space) and the capacity for out of sample prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Measuring Broadband</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-measuring-broadband/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-measuring-broadband/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Communications Commission (FCC) and the Census regularly publish data on U.S. Internet availability, performance and use, at granularities from census block to county and state. The project goal is to answer questions based on the available data, such as &amp;ldquo;How reliable is Internet access?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Who is deploying fiber where?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Can we predict reliability of different technologies?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Can we predict the deployment of fiber?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Outcomes of multivisceral resections in colorectal cancer</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-outcomes-of-multivisceral-resections-in-colorectal-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-outcomes-of-multivisceral-resections-in-colorectal-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When a colorectal cancer has grown through the wall of the colon or rectum and into other adjacent tissues or organs, it is identified as a T4 primary tumor.  If there is no evidence of distant metastasis then it is labeled a locally advanced tumor.  Such locally advanced tumors account for approximately 5-15 % of new colorectal cancers.  Surgery remains the principal treatment modality for patients with locally advanced colorectal cancer.  Studies have demonstrated planned en bloc or multivisceral resections rather than intraoperative assessment of margins more likely results in R0 resections leading to better local control and long-term survival.  However, the decision-making for a surgeon confronting a T4 colorectal cancer is challenging because surgery related mortality rates after multivisceral resections are reported up to 12%.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Random Forest vs. Neural Networks for Estimating the Ocean Carbon Sink</title>
      <link>/2019/01/random-forest-vs-neural-networks-for-estimating-the-ocean-carbon-sink/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/random-forest-vs-neural-networks-for-estimating-the-ocean-carbon-sink/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ocean has absorbed the equivalent of 41% of industrial-age fossil carbon emissions. In the future, this rate of this ocean carbon sink will determine how much of mankind’s emissions remain in the atmosphere and drive climate change.  To quantify the ocean carbon sink, surface ocean pCO2 must be known, but cannot be measured from satellite; instead it requires direct sampling across the vast and dangerous oceans. Thus, there will never be enough observations to directly estimate the carbon sink as it evolves. Data science can fill this gap by offering robust approaches to extrapolate from sparse observations to full coverage fields given auxiliary data that can be measured remotely.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Training a deep neural network on large-scale brain imaging and cognition data.</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-training-a-deep-neural-network-on-large-scale-brain-imaging-and-cognition-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-training-a-deep-neural-network-on-large-scale-brain-imaging-and-cognition-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to develop and validate a deep neural network that predicts a child&amp;rsquo;s emotion and cognition. DSI scholars will implement 3D convolutional neural networks on brain imaging data from thousands of children to predict cognitive, emotional, and socio-developmental variables. Statistical evaluation of the model performance will be conducted. The scalable deep neural network analysis will help find brain underpinnings of cognition and emotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Blockchain Anomaly Detection</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-blockchain-anomaly-detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-blockchain-anomaly-detection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project has collected a large set of data (&amp;gt;200GB) from a cryptocurrency block chain.  It is developing methods for detecting anomalies in transactions based on newer Social Networks, Graph Analysis and Machine Learning methods. The work involves data cleaning/wrangling and creation and implementation of various algorithms and analyzing the transactions for identifying different set of anomalies and manipulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data science for better health</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-data-science-for-better-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-data-science-for-better-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our goal is use a large pool of homecare data (including structured data, free text clinical notes, and recorded patient-provider phone conversations) to build predictive models that help identify patients at risk for poor outcomes (like hospital admission or falls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Learning Representations and Patterns in Mathematical Proofs </title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-learning-representations-and-patterns-in-mathematical-proofs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-learning-representations-and-patterns-in-mathematical-proofs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A common challenge for students in heavy proof-based courses is to come up with a long sequence of logical arguments from the problem statement to the final solution. In doing so, they can often skip steps leading to logical leaps or downright incorrect solutions. Ideally the instructor should identify these mis-steps and help students master such proof-based course material. Here we want to take a data-driven approach to address this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Looking for the Weird in TESS</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-looking-for-the-weird-in-tess/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-looking-for-the-weird-in-tess/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year one of my graduate students developed a novel algorithm for detecting &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; signals in photometric time series, such as those taken by NASA&amp;rsquo;s Kepler Mission and now TESS. An undergraduate students will work in my team to run the algorithm on TESS data, which is just starting to be released publicly (&lt;a href=&#34;https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/status.html&#34;&gt;https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/tess/status.html&lt;/a&gt;). We hope to detect strange signatures, possibly including analogs to Tabby&amp;rsquo;s Star, interacting binaries and perhaps even technosignatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Measuring Liberal Arts: Creating an Index for Higher Education</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project works with a novel corpus of text-based school data to develop a multi-dimensional measure of the degree to which American colleges and universities offer a liberal arts education. We seek a data scientist for various tasks on a project that uses analysis of multiple text corpora to better understand the liberal arts. This is an ongoing three-year project with opportunities for future collaborations, academic publications, and developing and improving existing data science and machine learning skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Quantifying Global Risks</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-quantifying-global-risks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-quantifying-global-risks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a globalized world we live in today consequences of catastrophic events easily transgress national borders. Whether it’s a natural disaster, a war or an economic crisis it’s likely to spread out and affect all of us. We propose a framework to model global risks that is not bound to any specific model and is a hybrid of human and machine intelligence. The core of this approach is in using Bayesian Nets of causalities constructed by an analyst equipped with text mining and a map of economic, political and business interconnections.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visualization of continuous health data measurements</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the promise of predictive analytics in healthcare, the lack of continuous internal sensing devices has impeded its realization. With the exception of CGMs, no current commercially available wearable devices yield information intimate to the body. To overcome this deficiency, our research group has developed a minimally invasive wearable device capable of continuous monitoring of glucose and electrolytes in the superficial layer of the skin in an extremely minimally invasive manner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Columbia DBMI Summer Research Fellowship in Biomedical Informatics and Health Data Science</title>
      <link>/2019/01/columbia-dbmi-summer-research-fellowship-in-biomedical-informatics-and-health-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/columbia-dbmi-summer-research-fellowship-in-biomedical-informatics-and-health-data-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://summer.dbmi.columbia.edu&#34;&gt;Columbia Department of Biomedical Informatics (DBMI) Summer Research Fellowship&lt;/a&gt; provides college undergraduate students from a wide range of backgrounds (biology, psychology, engineering, computer science, applied mathematics, statistics, etc.) and rising high-school seniors with fundamental knowledge, hands-on skills, and research experience in biomedical informatics and health data science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Faculty Participation --- DSI Scholars Spring-Summer 2019</title>
      <link>/2018/12/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;call-for-faculty-participation-december-2018&#34;&gt;Call for Faculty Participation. December 2018.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Institute is pleased to call for Faculty Participation in the 2nd cohort of Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for Spring and/or Summer 2019. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage undergraduate and master students to work with Columbia faculty through a data science research internship. The program’s unique enrichment activities will foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enriched Learning Experience for DSI Scholars Summer 2018</title>
      <link>/2018/09/dsi-scholars-summer-2018-meetup-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/09/dsi-scholars-summer-2018-meetup-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DSI Scholars is different from conventional &lt;em&gt;researh experience for students&lt;/em&gt; programs by providing enrichment activities that build a community of data science learning and research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for student applications - DSI Scholars Summer 2018</title>
      <link>/2018/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce the launch of the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for the Inaugural Class of Summer 2018. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Breaking the neural code of a cnidarian</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-breaking-the-neural-code-of-a-cnidarian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-breaking-the-neural-code-of-a-cnidarian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the relation between the activity of all the neurons in the cnidarian hydra and its behavioral repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Technology transfer insights from data</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-technology-transfer-insights-from-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-technology-transfer-insights-from-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CTV’s core mission is to facilitate the transfer of inventions from academic labs to the market for the benefit of society. In a typical year, CTV receives ~400 inventions, completes ~100 licenses and options, and helps form ~20 startups. A good video summary of CTV is here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/110193999&#34;&gt;https://vimeo.com/110193999&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Project ToxicDocs</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-project-toxicdocs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-project-toxicdocs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We house the world&amp;rsquo;s largest dataset of once-secret documents on industrial pollution, unleashed from the vaults of corporations like DuPont, Dow, and Monsanto in toxic tort litigation. We are applying data science methods to analyze and render this material useable to a broad audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: A longitudinal network study of Alzheimer’s and dementia care in relation to disparities and outcomes</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-a-longitudinal-network-study-of-alzheimer-s-and-dementia-care-in-relation-to-disparities-and-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease and related dementia (AD/dementia) represent a looming public health crisis, affecting roughly 5 million people in the U.S. and 11% of older adults. As with other chronic conditions, racial/ethnic and socio-economic disparities exist in the prevalence and burden of illness. However, less is known about how disparities in access to care influence the care trajectories – i.e., the scope, frequency and sequence of services used across healthcare settings – of those with AD/dementia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data Science and the regulation of financial markets (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The development of computational data science
techniques in natural language processing (NLP) and machine
learning (ML) algorithms to analyze large and complex textual
information opens new avenues to study intricate processes,
such as government regulation of financial markets, at a scale
unimaginable even a few years ago. This project develops scalable
NLP and ML algorithms (classification, clustering and
ranking methods) that automatically classify laws into various
codes/labels, rank feature sets based on use case, and induce
best structured representation of sentences for various types of
computational analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Enhancing self-directed learning opportunities</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analyze data from one of the following library applications/systems and create visualizations that highlight the most important findings pertaining to the support of self-directed learning:  Vialogues (TC Video Discussion Application), PocketKnowledge (TC Online Archive), DocDel (E-Reserve System), Pressible (Blogging Platform), Library Website and Mobile App.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Genomic and environmental predictor of preterm birth</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-genomic-and-environmental-predictor-of-preterm-birth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-genomic-and-environmental-predictor-of-preterm-birth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Predicting preterm birth in nulliparous women is challenging and our efforts to develop predictors for that condition from environmental variables produce insufficient classifier accuracy. Recent studies highlight the involvement of common genetic variants in length of pregnancy. This project involves the development of a risk score for preterm birth based on both genetic and environmental attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Global Interconnections Project (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-global-interconnections-project-application-closed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-global-interconnections-project-application-closed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Understand interconnected nature of global multi-national companies via their supply chain, product and services competition, co-investments and co-ownerships as well as other dependencies between operations and revenue streams. We would like to consider the way news on any company specifically propagate down the connection graph and impact other businesses that are related in a way that is not necessarily explicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Internships in DSI Center for Data, Media &amp; Society</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-internships-in-dsi-center-for-data-media-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-internships-in-dsi-center-for-data-media-society/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The DSI Center for Data, Media &amp;amp; Society is seeking undergraduate and masters students during the summer to work on projects at the intersection of Computer Science, Data Science, and the humanities.  These projects will combine domain expertise in the humanities with computer and data science techniques to tackle important societal and media problems.  Projects can vary from documenting human rights violations, providing rural farmers with financial safety-nets, analyzing the sources of social media popularity, and more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Modeling Genomic Evolution with Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-modeling-genomic-evolution-with-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-modeling-genomic-evolution-with-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Fall 2018&lt;/strong&gt; internship is available in the Eaton lab to work on the development and application of machine learning approaches to historical evolutionary inference. Research will involve learning to use high performance distributed computing infrastructure, performing population genetic simulations, fitting machine learning models, and writing reproducible shareable code. The ideal candidate will have experience and interest in Python coding and a reasonable understanding of linear algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Neuronal Ensemble Detection with Temporal CRF (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-neuronal-ensemble-detection-with-temporal-crf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-neuronal-ensemble-detection-with-temporal-crf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given calcium imaging data of active neurons, can we detect groups of co-firing neurons, called neuronal ensembles? We have a number of datasets consisting of hundreds of neurons imaged for thousands of time steps, and seek to extend an existing CRF model to consider temporal relationships. The goal is to be able to detect neuronal ensembles that span multiple time steps, and that are not conditioned on external stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Real time observation and navigation of multitude of autonomous cars, in dense urban traffic intersections with many pedestrians</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-real-time-observation-and-navigation-of-multitude-of-autonomous-cars-in-dense-urban-traffic-intersections-with-many-pedestrians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-real-time-observation-and-navigation-of-multitude-of-autonomous-cars-in-dense-urban-traffic-intersections-with-many-pedestrians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Project components: (i) Monitoring of traffic intersections, using bird’s eye cameras, supported by ultra-low latency computational/communications hubs; (ii) Simultaneous video-based tracking of cars and pedestrians, and prediction of movement based on long-term observations of the intersection; (iii) Real-time computational processing, using deep learning, utilizing GPUs, in support of ii;  (iv) Sub-10ms latency communication between all vehicles and the computational/communication hub, to be used in support of autonomous vehicle navigation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Real-time brain state classification</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-real-time-brain-state-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-real-time-brain-state-classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using machine learning to conduct brain state classification at real-time on EEG/fNIRS/fMRI data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Statistical modeling for dynamic social networks</title>
      <link>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Networked systems are ubiquitous in modern society.  In a dynamic social or biological environment, the interactions among subjects can undergo large and systematic changes. Due to the rapid advancement of technology, a lot of social networks are observed with time information. Some examples include the email communication network between users, comments on Facebook, the retweet activities on Twitter, etc.  We aim to propose new statistical models and associated methodologies for various problems including community detection, change point detection and behavior prediction. The proposed methods will be evaluated on a wide range of network datasets in different areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Analysis pipeline for strain-level microbiome shotgun sequencing</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-analysis-pipeline-for-strain-level-microbiome-shotgun-sequencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-analysis-pipeline-for-strain-level-microbiome-shotgun-sequencing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DNA sequence reads from a community of microbial genomes are currently processed without considering sequence variants. The project involves building a processing pipeline of such billions of short reads, identifying closest strains they might belong to, assembling them into specific clones, calling their variants, and analyzing the dynamic nature of these bacterial strains along sampling points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Healthcare data analytics internship</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-healthcare-data-analytics-internship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-healthcare-data-analytics-internship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently Columbia University, Cornell, and NewYork-Presbyterian have agreed to integrate their clinical (healthcare) and business IT systems onto one shared platform called Epic. The motivating factors to move to Epic are to enhance the patient experience, improve and integrate care, and give our physicians an integrated technology platform that supports the mission of an academic medical center. The intern will assist with developing the “operational” analytics capabilities of Columbia University Medical Center including financial, healthcare operations and healthcare quality analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Human peri-ictal single unit activity</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-human-peri-ictal-single-unit-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-human-peri-ictal-single-unit-activity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Microelectrode array recordings from patients undergoing surgical evaluation have captured typical clinical seizures.  Because of the extreme pathological conditions at these times, identifying single units from extracellular data is a particular challenge.  Our group has developed techniques for tracking neurons through the ictal transition. We are applying them to newly acquired data and addressing fundamental questions about the activity of different cell classes at seizure initiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Informatics approaches to biomedical evidence appraisal using public data</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-informatics-approaches-to-biomedical-evidence-appraisal-using-public-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-informatics-approaches-to-biomedical-evidence-appraisal-using-public-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The quality of biomedical evidence can affect research sustainability, patient safety, and the public&amp;rsquo;s trust in biomedical research. However, often the quality of biomedical evidence remains opaque to the public. It is imperative to improve the transparency of evidence quality. This project aims to leverage the public data sources, including but not limited to The ClinicalTrials.gov, The PubMed database for biomedical literature, The National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) database, and so on, to develop and apply novel data mining and visualization methods for appraising the biomedical research evidence, uncovering implicit biases in clinical research designs at different levels, and presenting this information intuitively to the public.  Students on this project will acquire or hone their skills in data mining, results presentation, and user interface designs and evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Political attitudes and social networks</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-political-attitudes-and-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-political-attitudes-and-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are collecting and analyzing survey data asking people about the political attitudes and other characteristics of their family, friends, and others in their social circles. Some of this work is described &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/unpublished/penumbra_paper_11_clean.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and we are also doing polling relevant to the 2018 midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visual-tactile geometric reasoning</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-visual-tactile-geometric-reasoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-visual-tactile-geometric-reasoning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robotic grasp planning based on raw sensory data is difficult due to occlusion and incomplete scene geometry.  Often one sensory modality does not provide enough context to enable reliable planning.  A single depth sensor image cannot provide information about occluded regions of an object, and tactile information is incredibly sparse spatially.  We are building a Deep Learning CNN that combines both 3D vision and tactile information to perform shape completion of an object seen from a single view only, and plan stable grasps on these completed models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visualization of continuous health data measurements</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ubiquity of current smart and IoT devices has the potential to transform healthcare. For example, current devices can measure continuously activity levels, heart rate, blood oxygen levels, and electrocardiogram. Our lab is developing new devices which can measure additional streams of health data which are currently not possible.  The summer project will involve visualization of this entire set of data, machine learning, and multiparametric data analysis to extract trends that match health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing Columbia DSI Scholars Inaugural Program of Summer 2018</title>
      <link>/2017/12/announcing-columbia-dsi-scholars-inaugural-class-of-summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/announcing-columbia-dsi-scholars-inaugural-class-of-summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;call-for-faculty-participation-december-2017&#34;&gt;Call for Faculty Participation. December 2017.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Institute is pleased to announce the launch of the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for the Inaugural Class of Summer 2018. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage undergraduate and master students to work with Columbia faculty through a data science research internship. The program’s unique enrichment activities will foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>