<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Geospatial Statistics on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/geospatial-statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Geospatial Statistics on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/geospatial-statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Getting It Right: Building Age and Typology for NYC&#39;s Buildings</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-getting-it-right-building-age-and-typology-for-nycs-buildings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-getting-it-right-building-age-and-typology-for-nycs-buildings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting a better approximation of the age of a NYC’s building can improve assigning the building to a structural type that includes type of construction and relevant building code in effect. Mapping the age and type of building would help NYC DOB and the City on a number of fronts, which include enabling NYC DOB to be more effective in enforcing  building and construction safety and evaluating risk when adjacent or nearby subsurface construction is proposed. Furthermore, the more precise characterization of NYC buildings will improve efforts by the City to craft policies aimed at energy efficiency (TWG) as it drives to 80% GHG reductions by 2050 (80X50) and determining natural disaster vulnerability of its building stock (HAZUS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Mapping Construction and Demolition Waste Flows to Re-Use CDW in the City&#39;s Capital Program</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-mapping-construction-and-demolition-waste-flows-to-re-use-cdw-in-the-citys-capital-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-mapping-construction-and-demolition-waste-flows-to-re-use-cdw-in-the-citys-capital-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The State regulates Construction and Demolition Waste (CDW) — its generation, recycling and reuse — and collects all data on CDW.  There is no city source of data for CDW.  For the city to innovate policy with respect to CDW by leveraging its capital program as one way to close material loops, which would generate environmental sustainability and financial sustainability benefits, understanding where CDW goes from the demolition process through the recycling process is the most important single step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Visualization of water quality data as it flows into the NYC drinking water distribution system</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-visualization-of-water-quality-data-as-it-flows-into-the-nyc-drinking-water-distribution-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-visualization-of-water-quality-data-as-it-flows-into-the-nyc-drinking-water-distribution-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DEP uses near real-time water quality data to guide its operations (i.e., the selection and routing of water) to achieve optimum quality for consumers. Historical data is used to evaluate the effectiveness of watershed protection programs, and model predictions of future water quality are used to understand potential impacts to the water supply under different infrastructure and climate scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using ICESat 2 satellite laser altimetry to track storms in Antarctica</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-using-icesat-2-satellite-laser-altimetry-to-track-storms-in-antarctica/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-using-icesat-2-satellite-laser-altimetry-to-track-storms-in-antarctica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The main goal of this work is to assess if storms have increased in frequency over Antarctica. It is theorized that climate change will increase the intensity of the winds and frequency of the storms. With ICESat 2 satellite laser altimetry, we can count the number of storms and blowing snow events. ICESat 2 is a photon counting laser and generates terrabytes of data each day. Innovative data science techniques are needed to handle the data and analyze it. This project is, therefore, a suitable topic for a masters student that combines an important problem in Geophysics and climate science with a great Data Science application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>