<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Summer 2023 on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/summer-2023/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Summer 2023 on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/summer-2023/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Call for Student Applications - Spring-Summer 2023</title>
      <link>/2023/02/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2023/02/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce that the Data Science Institute (DSI) and Data For Good Scholars programs for Spring-Summer 2023 are open for application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia University&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master&amp;rsquo;s students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data For Good Scholars program connects student volunteers to organizations and individuals working for the social good whose projects have developed a need for data science expertise. As &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; problems with real world data, these projects are excellent opportunities for students to learn how data science is practiced outside of the university setting and to learn how to work effectively with people for whom data science sits outside of their subject area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real Time Digital Twin for Smart City Intersections</title>
      <link>/2023/02/project-real-time-digital-twin-for-smart-city-intersections/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2023/02/project-real-time-digital-twin-for-smart-city-intersections/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We research techniques for improving safety of pedestrians, traffic flow, and smart streetscape applications. We aim to accomplish precise localization and tracking of objects by utilizing infrastructure-installed multimodal sensors such as cameras and lidars to provide a global view of the behavior of smart city traffic participants. We rely significantly on traffic intersections which are particularly suitable locations for the deployment of computing, communications, and AI-based services for smart cities of the future. The abundance of data to be collected and processed, in combination with privacy and security concerns, motivates the use of machine learning and deep learning processing, and to deploy the edge-computing paradigm which aligns well with physical intersections in metropolises.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Faculty Participation --- DSI Scholars Spring-Summer 2023</title>
      <link>/2023/01/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2023/01/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;call-for-faculty-participation--spring-summer-2023&#34;&gt;Call for Faculty Participation- Spring-Summer 2023.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Institute is calling for faculty submissions of research projects for the Spring and Summer 2023 sessions of the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage undergraduate and master students to work with Columbia faculty, through the creation of data science research internships. Last year, we worked with over 30 projects and received more than 250 unique applications from Columbia Students. The program&amp;rsquo;s unique enrichment activities foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia. Apply &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSexk3F7EcVWWLsueTuTbLdlLiMdckE-HkKd6HiPNpNdjfjNYg/viewform?usp=sf_link&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
