<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Announcement on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/categories/announcement/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Announcement on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/announcement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Student Applications - Fall 2019</title>
      <link>/2019/09/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-fall-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-fall-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce that the Data Science Institute (DSI) and Data For Good Scholars programs for Fall 2019 are open for application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia University&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master&amp;rsquo;s students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data For Good Scholars program connects student volunteers to organizations and individuals working for the social good whose projects have developed a need for data science expertise. As &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; problems with real world data, these projects are excellent opportunities for students to learn how data science is practiced outside of the university setting and to learn how to work effectively with people for whom data science sits outside of their subject area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Data for Good” Scholars - a new DSI Scholars initiative</title>
      <link>/2019/03/data-for-good-scholars-a-new-dsi-scholars-initiative/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/data-for-good-scholars-a-new-dsi-scholars-initiative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce a new initiative under the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program: &amp;ldquo;Data for Good&amp;rdquo; undergraduate scholars who will work on projects with societal impacts. For the program&amp;rsquo;s inaugural term, Spring-Summer 2019, we are calling for applications from Columbia and Barnard undergraduate students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for student applications - Spring-Summer 2019</title>
      <link>/2019/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce that the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for Spring-Summer 2019 is open for application. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia University&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master&amp;rsquo;s students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Faculty Participation --- DSI Scholars Spring-Summer 2019</title>
      <link>/2018/12/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/call-for-faculty-participation-dsi-scholars-spring-summer-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;call-for-faculty-participation-december-2018&#34;&gt;Call for Faculty Participation. December 2018.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Institute is pleased to call for Faculty Participation in the 2nd cohort of Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for Spring and/or Summer 2019. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage undergraduate and master students to work with Columbia faculty through a data science research internship. The program’s unique enrichment activities will foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for student applications - DSI Scholars Summer 2018</title>
      <link>/2018/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/call-for-student-applications-dsi-scholars-summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Columbia University &lt;a href=&#34;http://datascience.columbia.edu/&#34;&gt;Data Science Institute&lt;/a&gt; is pleased to announce the launch of the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for the Inaugural Class of Summer 2018. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage Columbia&amp;rsquo;s undergraduate and master students in data science research with Columbia faculty through a research internship. The program connects students with research projects across Columbia and provides student researchers with an additional learning experience and networking opportunities. Through unique enrichment activities, this program aims to foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing Columbia DSI Scholars Inaugural Program of Summer 2018</title>
      <link>/2017/12/announcing-columbia-dsi-scholars-inaugural-class-of-summer-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/12/announcing-columbia-dsi-scholars-inaugural-class-of-summer-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;call-for-faculty-participation-december-2017&#34;&gt;Call for Faculty Participation. December 2017.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Data Science Institute is pleased to announce the launch of the Data Science Institute (DSI) Scholars Program for the Inaugural Class of Summer 2018. The goal of the DSI Scholars Program is to engage undergraduate and master students to work with Columbia faculty through a data science research internship. The program’s unique enrichment activities will foster a learning and collaborative community in data science at Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>