<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Excel on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/tags/excel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Excel on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/tags/excel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Identification of genomic and transcriptomic landscape of head and neck cancer</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/01/project-identification-of-genomic-and-transcriptomic-landscape-of-head-and-neck-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/01/project-identification-of-genomic-and-transcriptomic-landscape-of-head-and-neck-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A highly collaborative project is available in Dr. Alison Taylor&amp;rsquo;s and Dr. Fatemeh Momen-Heravi&amp;rsquo;s lab. This project aims to identify molecular changes such as mutations and RNA signature of head and neck cancer in Black/African American and Hispanic minority populations with the goal of identifying novel therapies for cancer patients and reduce health disparities. The project entails analysis of DNA and RNA sequencing data. Basic coding skills are necessary and the student will be mentored by both principal investigators. The prospective candidate should be motivated, a fast learner, and be able to work in a highly collaborative team environment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biomarker discovery for cancer immunotherapy</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Immune checkpoint blockade therapy has shown successful clinical outcomes in the treatment of  various solid tumors such as head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC), melanoma, non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) and others. However, immune checkpoint inhibitors work best in patients who exhibit certain tumor biomarkers. In a collaboration with the Department of Hematology Oncology, the Department of Systems Biology, and the Mailman School of Public Health at Columbia University we aim to identify biomarkers which are associated with treatment outcome in patients with solid tumors who underwent immunotherapy. The project includes bioinformatic analysis of sequencing data. Mentoring and training will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biomechanical indicators of adaptive decision making in children with unilateral cerebral palsy</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-biomechanical-indicators-of-adaptive-decision-making-in-children-with-unilateral-cerebral-palsy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-biomechanical-indicators-of-adaptive-decision-making-in-children-with-unilateral-cerebral-palsy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project will entail data processing and data analysis of behavioral and biomechanical data (collected) from experiments. The goal will be to develop a manuscript for publication at the end of the Spring semester 2021&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
