<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Closed Spring 2021 on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/categories/closed-spring-2021/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Closed Spring 2021 on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/closed-spring-2021/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A global-to-local processing bias in conditions of restricted awareness: the case of symmetry and illusory figures</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-a-global-to-local-processing-bias-in-conditions-of-restricted-awareness-the-case-of-symmetry-and-illusory-figures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-a-global-to-local-processing-bias-in-conditions-of-restricted-awareness-the-case-of-symmetry-and-illusory-figures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A wealth of evidence for the automaticity of perceptual organization processes points toward the existence of a global-to-local processing bias in early perceptual stages. Global features are encoded and spontaneously reported during early conscious vision, resulting in the perception of coherent objects prior to identifying detailed information. Yet, results from experiments that presented illusory figure presentation below the perceptual threshold to study the reliance of perceptual organization on visual awareness have shown conflicting findings, leaving open the question of how global features interact during figure perception. The present study will examine the interaction between symmetry and perceptual completion under conditions of restricted awareness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acute Care and Emergency Referral Systems (ACERS) Project</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-acute-care-and-emergency-referral-systems-acers-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-acute-care-and-emergency-referral-systems-acers-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Acute Care and Emergency Referral Systems (ACERS) Project is a three-year, USAID-funded implementation research and capacity building project that aims to contribute to the improvement in  maternal and newborn survival rates by increasing care-seeking behavior, strengthening emergency referral and dispatch systems, and providing high quality emergency obstetric and newborn care (EmONC) services in the Northern and Oti Regions of Ghana.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing nursing home information technology and quality</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-assessing-nursing-home-information-technology-and-quality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-assessing-nursing-home-information-technology-and-quality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using a validated survey called the Digital IT Maturity Survey, the team is conducting a three-wave, longitudinal, repeated measures survey in a national sample of NHs. Currently, in year 2 of recruitment and analyzing year 1 data. Methods include an examination of the relationships between NH IT Maturity and stages of maturity, and nationally-reported, publicly-available NH Quality Measures available through Nursing Home Compare over three consecutive years. Specific aims are: 1) Explore NH IT maturity using the survey and staging model during a 3-year national assessment 2) Examine if NH IT maturity is associated with CMS quality measures in a national sample of NHs over 3 years. This study includes a survey of NH IT Maturity in a nationally representative sample including 10% of NHs recruited from each state in the United States (N=1,570). Statistical analysis will be done using the software SAS v9 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). Since the sampling method involves stratification by state and since the sampling weights assigned to homes will depend on the number of respondents within each state, the analysis must take the complex sampling design into account. SAS procedures including SURVEYMEANS, SURVEYFREQ, SURVEYLOGISTIC, and SURVEYREG will be used for such analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Broadband funding: racial and economic equity</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-broadband-funding-racial-and-economic-equity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-broadband-funding-racial-and-economic-equity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The federal government spends billions of dollars a year supporting rural broadband (internet access), subsidizing build-out in low-density areas that do not have broadband (unserved areas). However, it is not clear whether the rural areas most in need are receiving a fair share of the funding. Using a very large dataset of broadband availability, census data and recent auction results, the project will analyze whether unserved areas with high racial diversity or lower median income are receiving a fair share of funding. Depending on team size, we will also attempt to create a shareable master data set building on OpenStreetMap and other sources that provides key data points for census units.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of spontaneous animal behaviors from 3D pose estimation data</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-characterization-of-spontaneous-animal-behaviors-from-3d-pose-estimation-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-characterization-of-spontaneous-animal-behaviors-from-3d-pose-estimation-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major goal in neuroscience is to understand how neuronal activity gives rise to behavior. With new technologies, it is possible to record the activity of thousands of neurons simultaneously. However, the interpretation of these data depends on a solid understanding of animal behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of four workflows for structural variants identification</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-comparison-of-four-workflows-for-structural-variants-identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-comparison-of-four-workflows-for-structural-variants-identification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in genomic technologies have led to the identification of many novel disease-gene associations, enabling more precise diagnoses. Along with the technologies enabling rapid DNA sequencing, multiple computational approaches have been developed to identify structural variants (i.e. relatively large deletions and duplications of genomic sequences). These workflows can lead to the identification of different structural variants, raising the risk of missing disease-causing variants when using only one of those methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of three workflows for the identification of genetic variants</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-comparison-of-three-workflows-for-the-identification-of-genetic-variants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-comparison-of-three-workflows-for-the-identification-of-genetic-variants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in genomic technologies have led to the identification of many novel disease-associated genes, enabling more precise diagnoses. Along with the technologies enabling rapid DNA sequencing, multiple computational approaches have been developed to extract the genetic information from raw data, including The Broad Institute&amp;rsquo;s GATK, Seven Bridge&amp;rsquo;s GenomeGraph and Google&amp;rsquo;s DeepVariant. These workflows can lead to the identification of different genetic variants, raising the risk of missing disease-causing variants when using only one of these methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>COVID-19 Evidence Extraction and Computing</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-covid-19-evidence-extraction-and-computing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-covid-19-evidence-extraction-and-computing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the explosive growth of medical literature, making sense of medical evidence is harder than ever. The free text form also makes it difficult to perform evidence retrieval of appraisal. There is a great need for tools and methods that can structure and reason over medical evidence. The goal of this project is to develop computational and symbolic methods to extract evidence from PubMed abstracts, integrate it with evidence derived from real world clinical data (or practice-based evidence), and perform automated knowledge discovery and evidence reasoning. We also hope this research can support evidence-based medicine during the COVID-19 pandemic and provide opportunities for students to hone his/her skills on natural language processing, data mining, deep learning, and semantic knowledge engineering. We have solid preliminary results for the students to build upon. An open-source PICO parser that extracts Population, Intervention, Comparison and Outcome information from PubMed abstracts has been developed and published. Current COVID-19 literature has been downloaded from PubMed and been pre-processed. Preliminary analyses are under way to investigate the patterns in the study populations in COVID-19 clinical studies. Our next steps include but are not limited to evidence summarization at the study level and evidence reasoning at the problem/topic level.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantification of expected bi-allelic genetic variants&#39; rate</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-quantification-of-expected-bi-allelic-genetic-variants-rate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-quantification-of-expected-bi-allelic-genetic-variants-rate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Advances in genomic technologies have led to the identification of many novel disease-gene associations, allowing medical diagnoses to be more precise and tailored to an individual. However, the high number of variants present in each individual represents a significant challenge for the implementation of genomic medicine. The goal of this project is to enable the identification of novel genes associated with recessive disorders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using speech and language to identify patients at risk for hospitalizations and emergency department visits in homecare</title>
      <link>/2021/01/project-using-speech-and-language-to-identify-patients-at-risk-for-hospitalizations-and-emergency-department-visits-in-homecare/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/01/project-using-speech-and-language-to-identify-patients-at-risk-for-hospitalizations-and-emergency-department-visits-in-homecare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This study is the first step in exploring an emerging and previously understudied data stream - verbal communication between healthcare providers and patients. In partnership between Columbia Engineering, School of Nursing, Amazon, and the largest home healthcare agency in the US, the study will investigate how to use audio-recorded routine communications between patients and nurses to help identify patients at risk of hospitalization or emergency department visits. The study will combine speech recognition, machine learning and natural language processing to achieve its goals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
