<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Machine Learning on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Advancing Public Health Monitoring and Analytics in New York City through Development of a Master Person Index</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-advancing-public-health-monitoring-and-analytics-in-new-york-city-through-development-of-a-master-person-index/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-advancing-public-health-monitoring-and-analytics-in-new-york-city-through-development-of-a-master-person-index/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Through a collaboration between Columbia University and the NYC Department of Health and Mental Hygiene (DOHMH), we are seeking a data scientist with JAVA, machine learning and/or SQL skills along with good writing, administrative and organizational abilities to contribute to the developing infrastructure and modeling of an extensible master person index (MPI) and data management solution. The intern would work directly with DOHMH scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Analysis and Prediction of Opioid Outbreak Clusters</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-analysis-and-prediction-of-opioid-outbreak-clusters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-analysis-and-prediction-of-opioid-outbreak-clusters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are interested in investigating how deaths and hospitalizations resulting from opioid overdoses cluster across space and time in the US. This analysis will be conducted with the aid of two comprehensive databases: 1) detailed mortality data across the US; and 2) a stratified sample of all hospitalizations in the US, which can be subset to select for opioid overdoses. Analyses will be extended to drug type (prescription drugs, fentanyl etc.) and subject demographics (age, race, etc.). We have previously conducted similar cluster analysis for other health phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: ArXivLab: A Platform for Developing and Evaluating Exploratory Tools for the Scientific Literature</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-arxivlab-a-platform-for-developing-and-evaluating-exploratory-tools-for-the-scientific-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-arxivlab-a-platform-for-developing-and-evaluating-exploratory-tools-for-the-scientific-literature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Through ArXivLab we aim to develop the next generation recommender systems for the scientific literature using statistical machine learning approaches. In collaboration with ArXiv we are currently developing a new scholarly literature browser which will be able to extract knowledge implicit in the mathematical and scientific literature, offer advanced mathematical search capabilities and provide personalized recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Distance Metric Learning in Hyperbolic Spaces</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-distance-metric-learning-in-hyperbolic-spaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-distance-metric-learning-in-hyperbolic-spaces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Effective representations and analyses of symbolic data, such as lexical data (words) and networks (graphs), have become of great interest in recent years, due both to advancements in data collection in Natural Language Processing (NLP), and the ubiquity of social networks. Such data often has no natural numerical representation, and is typically described in terms relational expressions or as pairwise similarities. It turns out that finding numerical representations of such data in “Hyperbolic” spaces&amp;mdash;rather than into the more familiar Euclidean spaces&amp;mdash;is a more effective way to preserve valuable relational information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Injury-Disease Interactions in Older Adults</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-injury-disease-interactions-in-older-adults/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-injury-disease-interactions-in-older-adults/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Injury, such as falls, motor vehicle crashes, and drug overdose, is a major source of morbidity and mortality.  The interaction between injury and disease is complex and mutually causative.  For instance, patients with Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease or Parkinson&amp;rsquo;s Disease are known to be at heightened risk of hip fracture from falls and in turn injurious falls among these patients can drastically alter the trajectory of the disease.  So far, research on injury-disease interaction has been scant and fragmented.  The proposed project is aimed at uncovering the gestalt of the relations between different injuries and different diseases through a data science approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Machine learning of clouds</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-machine-learning-of-clouds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-machine-learning-of-clouds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The objective is to use new large cloud-resolving simulations to try and better represent cloud processes in coarse-resolution climate models (~100km in horizontal resolution). Those simulations are global (spanning the entire globe) at 2km resolution and 30-minute output. The data will be hosted on google cloud platform (Pangeo) (the data size is about 50TB). We will in particular evaluate the impact of using Constitutional Neural Network (in time and space) and the capacity for out of sample prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Random Forest vs. Neural Networks for Estimating the Ocean Carbon Sink</title>
      <link>/2019/01/random-forest-vs-neural-networks-for-estimating-the-ocean-carbon-sink/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/random-forest-vs-neural-networks-for-estimating-the-ocean-carbon-sink/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ocean has absorbed the equivalent of 41% of industrial-age fossil carbon emissions. In the future, this rate of this ocean carbon sink will determine how much of mankind’s emissions remain in the atmosphere and drive climate change.  To quantify the ocean carbon sink, surface ocean pCO2 must be known, but cannot be measured from satellite; instead it requires direct sampling across the vast and dangerous oceans. Thus, there will never be enough observations to directly estimate the carbon sink as it evolves. Data science can fill this gap by offering robust approaches to extrapolate from sparse observations to full coverage fields given auxiliary data that can be measured remotely.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Learning Representations and Patterns in Mathematical Proofs </title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-learning-representations-and-patterns-in-mathematical-proofs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-learning-representations-and-patterns-in-mathematical-proofs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A common challenge for students in heavy proof-based courses is to come up with a long sequence of logical arguments from the problem statement to the final solution. In doing so, they can often skip steps leading to logical leaps or downright incorrect solutions. Ideally the instructor should identify these mis-steps and help students master such proof-based course material. Here we want to take a data-driven approach to address this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visualization of continuous health data measurements</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the promise of predictive analytics in healthcare, the lack of continuous internal sensing devices has impeded its realization. With the exception of CGMs, no current commercially available wearable devices yield information intimate to the body. To overcome this deficiency, our research group has developed a minimally invasive wearable device capable of continuous monitoring of glucose and electrolytes in the superficial layer of the skin in an extremely minimally invasive manner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data Science and the regulation of financial markets (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The development of computational data science
techniques in natural language processing (NLP) and machine
learning (ML) algorithms to analyze large and complex textual
information opens new avenues to study intricate processes,
such as government regulation of financial markets, at a scale
unimaginable even a few years ago. This project develops scalable
NLP and ML algorithms (classification, clustering and
ranking methods) that automatically classify laws into various
codes/labels, rank feature sets based on use case, and induce
best structured representation of sentences for various types of
computational analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Genomic and environmental predictor of preterm birth</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-genomic-and-environmental-predictor-of-preterm-birth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-genomic-and-environmental-predictor-of-preterm-birth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Predicting preterm birth in nulliparous women is challenging and our efforts to develop predictors for that condition from environmental variables produce insufficient classifier accuracy. Recent studies highlight the involvement of common genetic variants in length of pregnancy. This project involves the development of a risk score for preterm birth based on both genetic and environmental attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Modeling Genomic Evolution with Machine Learning</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-modeling-genomic-evolution-with-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-modeling-genomic-evolution-with-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Fall 2018&lt;/strong&gt; internship is available in the Eaton lab to work on the development and application of machine learning approaches to historical evolutionary inference. Research will involve learning to use high performance distributed computing infrastructure, performing population genetic simulations, fitting machine learning models, and writing reproducible shareable code. The ideal candidate will have experience and interest in Python coding and a reasonable understanding of linear algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Real-time brain state classification</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-real-time-brain-state-classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-real-time-brain-state-classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Using machine learning to conduct brain state classification at real-time on EEG/fNIRS/fMRI data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Statistical modeling for dynamic social networks</title>
      <link>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Networked systems are ubiquitous in modern society.  In a dynamic social or biological environment, the interactions among subjects can undergo large and systematic changes. Due to the rapid advancement of technology, a lot of social networks are observed with time information. Some examples include the email communication network between users, comments on Facebook, the retweet activities on Twitter, etc.  We aim to propose new statistical models and associated methodologies for various problems including community detection, change point detection and behavior prediction. The proposed methods will be evaluated on a wide range of network datasets in different areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visual-tactile geometric reasoning</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-visual-tactile-geometric-reasoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-visual-tactile-geometric-reasoning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robotic grasp planning based on raw sensory data is difficult due to occlusion and incomplete scene geometry.  Often one sensory modality does not provide enough context to enable reliable planning.  A single depth sensor image cannot provide information about occluded regions of an object, and tactile information is incredibly sparse spatially.  We are building a Deep Learning CNN that combines both 3D vision and tactile information to perform shape completion of an object seen from a single view only, and plan stable grasps on these completed models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Visualization of continuous health data measurements</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-visualization-of-continuous-health-data-measurements/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ubiquity of current smart and IoT devices has the potential to transform healthcare. For example, current devices can measure continuously activity levels, heart rate, blood oxygen levels, and electrocardiogram. Our lab is developing new devices which can measure additional streams of health data which are currently not possible.  The summer project will involve visualization of this entire set of data, machine learning, and multiparametric data analysis to extract trends that match health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>