<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Projects Fall 2020 on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/categories/open-projects-fall-2020/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Projects Fall 2020 on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/open-projects-fall-2020/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Biomarker discovery for cancer immunotherapy</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Immune checkpoint blockade therapy has shown successful clinical outcomes in the treatment of  various solid tumors such as head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC), melanoma, non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) and others. However, immune checkpoint inhibitors work best in patients who exhibit certain tumor biomarkers. In a collaboration with the Department of Hematology Oncology, the Department of Systems Biology, and the Mailman School of Public Health at Columbia University we aim to identify biomarkers which are associated with treatment outcome in patients with solid tumors who underwent immunotherapy. The project includes bioinformatic analysis of sequencing data. Mentoring and training will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>California&#39;s Water Data Challenge: Generating User-guided Prediction of Water Supply in the Californian Rivers</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-californias-water-data-challenge-generating-user-guided-prediction-of-water-supply-in-the-californian-rivers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-californias-water-data-challenge-generating-user-guided-prediction-of-water-supply-in-the-californian-rivers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Freshwater supply is critical for managing and meeting human and ecological demands. However, while stocks of water in both natural and artificial reservoirs are helpful for increasing availability, droughts and floods, as well as whiplash events affect reliability on these systems, posing grave consequences on water users. This risk is particularly salient in the state of California, where many local communities have been plagued by extreme hydrological events. In this current research, we contribute to California&amp;rsquo;s Water Data Challenge effort where a diverse group of volunteers convened to form a multi-disciplinary team that addresses the crucial issues of extreme events in California using data science approaches. Members include researchers and professionals who come from a range of backgrounds representing academia and private sectors. We combine a range of publicly available datasets with Machine Learning (ML) techniques to explore predictability of extreme events during California’s water years. More specifically, we use a variety of water districts and showcase how ML prediction models are not only able to predict the flow of water at varying time horizons, they capture uncertainties posed by the climate and human influences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can we detect COVID in the Internet?</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-can-we-detect-covid-in-the-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-can-we-detect-covid-in-the-internet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has changed the way we use the internet, from taking classes to social interactions and entertainment. The FCC publishes a large dataset of network measurements from thousands of homes, with gigabytes of data. The project goal is to analyze the data and answer questions such as: Has the increased usage reduced internet speeds? Can we tell how much people are staying at home from data usage records? Is the increased use of video conferencing reflected in the upload metrics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>China&#39;s War on Poverty</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-chinas-war-on-poverty/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-chinas-war-on-poverty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the Chinese government launched its grand initiative to eradicate rural poverty by 2020. The initiative has made great progress since then, yet little rigorous empirical evidence is available due to data limitations. This project aims to use big data through both official and social media to analyze the trends, achievements, and challenges of this initiative and offer implications for the future and from a comparative perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: African North Americans Database</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-african-north-americans-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-african-north-americans-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is the first comprehensive examination of African North Americans who crossed one of the U.S.-Canada borders, going either direction, after the Underground Railroad, in the generation alive roughly 1865-1930. It analyzes census and other records to match individuals and families across the decades, despite changes or ambiguities in their names, ages, &amp;ldquo;color,&amp;rdquo; birthplace, or other details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Food Insecurity, Obesity, and COVID-19</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-food-insecurity-obesity-and-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-food-insecurity-obesity-and-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New York Presbyterian/Columbia University Irving Medical Center (NYP/CUIMC) serves a high number of racial/ethnic minority and low-income patients. In this project, we will create a data repository of all patients who have completed a universal screen in a clinical encounter for social determinants of health, including food insecurity. The scholar will handle large datasets extracted from the medical record for database creation and data visualizations. The dataset will include patient demographics, food security, and clinical outcomes. This data resource will allow the scholar to partner with researchers to examine predictors of food insecurity, clinical courses, and health outcomes among a large population of patients, including a time period prior to the COVID-19 surge in New York City.  The project will be co-mentored through the members of the University-wide Food Systems Network, a novel collaboration of researchers at the Medical Center, Earth Institute, SIPA, and Teacher&amp;rsquo;s College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Getting It Right: Building Age and Typology for NYC&#39;s Buildings</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-getting-it-right-building-age-and-typology-for-nycs-buildings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-getting-it-right-building-age-and-typology-for-nycs-buildings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting a better approximation of the age of a NYC’s building can improve assigning the building to a structural type that includes type of construction and relevant building code in effect. Mapping the age and type of building would help NYC DOB and the City on a number of fronts, which include enabling NYC DOB to be more effective in enforcing  building and construction safety and evaluating risk when adjacent or nearby subsurface construction is proposed. Furthermore, the more precise characterization of NYC buildings will improve efforts by the City to craft policies aimed at energy efficiency (TWG) as it drives to 80% GHG reductions by 2050 (80X50) and determining natural disaster vulnerability of its building stock (HAZUS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Mapping Construction and Demolition Waste Flows to Re-Use CDW in the City&#39;s Capital Program</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-mapping-construction-and-demolition-waste-flows-to-re-use-cdw-in-the-citys-capital-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-mapping-construction-and-demolition-waste-flows-to-re-use-cdw-in-the-citys-capital-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The State regulates Construction and Demolition Waste (CDW) — its generation, recycling and reuse — and collects all data on CDW.  There is no city source of data for CDW.  For the city to innovate policy with respect to CDW by leveraging its capital program as one way to close material loops, which would generate environmental sustainability and financial sustainability benefits, understanding where CDW goes from the demolition process through the recycling process is the most important single step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: The Cost of Human Rights Violations</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rightscolab.org&#34;&gt;Rights CoLab&lt;/a&gt; is working with the Sustainability Accounting Standards Board (SASB) to develop and define a strengthened set of disclosure standards that investors can use to persuade companies to improve labor rights for both direct employees and workers in their supply chains. The project has two components: a data science project and an Independent Advisory Group. Our coalition of labor experts, data scientists, and SASB partners is focused on improving social disclosure standards that drive real gains in human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Visualization of water quality data as it flows into the NYC drinking water distribution system</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-dfg-visualization-of-water-quality-data-as-it-flows-into-the-nyc-drinking-water-distribution-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-dfg-visualization-of-water-quality-data-as-it-flows-into-the-nyc-drinking-water-distribution-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DEP uses near real-time water quality data to guide its operations (i.e., the selection and routing of water) to achieve optimum quality for consumers. Historical data is used to evaluate the effectiveness of watershed protection programs, and model predictions of future water quality are used to understand potential impacts to the water supply under different infrastructure and climate scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data driven approaches to finding undiagnosed HS patients in EHR</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-data-driven-approaches-to-finding-undiagnosed-hs-patients-in-ehr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-data-driven-approaches-to-finding-undiagnosed-hs-patients-in-ehr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Electronic Health Records (EHR) provide a rich integrated source of phenotypic information that allow for automated extraction and recognition of phenotypes from EHR narratives and provide an efficient framework for conducting epidemiological and clinical studies.  In addition, when EHR are linked to genetic data in electronic biorepositories such as eMERGE and All of US, phenotype information embedded in EHR can be used to efficiently construct cohorts powered for genetic discoveries. However, limitations arise from repurposing data generated from healthcare processes for research, which can include data sparseness, low quality data and diagnostic errors. Phenotyping algorithms are developed to overcome these limitations providing a robust means to assess case status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decode the DNA Methylation in Memory</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-decode-the-dna-methylation-in-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-decode-the-dna-methylation-in-memory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Memory is a basic function of our brain that enables us to use the past experiences to service the present and future on a daily base, and memory function is often disrupted in neurological and psychiatric diseases, such as Alzheimer’s disease and posttraumatic stress disorder. To understand the molecular mechanism of memory storage, we will focus on DNA methylation, a chemical modification of our genome, that is hypothesized to play a critical role for memory. We have identified thousands of DNA methylation changes at numerous genomic loci occurred during the formation of fear and reward memory in the mouse brain. We will develop new computational tools to analyze these changes of DNA methylation and search for the common sequence features of these genomic loci. The result of this project will lead to a systematic understanding of the principle on the function and regulation of DNA methylation in memory, and will pave the way to develop new therapeutic strategies for diseases involved memory defects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deconvolution methods for detecting contamination in microbiome samples</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-deconvolution-methods-for-detecting-contamination-in-microbiome-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-deconvolution-methods-for-detecting-contamination-in-microbiome-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Complex microbial communities play an important role in numerous fields, from human health to bioremediation. One critical challenge in their data analysis is to separate true biological data from contamination of various sources. While contemporary experimental procedures include various negative controls, a comprehensive statistical approach for their analysis has not been developed. Such a framework would have a far-reaching impact on the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deconvolution methods for detecting spatial contamination in microbiome samples</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-deconvolution-methods-for-detecting-spatial-contamination-in-microbiome-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-deconvolution-methods-for-detecting-spatial-contamination-in-microbiome-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Complex microbiomes play an important role in numerous fields. One critical challenge in their data analysis is to separate true biological data from contamination. Contemporary experimental procedures include negative controls from various sources, but their analysis is complicated by “well-to-well” contamination: contamination that associates with the position of samples during experimental procedures. This causes bacteria sampled from a true biological source to appear in nearby control samples, and vice versa. An analytic approach that accounts for this source of contamination would have a far-reaching impact on the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining Aneuploidy from Next-Gen Sequencing</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-defining-aneuploidy-from-next-gen-sequencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-defining-aneuploidy-from-next-gen-sequencing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our lab is interested in aneuploidy, or the incorrect number of whole chromosomes and chromosome arms. A challenge in this area of research is that karyotypes require a large number of proliferating cells for analysis. To address this, our lab and collaborators developed new algorithms to identify aneuploidy alterations from DNA sequencing data. Here, the project goal is to implement these algorithms at Columbia, and subsequently to apply these analysis methods to samples generated in the lab and patient samples. Building on this, the DSI student may also develop new algorithms for use with single-cell sequencing data and RNA sequencing data. Experience in one or more of the following is a must: UNIX, R, and python. The DSI student will be mentored by Dr. Alison Taylor, and he/she will also work closely with all lab members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generating a graph representation of microbial community diversity</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-generating-a-graph-representation-of-microbial-community-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-generating-a-graph-representation-of-microbial-community-diversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the interaction between human-associated microbial communities and human health is expected to revolutionize healthcare. Recent work found that this interaction is, in part, shaped by genetic differences between otherwise identical species in the microbiome. Detecting this variation, however, is a significant challenge. This project aims to profile microbial genetic variation within and across multiple patients&amp;rsquo; microbiomes. This will allow us to better compare and interpret this variation in the context of human disease, gaining mechanistic insight into complex human-microbiome interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identification of genetic variation involved in Mendelian diseases</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-identification-of-genetic-variation-involved-in-mendelian-diseases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-identification-of-genetic-variation-involved-in-mendelian-diseases/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project will focus on the identification of genetic factors involved in various forms of hereditary diseases, including neurodevelopmental disorders, hearing loss, skeletal disorders and more. Some of these children endure years-long diagnostic odysseys of trial-and-error testing with inconclusive results and misdirected treatments. We are dedicated to track down their molecular causes by integrating various “-omics” technologies, including genomics, transcriptomics and epigenomics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identify molecular signiture of head and neck cancer in minority populations</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-identify-molecular-signiture-of-head-and-neck-cancer-in-minority-populations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-identify-molecular-signiture-of-head-and-neck-cancer-in-minority-populations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A highly collaborative project is available in Dr. Alison Taylor’s and Dr. Fatemeh Momen-Heravi’s lab. This project aims to identify molecular changes such as mutations and RNA signature of head and neck cancer in Black/African American and Hispanic minority populations with the goal of identifying novel therapies for cancer patients and reduce health disparities. The project entails analysis of DNA and RNA sequencing data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Liberal Arts: Creating an Index for Higher Education</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-measuring-liberal-arts-creating-an-index-for-higher-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project works with a novel corpus of text-based school data to develop a multi-dimensional measure of the degree to which American colleges and universities offer a liberal arts education. We seek a data scientist for various tasks on a project that uses analysis of multiple text corpora to better understand the liberal arts. This is an ongoing three-year project with opportunities for future collaborations, academic publications, and developing and improving existing data science and machine learning skills. Tasks likely include: (1) Using Amazon Web Services to create and maintain cloud-based storage (SQL, S3 buckets) of the project&amp;rsquo;s expanding library of data. (2) Extracting information (named entities, times, places, books, and so on) from millions of plain-text syllabus records. (3) Merging multiple forms of data into a single dataset. (4) Scraping websites for relevant information (e.g., college course offerings, school rankings). Some pages may include dynamically created content that requires the use of a program such as Selenium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physically-informed polycrystal plasticity models of beta-HMX</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-physically-informed-polycrystal-plasticity-models-of-beta-hmx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-physically-informed-polycrystal-plasticity-models-of-beta-hmx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, these types of data are routinely neglected in hand-crafted constitutive models due to the complexity. Instead, descriptors such as void fraction, dislocation density, and other statistical measures of the microstructures are often incorporated into yield surface or hardening rules (e.g. Gurson damage model, critical state plasticity). In this work, we will overcome this technical barrier by using a deep convolutional neural network to deduce low-dimensional descriptors that best describes the physics of the deformation process of polycrystals. With deep Q reinforcement learning to automate the trial-and-error process, we may explore the decision tree with a large number of trials that are impossible to be done manually. This treatment will empower us to discover the underlying mechanics of polycrystals under a variety of pressure, temperature, and loading rates highly relevant to the Air Force applications. While previous work on data-driven models has often focused on complete substitutions of constitutive laws with a data-driven paradigm, I intend to seek the best option representing the hierarchy of material responses, while implementing adversarial attacks to determine hidden weaknesses of existing polycrystal plasticity models as well as the one generated from the ML approaches. I will make use of a collocation Fast Fourier Transformation (FFT) solver to speed up the generations of the material database, digesting microstructural data via descriptors in the non-Euclidean space, Graph-based knowledge abstraction, and adversarial attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prediction of microbial communities metabolic output</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-prediction-of-microbial-communities-metabolic-output/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-prediction-of-microbial-communities-metabolic-output/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The human microbiome is associated with different diseases, but the metabolic mechanisms through which it can modulate health are mostly unknown. Understanding these mechanisms is of paramount importance for prevention and treatment. While metagenomics analysis provides associations between microbial presence and specific diseases, metabolomics analysis can highlight metabolic alterations. None of the two, however, can unveil microbiome metabolic mechanisms associated with these detected alterations. In an attempt to fill this knowledge gap, several microbiome metabolic modeling methods were recently developed. An accurate evaluation of the accuracy of such methods in relation to different pathologies and microbiomes was never conducted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors associated with aggressive forms of head and neck cancer</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-risk-factors-associated-with-aggressive-forms-of-head-and-neck-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-risk-factors-associated-with-aggressive-forms-of-head-and-neck-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A translational medical informatic project is available to identify risk factors associated with head and neck cancer and lung cancer in electronic medical records. Projects include data extraction, data curation, and establishing and maintaining a database of biospecimens and patients&amp;rsquo; characteristics. Statistical analysis and modeling will be done to identify clinical characteristics and risk factors which are associated with aggressive form of tumors. Training and mentorship will be provided. Prospective candidates should have great communication skills, willingness to work in a highly collaborative environment, and have excellent time management and organizational skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single cell RNA-seq analysis of eye development and disease</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-single-cell-rna-seq-analysis-of-eye-development-and-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-single-cell-rna-seq-analysis-of-eye-development-and-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Single cell sequencing has generated unprecedented insight into the cellular complexity of normal and diseased organ. We are interested in using this technique to understand the mechanisms of eye development, disease and regeneration. We also would like to compare the transcriptomic signatures between mouse models and human tissues. This project involves analysis of large amount of data from single cell sequencing. It requires understanding of statistical analysis and proficient programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-nucleus and spatial transcriptomics analysis of APOE mouse and human brain samples</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-single-nucleus-and-spatial-transcriptomics-analysis-of-apoe-mouse-and-human-brain-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-single-nucleus-and-spatial-transcriptomics-analysis-of-apoe-mouse-and-human-brain-samples/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are conducting a large-scale study analyzing brain tissues from mice and humans with different APOE genotypes, using both single-nucleus sequencing and spatial transcriptomics to assess RNA expression differences caused by APOE genotype. We are working with an expert bioinformatics core, but would like a data science student to help perform the analyses and act as an in-lab lead for the bioinformatics analysis. Prior experience analyzing RNA-sequencing data is preferred, but not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using machine learning to understand tropical cyclone genesis pathways</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-using-machine-learning-to-understand-tropical-cyclone-genesis-pathways/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-using-machine-learning-to-understand-tropical-cyclone-genesis-pathways/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until today there is no comprehensive theory for formation of tropical cyclones (hurricanes, typhoons). Therefore, it is common to use statistical methods to derive empirical indices as proxies for the probability for genesis. There are also different types of genesis pathways that have been explored in ad-hoc manner. I would like to explore the possibility of using machine learning to explore tropical cyclone genesis, in particular the different pathways in a more comprehensive manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using social network analysis to improve access to mental health treatment in Brazil</title>
      <link>/2020/09/project-using-social-network-analysis-to-improve-access-to-mental-health-treatment-in-brazil/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/09/project-using-social-network-analysis-to-improve-access-to-mental-health-treatment-in-brazil/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The proposed project would focus on analyzing quantitative data from a 4 year NIMH-funded study entitled &amp;ldquo;Integrating evidence-based  depression treatment in primary care: Tuberculosis (TB) in Brazil as a model&amp;rdquo; (PI: Sweetland, K01MH104514). The aim of the study was to assess whether social network analysis could be used to leverage the receptivity and connectivity of TB providers in a Brazilian public health system in a way that could accelerate the adoption (implementation) and diffusion (dissemination) of an evidence-based treatment for depression treatment in a primary care network. Baseline receptivity was operationalized via six brief quantitative scales to measure mental health literacy, work self-efficacy, organizational climate, attitudes towards evidence-based practices, organizational readiness to change and individual innovation thresholds. Connectivity was assessed by asking TB providers with whom they discuss difficult cases, give advice to, or receive advice regarding difficult TB cases. Baseline receptivity and connectivity data was used to identify 3 pilot sites in which to train primary care providers to deliver evidence-based depression treatment for one year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>