<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data For Good on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/data-for-good/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data For Good on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/data-for-good/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: African North Americans Database</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/09/project-dfg-african-north-americans-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/09/project-dfg-african-north-americans-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is the first comprehensive examination of African North Americans who crossed one of the U.S.-Canada borders, going either direction, after the Underground Railroad, in the generation alive roughly 1865-1930. It analyzes census and other records to match individuals and families across the decades, despite changes or ambiguities in their names, ages, &amp;ldquo;color,&amp;rdquo; birthplace, or other details.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: African North Americans Database</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/01/project-dfg-african-north-americans-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/01/project-dfg-african-north-americans-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is the first comprehensive examination of African North Americans who crossed one of the U.S.-Canada borders, going either direction, after the Underground Railroad, in the generation alive roughly 1865-1930. It analyzes census and other records to match individuals and families across the decades, despite changes or ambiguities in their names, ages, &amp;ldquo;color,&amp;rdquo; birthplace, or other details.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Identifying New York City Retaining Walls</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/01/project-dfg-identifying-new-york-city-retaining-walls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/01/project-dfg-identifying-new-york-city-retaining-walls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Retaining walls are structures designed to restrain soil to a slope that it would not naturally keep to.
They were used to facilitate the city’s development in hilly areas. Students may be familiar with the
Morningside Park retaining wall , present immediately East of the Columbia campus. Retaining walls
facing streets are mapped and inspected. Not so retaining walls supporting soil at back yards. Because
the NYC Building Department is not aware of the presence of most, they are not inspected and left to
decay. A fatal collapse occurred in October 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Mapping Construction and Demolition Waste Flows to Re-Use CDW in the City&#39;s Capital Program</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/01/project-dfg-mapping-construction-and-demolition-waste-flows-to-re-use-cdw-in-the-citys-capital-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2021/01/project-dfg-mapping-construction-and-demolition-waste-flows-to-re-use-cdw-in-the-citys-capital-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New York State regulates construction and demolition waste (CDW)—its generation, recycling and reuse—and collects all data on CDW from private waste haulers and transfer stations/recycling facilities. There is no city source of data for CDW. For the city to innovate policy with respect to CDW, which is a source of embedded carbon, by leveraging its capital program to close material loops, generating environmental sustainability and financial sustainability benefits, it is important to understand where CDW goes after the demolition process through the transfer and recycling processes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: African North Americans Database</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-african-north-americans-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-african-north-americans-database/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is the first comprehensive examination of African North Americans who crossed one of the U.S.-Canada borders, going either direction, after the Underground Railroad, in the generation alive roughly 1865-1930. It analyzes census and other records to match individuals and families across the decades, despite changes or ambiguities in their names, ages, &amp;ldquo;color,&amp;rdquo; birthplace, or other details.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Developing Predictive Model for Project Cost Estimate</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-developing-predictive-model-for-project-cost-estimate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-developing-predictive-model-for-project-cost-estimate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;NYC DDC has initiated a machine learning project to develop predictive model for estimating cost of project and work items. Using the latest technique in Machine Learning and Advanced Statistics, NYC DDC to develop a model that predicts the cost of future and active projects and construction work items in different phases of the lifecycle of the project based on historical data. DDC has partnered with Microsoft who is providing the proof of concept guidance and making tools available for the proof of concept development. DDC is seeking assistance of a data scientist from the Town and Gown program to develop the model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Food Insecurity, Obesity, and COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-food-insecurity-obesity-and-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-food-insecurity-obesity-and-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New York Presbyterian/Columbia University Irving Medical Center (NYP/CUIMC) serves a high number of racial/ethnic minority and low-income patients. In this project, we will create a data repository of all patients who have completed a universal screen in a clinical encounter for social determinants of health, including food insecurity. The scholar will handle large datasets extracted from the medical record for database creation and data visualizations. The dataset will include patient demographics, food security, and clinical outcomes. This data resource will allow the scholar to partner with researchers to examine predictors of food insecurity, clinical courses, and health outcomes among a large population of patients, including a time period prior to the COVID-19 surge in New York City.  The project will be co-mentored through the members of the University-wide Food Systems Network, a novel collaboration of researchers at the Medical Center, Earth Institute, SIPA, and Teacher&amp;rsquo;s College.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Getting It Right: Building Age and Typology for NYC&#39;s Buildings</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-getting-it-right-building-age-and-typology-for-nycs-buildings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-getting-it-right-building-age-and-typology-for-nycs-buildings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting a better approximation of the age of a NYC’s building can improve assigning the building to a structural type that includes type of construction and relevant building code in effect. Mapping the age and type of building would help NYC DOB and the City on a number of fronts, which include enabling NYC DOB to be more effective in enforcing  building and construction safety and evaluating risk when adjacent or nearby subsurface construction is proposed. Furthermore, the more precise characterization of NYC buildings will improve efforts by the City to craft policies aimed at energy efficiency (TWG) as it drives to 80% GHG reductions by 2050 (80X50) and determining natural disaster vulnerability of its building stock (HAZUS).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Mapping Construction and Demolition Waste Flows to Re-Use CDW in the City&#39;s Capital Program</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-mapping-construction-and-demolition-waste-flows-to-re-use-cdw-in-the-citys-capital-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-mapping-construction-and-demolition-waste-flows-to-re-use-cdw-in-the-citys-capital-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The State regulates Construction and Demolition Waste (CDW) — its generation, recycling and reuse — and collects all data on CDW.  There is no city source of data for CDW.  For the city to innovate policy with respect to CDW by leveraging its capital program as one way to close material loops, which would generate environmental sustainability and financial sustainability benefits, understanding where CDW goes from the demolition process through the recycling process is the most important single step.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Operationalize Project Cash Flow Model</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-operationalize-project-cash-flow-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-operationalize-project-cash-flow-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with DDC, Microsoft AI team has developed a predictive machine learning model that forecasts monthly distribution of cash flow for DDC’s active projects. DDC intends to operationalize this model and possibly integrate into our dashboards.  Assistance is needed of a data scientist to collaborate with DDC in operationalizing the model whereby DDC can prepare the visuals and data scientist can assist with operationalizing the machine learning components.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: The Cost of Human Rights Violations</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-the-cost-of-human-rights-violations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rightscolab.org&#34;&gt;Rights CoLab&lt;/a&gt; is working with the Sustainability Accounting Standards Board (SASB) to develop and define a strengthened set of disclosure standards that investors can use to persuade companies to improve labor rights for both direct employees and workers in their supply chains. The project has two components: a data science project and an Independent Advisory Group. Our coalition of labor experts, data scientists, and SASB partners is focused on improving social disclosure standards that drive real gains in human rights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Visualization of water quality data as it flows into the NYC drinking water distribution system</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-visualization-of-water-quality-data-as-it-flows-into-the-nyc-drinking-water-distribution-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-dfg-visualization-of-water-quality-data-as-it-flows-into-the-nyc-drinking-water-distribution-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DEP uses near real-time water quality data to guide its operations (i.e., the selection and routing of water) to achieve optimum quality for consumers. Historical data is used to evaluate the effectiveness of watershed protection programs, and model predictions of future water quality are used to understand potential impacts to the water supply under different infrastructure and climate scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
