<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cancer on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/tags/cancer/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cancer on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/tags/cancer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Biomarker discovery for cancer immunotherapy</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-biomarker-discovery-for-cancer-immunotherapy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Immune checkpoint blockade therapy has shown successful clinical outcomes in the treatment of  various solid tumors such as head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC), melanoma, non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) and others. However, immune checkpoint inhibitors work best in patients who exhibit certain tumor biomarkers. In a collaboration with the Department of Hematology Oncology, the Department of Systems Biology, and the Mailman School of Public Health at Columbia University we aim to identify biomarkers which are associated with treatment outcome in patients with solid tumors who underwent immunotherapy. The project includes bioinformatic analysis of sequencing data. Mentoring and training will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identify molecular signiture of head and neck cancer in minority populations</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-identify-molecular-signiture-of-head-and-neck-cancer-in-minority-populations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-identify-molecular-signiture-of-head-and-neck-cancer-in-minority-populations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A highly collaborative project is available in Dr. Alison Taylor’s and Dr. Fatemeh Momen-Heravi’s lab. This project aims to identify molecular changes such as mutations and RNA signature of head and neck cancer in Black/African American and Hispanic minority populations with the goal of identifying novel therapies for cancer patients and reduce health disparities. The project entails analysis of DNA and RNA sequencing data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors associated with aggressive forms of head and neck cancer</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-risk-factors-associated-with-aggressive-forms-of-head-and-neck-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/09/project-risk-factors-associated-with-aggressive-forms-of-head-and-neck-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A translational medical informatic project is available to identify risk factors associated with head and neck cancer and lung cancer in electronic medical records. Projects include data extraction, data curation, and establishing and maintaining a database of biospecimens and patients&#39; characteristics. Statistical analysis and modeling will be done to identify clinical characteristics and risk factors which are associated with aggressive form of tumors. Training and mentorship will be provided. Prospective candidates should have great communication skills, willingness to work in a highly collaborative environment, and have excellent time management and organizational skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
