<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open  2022 on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/open-2022/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open  2022 on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/categories/open-2022/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Application of Gaussian Mixture Regression to obtain useful, actionable air pollution data from consumer-grade, low-cost monitoring devices</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-application-of-gaussian-mixture-regression-to-obtain-useful-actionable-air-pollution-data-from-consumer-grade-low-cost-monitoring-devices/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-application-of-gaussian-mixture-regression-to-obtain-useful-actionable-air-pollution-data-from-consumer-grade-low-cost-monitoring-devices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our primary objective for this work will be to build a GMR model that can correct for bias in low cost particulate matter (PM2.5) sensors to be used globally. We will select 5-10 diverse reference PM2.5 and low cost PM2.5 co-locations to build a Gaussian Mixture Regression model (GMR). Recently, our team showed that GMR provides a higher quality correction factor for PurpleAir PM2.5 sensors than multiple linear regression and random forest, in terms of both correlation and accuracy. We then plan to evaluate this model on at least 20 independent co-location datasets that the GMR has not seen. There has been an exciting recent rise in commercially available low-cost sensors (LCS), such as PurpleAir (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.purpleair.com&#34;&gt;www.purpleair.com&lt;/a&gt;) and Clarity sensors, which when paired with machine learning (ML) based correction algorithms demonstrate high accuracy compared to co-located reference grade monitors5,6. So far, these corrections have been limited to the few LCS locations which are co-located with expensive reference-grade monitors, while the potential from the thousands of un-co-located sensors remains untapped. PurpleAir and similar devices have been deployed all over the world. Ideally our global correction factor will allow for the extraction of more trustworthy data from huge open-access databases of air pollution data such as PurpleAir.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>D-Hacking</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-d-hacking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-d-hacking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has long been recognized that there could be a tradeoff between optimizing the accuracy of machine learning predictions and satisfying definitions of fairness for protected or vulnerable groups. This tradeoff has led to an increased interest in finding models that both perform well while also exhibiting fairness properties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Using NLP to Reveal the Cost of Corporate Human Rights Violations</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-dfg-using-nlp-to-reveal-the-cost-of-corporate-human-rights-violations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-dfg-using-nlp-to-reveal-the-cost-of-corporate-human-rights-violations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rights CoLab (&lt;a href=&#34;https://rightscolab.org/&#34;&gt;https://rightscolab.org/&lt;/a&gt;) is working with the Sustainability Accounting Standards Board (SASB) to define a strengthened set of disclosure standards that investors can use to persuade companies to improve labor rights for both their workforce and workers in supply chains. The project has two components: 1) a data science project, and 2) an Expert Group.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting inherited compound heterozygous variants</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-detecting-inherited-compound-heterozygous-variants/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-detecting-inherited-compound-heterozygous-variants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the methods to identify novel gene-disease associations is called “trio analysis”, when an affected child (proband) and both his/her parents DNA are sequenced. The genetic information from the child and his/her parents allows for the rapid identification of compound heterozygous variants (i.e. 2 variants in the same gene, one inherited from the mother and the other one from the father).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development of a Pediatric Cardiology Patient Passport Smartphone Application</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-development-of-a-pediatric-cardiology-patient-passport-smartphone-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-development-of-a-pediatric-cardiology-patient-passport-smartphone-application/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project aims to create/develop a smartphone application for use with our pediatric cardiology patients. The application would be a &amp;ldquo;patient passport,&amp;rdquo; which essentially would be a snapshot of their most critical medical information. It will not be linked to the clinical health records; rather, it needs to be a template with various questions that we would create (name, diagnosis, surgeries, current medications, etc). The doctor would fill out the information with the patient, and it would then be saved on the patient&amp;rsquo;s phone for them to show other healthcare professionals. We are looking for a student who can help us design this app (from a technological perspective) and get it up and running. It would need to be encrypted and password protected.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generating a 3D atlas of the salamander brain</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-generating-a-3d-atlas-of-the-salamander-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-generating-a-3d-atlas-of-the-salamander-brain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The brain is the most complex organ of the body, and hosts a multitude of cell types organized in functionally-specialized brain regions. So far, systematic attempts to describe the complexity of the brain have been limited to a few species, including mouse and the fruit fly. Extending the description of brains to multiple species is essential to identify evolutionarily-conserved principles of brain organization and function.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personalized nutritional recommendations in diabetes</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-personalized-nutritional-recommendations-in-diabetes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-personalized-nutritional-recommendations-in-diabetes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This team project aims to investigate different approaches to presenting individuals with daily suggestions for meeting their nutritional goals. Specifically, we are interested in developing new mechanisms for choosing suggestions that satisfy an individual’s’ preferences and habits (e.g., similar to an individual’s previous meals, based on the analysis of textual meal descriptions), comparing effectiveness of meal recommendations that are expressed as text versus those expressed as images of meals, and developing ways to balance an individual’s preferences with exposing them to new meal ideas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renewable Scenario Generation using Generative Adversarial Network</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-renewable-scenario-generation-using-generative-adversarial-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-renewable-scenario-generation-using-generative-adversarial-network/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project will use Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) to generate space-time correlated renewable generation scenarios. The student will gather historical wind speed and solar radiation data from Texas, and train a GAN to generate scenarios. The student will also investigate the scenario correlation with temperature, and use average temperature as a key feature for scenario generation, and benchmark it with alternative scenario generation approaches. This effort is part of a storage valuation project funded by DSI Seed Grant in 2022, in which these generated scenarios will be used for performing storage valuation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Justice Assessment of Flood Risk and Benefits</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-social-justice-assessment-of-flood-risk-and-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-social-justice-assessment-of-flood-risk-and-benefits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Discriminatory development policies have systematically relegated certain populations to undesirable locations including low elevation areas at risk of flooding. As the climate changes, many properties will no longer be inhabitable and others, especially houses in floodplains, will suffer damage due to more frequent and significant flooding. Current U.S. federal policy funds flood risk mitigation measures, such as property  acquisition, relocation and retrofitting, however depending on various factors at the sub-county level, these actions can have disproportionate benefit to high income areas and not extend to vulnerable populations. We investigate patterns related to potential disproportionate availability and access to government linked programs, exploring different types of climatic factors using flood insurance claims data from NFIP. Work with the intern will build off existing research on programmatic wide and event specific analysis in the Carolinas to explore patterns that may be of interest specifically to state and county level decision makers to evaluate how communities are benefiting from existing programs and to ensure equity. We plan to publish an event specific research article using high resolution data on the distribution of risks and benefits following a major disaster.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structural variant detection in neurological disorders</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-structural-variant-detection-in-neurological-disorders/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-structural-variant-detection-in-neurological-disorders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Structural variants (SVs) are large genomic alterations which can be implicated in disease. This project will focus on using novel genomic techniques to identify structural variants in genomic cold cases with neurological disorders. These &amp;ldquo;cold&amp;rdquo; cases which have previously remained unsolved with standard genomic approaches. We will use optical genome mapping and long read sequencing, together with novel bioinformatic techniques to detect and analyze structural variants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer Research Experiences for Undergraduates</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-summer-research-experiences-for-undergraduates/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-summer-research-experiences-for-undergraduates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;LEAP will offer research experiences for undergraduate students as summer research internships as part of LEAP&amp;rsquo;s research through synergistic innovations in data science and climate science. This includes, but is not limited to, physics-informed and causally-informed machine learning, novel ML-based subgrid parameterizations for Earth System Models, global parameter inference, and new ML- based diagnostics and metrics for evaluating these models, with a focus on the Community Earth System Model (CESM). The center is committed to building a diverse research community at the intersection of geosciences and data sciences with the objective to build a LEAP community on par with the US population in terms of gender and race diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Human Capital and Culture in the Fund Industry</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-understanding-human-capital-and-culture-in-the-fund-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-understanding-human-capital-and-culture-in-the-fund-industry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Asset management companies have been among the largest investors in the financial market. With $89 trillion in assets under management, this industry has been experiencing rapid changes. For example, many firms started enlarging the technological capabilities to improve decision-making, data management, and client experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Design and Children’s Mobility and Crash Risks in US Cities</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-urban-design-and-childrens-mobility-and-crash-risks-in-us-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-urban-design-and-childrens-mobility-and-crash-risks-in-us-cities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Road traffic crashes involving child passengers, child pedestrians, and child bicyclists are the leading cause of death for people aged 5 to 15 years in the USA. A total of 10,344 children died on US roads in the decade from 2010-2019; a further 4.2 million were hospitalized. Urban design—meaning the overall physical form of cities—is a modifiable environmental feature that can be changed to reduce the immense burden due to child road traffic injuries. Altering the overall configuration of a city’s transportation network affects the way children and other road users routinely travel through urban space, thereby altering children’s risks for being injured or killed in a road traffic crash.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weather Effects on High Frequency Communication Links</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-weather-effects-on-high-frequency-communication-links/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2022/01/project-weather-effects-on-high-frequency-communication-links/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Future wireless networks will use high-frequency millimeter-wave (mmWave) links for transmitting and receiving information with high throughput. A key difference between mmWave links and conventional sub-6GHz links is that mmWave links are severely affected by weather conditions. Students working on this project will use a state-of-the-art mmWave radar to assess the impact of wind speed, temperature, humidity, and other factors on the high-frequency link. The end goal of the project is to develop a classifier that can infer weather conditions based on the signal received from the mmWave radar. In this project, students are expected to learn how the mmWave radar works, design experiments to obtain labeled data, perform measurements, and develop the classifier.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
