<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Analysis and Prediction of Opioid Outbreak Clusters</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-analysis-and-prediction-of-opioid-outbreak-clusters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-analysis-and-prediction-of-opioid-outbreak-clusters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are interested in investigating how deaths and hospitalizations resulting from opioid overdoses cluster across space and time in the US. This analysis will be conducted with the aid of two comprehensive databases: 1) detailed mortality data across the US; and 2) a stratified sample of all hospitalizations in the US, which can be subset to select for opioid overdoses. Analyses will be extended to drug type (prescription drugs, fentanyl etc.) and subject demographics (age, race, etc.). We have previously conducted similar cluster analysis for other health phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Discover novel regulators of macrophage efferocytosis by genome-wide CRISPR screen</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-discover-novel-regulators-of-macrophage-efferocytosis-by-genome-wide-crispr-screen/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-discover-novel-regulators-of-macrophage-efferocytosis-by-genome-wide-crispr-screen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Defective efferocytosis, the phagocytic clearance of apoptotic cells, by macrophages is the cause of many human diseases including tumor, autoimmune diseases and atherosclerosis. Enhancing efferocytosis has potential therapeutic benefits. Many key regulators of efferocytosis have been identified, but a systematic approach to map regulators of efferocytosis in an unbiased manner on a genome-wide scale is missing. This project applies innovative genome-wide CRISPR screen to discover novel regulators of macrophage efferocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Discovery of genes associated with progression of bladder cancer</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have been studying bladder cancer in a mouse model of the disease and we are seeking to understand the molecular features of the mouse models as they relate to human bladder cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Measuring Broadband</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-measuring-broadband/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-measuring-broadband/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Communications Commission (FCC) and the Census regularly publish data on U.S. Internet availability, performance and use, at granularities from census block to county and state. The project goal is to answer questions based on the available data, such as &amp;ldquo;How reliable is Internet access?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Who is deploying fiber where?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Can we predict reliability of different technologies?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Can we predict the deployment of fiber?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data science for better health</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-data-science-for-better-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-data-science-for-better-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our goal is use a large pool of homecare data (including structured data, free text clinical notes, and recorded patient-provider phone conversations) to build predictive models that help identify patients at risk for poor outcomes (like hospital admission or falls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Technology transfer insights from data</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-technology-transfer-insights-from-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-technology-transfer-insights-from-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CTV’s core mission is to facilitate the transfer of inventions from academic labs to the market for the benefit of society. In a typical year, CTV receives ~400 inventions, completes ~100 licenses and options, and helps form ~20 startups. A good video summary of CTV is here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/110193999&#34;&gt;https://vimeo.com/110193999&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data Science and the regulation of financial markets (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The development of computational data science
techniques in natural language processing (NLP) and machine
learning (ML) algorithms to analyze large and complex textual
information opens new avenues to study intricate processes,
such as government regulation of financial markets, at a scale
unimaginable even a few years ago. This project develops scalable
NLP and ML algorithms (classification, clustering and
ranking methods) that automatically classify laws into various
codes/labels, rank feature sets based on use case, and induce
best structured representation of sentences for various types of
computational analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Enhancing self-directed learning opportunities</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analyze data from one of the following library applications/systems and create visualizations that highlight the most important findings pertaining to the support of self-directed learning:  Vialogues (TC Video Discussion Application), PocketKnowledge (TC Online Archive), DocDel (E-Reserve System), Pressible (Blogging Platform), Library Website and Mobile App.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Statistical modeling for dynamic social networks</title>
      <link>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Networked systems are ubiquitous in modern society.  In a dynamic social or biological environment, the interactions among subjects can undergo large and systematic changes. Due to the rapid advancement of technology, a lot of social networks are observed with time information. Some examples include the email communication network between users, comments on Facebook, the retweet activities on Twitter, etc.  We aim to propose new statistical models and associated methodologies for various problems including community detection, change point detection and behavior prediction. The proposed methods will be evaluated on a wide range of network datasets in different areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Healthcare data analytics internship</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-healthcare-data-analytics-internship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-healthcare-data-analytics-internship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently Columbia University, Cornell, and NewYork-Presbyterian have agreed to integrate their clinical (healthcare) and business IT systems onto one shared platform called Epic. The motivating factors to move to Epic are to enhance the patient experience, improve and integrate care, and give our physicians an integrated technology platform that supports the mission of an academic medical center. The intern will assist with developing the “operational” analytics capabilities of Columbia University Medical Center including financial, healthcare operations and healthcare quality analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>