<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis and processing of GIS data in assessing international development</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-analysis-and-processing-of-gis-data-in-assessing-international-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-analysis-and-processing-of-gis-data-in-assessing-international-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We need someone with strong data wrangling capabilities, to be able to determine quick ways to clean and merge data. The format of the data is spatial (GIS) but it could also be manipulated in tabular format. GRID3 is a program within &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ciesin.org/&#34;&gt;CIESIN&lt;/a&gt; which is a research center located at the Lamont-Doherty Campus (with office space on the morningside campus) and is part of Columbia&amp;rsquo;s Earth Institute.  Candidates can learn more about the program at the GRID3 &lt;a href=&#34;https://grid3.org/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Stick2PrEP - Analysis of adherence for Pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) against HIV in observational and RCT interventions</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-data-for-good-stick2prep---analysis-of-adherence-for-pre-exposure-prophylaxis-prep-against-hiv-in-observational-and-rct-interventions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-data-for-good-stick2prep---analysis-of-adherence-for-pre-exposure-prophylaxis-prep-against-hiv-in-observational-and-rct-interventions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) has been shown to be extremely effective in reducing the acquisition of HIV.  However, achieving the population-level impact of this intervention is contingent on the identification and linkage of appropriate candidates and ongoing engagement in care throughout periods of high and low risk.  Pre-COVID we had a suite of active studies looking at engagement in PrEP care.  These included  our PrEP database, Get2PrEP (studying individuals with positive STI tests but no PrEP engagement), Back2PrEP (evaluating patients who dropped out of care and re-engaged), Lost2PrEP (survey of individuals who have been out of care for 6 months or more), and our major study Stick2PrEP2.0 a randomized-control trial of text message based feedback to individuals receiving PrEP care and evaluating engagement.  At the time of the COVID pandemic we had just started to perform interim analysis on Stick2PrEP2.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phenotyping COVID-19 patients using NLP and clinical notes</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-phenotyping-covid-19-patients-using-nlp-and-clinical-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-phenotyping-covid-19-patients-using-nlp-and-clinical-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our lab is using clinical notes to phenotype COVID patient outcomes. The aim is to better understand the sequela of COVID-19 from clinical notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social media echo chambers enhancing anxiety and depression: the effects of COVID-19</title>
      <link>/2020/05/project-social-media-echo-chambers-enhancing-anxiety-and-depression-the-effects-of-covid19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/project-social-media-echo-chambers-enhancing-anxiety-and-depression-the-effects-of-covid19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The question we ask is whether online echo-chambers on social media networks enhance the anxiety and depression of individuals during the COVID19 outbreak. More specifically we want to measure the intensity of the communication about COVID-19 within the echo-chamber of individuals on Twitter and investigate the impact on their subsequent tweets in terms of the level of anxiety and signs of depressive language in their Tweets.  We measure echo-chambers by the number of users in the social network that tweeted about COVID-19. We build on an extensive dataset of Twitter users for whom we have identified a large number of demographic and geographic variables (such as the gender, age, ethnicity, location by state, political affiliation) as well as their social network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating accurate and equitable data resources for precision public health using machine learning tools</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-creating-accurate-and-equitable-data-resources-for-precision-public-health-using-machine-learning-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-creating-accurate-and-equitable-data-resources-for-precision-public-health-using-machine-learning-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The objective of this project is to construct linkages across disparate public health data systems using machine learning tools and assess them for bias and equitable representation of subpopulations defined by demographic and socioeconomic factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data For Good: Data Analysis for a Just Transition in Energy for Thermal Comfort</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-data-analysis-for-a-just-transition-in-energy-for-thermal-comfort/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-data-analysis-for-a-just-transition-in-energy-for-thermal-comfort/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;42% of New York City greenhouse gas emissions result from on-site fossil fuel combustion in residential and commercial buildings; space heating is, by far, the majority contributor. Both New York State and NYC have policies to dramatically reduce emissions that will require a transformation in the way buildings are heated, including major efforts in existing buildings. This transition is inextricably linked to existing energy equity issues that we believe significantly overlap across NYC (and elsewhere). These include unreliable heating in the winter, susceptibility to extreme heat (an increasing occurrence with climate change) and struggles to afford energy needs. Various known data sources for NYC are available, though they are disparate and have not been analyzed holistically. Further, we believe there are potential engineering and policy solutions to these challenges. In this project, the DSI scholar will access (and search for where not yet known to qSEL researchers) relevant data sets, analyze those data sets to identify communities exposed to all or a subset of these issues, and assist qSEL researchers in developing models to evaluate possible solutions. The project has the possibility of extending through Summer 2020, subject to fundraising efforts and the success of the Spring 2020 project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of genes associated with progression of bladder cancer</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have been studying bladder cancer in a mouse model of the disease and we are seeking to understand the molecular features of the mouse models as they relate to human bladder cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single cell RNA-seq analysis of eye development and disease</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-single-cell-rna-seq-analysis-of-eye-development-and-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-single-cell-rna-seq-analysis-of-eye-development-and-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Single cell sequencing has generated unprecedented insight into the cellular complexity of normal and diseased organ. We are interested in using this technique to understand the mechanisms of eye development, disease and regeneration. We also would like to compare the transcriptomic signatures between mouse models and human tissues. This project involves analysis of large amount of data from single cell sequencing. It requires understanding of statistical analysis and proficient programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical analyses of Siamese fighting fish aggressive behavior</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-statistical-analyses-of-siamese-fighting-fish-aggressive-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-statistical-analyses-of-siamese-fighting-fish-aggressive-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Project: analyze behavior of Siamese fighting fish (Betta splendens) as part of a collaboration between the Bendesky and Cunningham labs of the Zuckerman Institute (NeuroTheory Center)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Urban Lead Atlas</title>
      <link>/2020/01/project-the-urban-lead-atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/project-the-urban-lead-atlas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Urban Lead Atlas is a collaborative community-based research initiative to create the nations’ first crowd-sourced open online map identifying toxic lead hazards located within the homes, schools, landscape, and lead service lines for water in American cities. The project will begin by integrating data from a small set of cities – New York, Philadelphia, Washington D.C. and Newark - including housing enforcement and lead service line datasets, data on lead dust in schools, and the results of soil lead tests in parks and backyards, on the websites of Columbia University’s Center for Sustainable Urban Development. Ultimately, the goal of the Urban Lead Atlas is to create and populate a fully open online platform that is capable of integrating data from “citizen scientists” and residents regarding the sites of lead hazards in their city’s environment and buildings. This research is important, as experts estimate that over nine million US children have lead blood levels which may cause sub-clinical effects and permanent adverse health, cognitive, and behavior outcomes. The Lead Atlas is intended as the first model for a national effort, the American Lead Atlas project, which seeks to create a national online collaborative map of lead hazards within American cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Healthcare machine learning and text mining (NimbleMiner)</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-healthcare-machine-learning-and-text-mining-nimbleminer/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-healthcare-machine-learning-and-text-mining-nimbleminer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our lab develops an open-source text mining software called NimbleMiner (&lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/mtopaz/NimbleMiner&#34;&gt;http://github.com/mtopaz/NimbleMiner&lt;/a&gt;). We will work on improving the software using the latest machine learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Locally advanced primary colon, rectosigmoid and rectal cancers: Perioperative outcomes and survival with multivisceral resection</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-locally-advanced-primary-colon-rectosigmoid-and-rectal-cancers-perioperative-outcomes-and-survival-with-multivisceral-resection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-locally-advanced-primary-colon-rectosigmoid-and-rectal-cancers-perioperative-outcomes-and-survival-with-multivisceral-resection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Locally advanced colorectal cancers that invade adjacent organs (i.e., T4 primary tumors) without evidence of distant metastasis account for approximately 5-15% of new colorectal cancers.  There are limited multi-institutional study describing the perioperative complication rates and long-term survival of patients undergoing single organ resection after neoadjuvant chemotherapy and/or radiation versus multivisceral resections for patients with T4 colorectal cancers.  Using the American College of Surgeons National Cancer Database (NCDB), we seek to analyze differential outcomes (perioperative complications and overall survival) by procedure performed, tumor details, pathological findings, chemo-radiotherapy regimens, patient demographics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-Cell Transcriptome Profiling in Atherosclerosis</title>
      <link>/2019/09/project-single-cell-transcriptome-profiling-in-atherosclerosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/09/project-single-cell-transcriptome-profiling-in-atherosclerosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Atherosclerosis—a chronic inflammatory disease of the artery wall—is the underlying cause of human coronary heart diseases. Cells within atherosclerotic lesions are heterogeneous and dynamic. Their pathological features have been characterized by histology and flow cytometry and more recently, by bulk-tissue omics profiling. Despite this progress, our knowledge of cell types and their roles in atherogenesis remains incomplete because of masking of differences across cells when using genomic measurement at bulk level. Single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) has catalyzed a revolution in understanding of cellular heterogeneity in organ systems and diseases. This project applies scRNA-seq to define the genetic influences on cell subpopulations and functions in atherosclerotic lesion of transgenic mice for candidate risk genes of human coronary heart diseases as inspired by human genomic discoveries. The students involved in this project are expected to work on: (1) analysis of scRNA-seq data using R/Bioconductor packages; (2) Interpretation of the data using pathway and network analysis. Some relevant workflows are available through the &amp;ldquo;Resources&amp;rdquo; page of our lab website at &lt;a href=&#34;https://hanruizhang.github.io/zhanglab/&#34;&gt;https://hanruizhang.github.io/zhanglab/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Analysis and Prediction of Opioid Outbreak Clusters</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-analysis-and-prediction-of-opioid-outbreak-clusters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-analysis-and-prediction-of-opioid-outbreak-clusters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are interested in investigating how deaths and hospitalizations resulting from opioid overdoses cluster across space and time in the US. This analysis will be conducted with the aid of two comprehensive databases: 1) detailed mortality data across the US; and 2) a stratified sample of all hospitalizations in the US, which can be subset to select for opioid overdoses. Analyses will be extended to drug type (prescription drugs, fentanyl etc.) and subject demographics (age, race, etc.). We have previously conducted similar cluster analysis for other health phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Discover novel regulators of macrophage efferocytosis by genome-wide CRISPR screen</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-discover-novel-regulators-of-macrophage-efferocytosis-by-genome-wide-crispr-screen/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-discover-novel-regulators-of-macrophage-efferocytosis-by-genome-wide-crispr-screen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Defective efferocytosis, the phagocytic clearance of apoptotic cells, by macrophages is the cause of many human diseases including tumor, autoimmune diseases and atherosclerosis. Enhancing efferocytosis has potential therapeutic benefits. Many key regulators of efferocytosis have been identified, but a systematic approach to map regulators of efferocytosis in an unbiased manner on a genome-wide scale is missing. This project applies innovative genome-wide CRISPR screen to discover novel regulators of macrophage efferocytosis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Discovery of genes associated with progression of bladder cancer</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-discovery-of-genes-associated-with-progression-of-bladder-cancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have been studying bladder cancer in a mouse model of the disease and we are seeking to understand the molecular features of the mouse models as they relate to human bladder cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Measuring Broadband</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-measuring-broadband/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-measuring-broadband/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Communications Commission (FCC) and the Census regularly publish data on U.S. Internet availability, performance and use, at granularities from census block to county and state. The project goal is to answer questions based on the available data, such as &amp;ldquo;How reliable is Internet access?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Who is deploying fiber where?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Can we predict reliability of different technologies?&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Can we predict the deployment of fiber?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data science for better health</title>
      <link>/2019/01/project-data-science-for-better-health/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/01/project-data-science-for-better-health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our goal is use a large pool of homecare data (including structured data, free text clinical notes, and recorded patient-provider phone conversations) to build predictive models that help identify patients at risk for poor outcomes (like hospital admission or falls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Technology transfer insights from data</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-technology-transfer-insights-from-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-technology-transfer-insights-from-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CTV’s core mission is to facilitate the transfer of inventions from academic labs to the market for the benefit of society. In a typical year, CTV receives ~400 inventions, completes ~100 licenses and options, and helps form ~20 startups. A good video summary of CTV is here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/110193999&#34;&gt;https://vimeo.com/110193999&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Data Science and the regulation of financial markets (application closed)</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-data-science-and-the-regulation-of-financial-markets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The development of computational data science
techniques in natural language processing (NLP) and machine
learning (ML) algorithms to analyze large and complex textual
information opens new avenues to study intricate processes,
such as government regulation of financial markets, at a scale
unimaginable even a few years ago. This project develops scalable
NLP and ML algorithms (classification, clustering and
ranking methods) that automatically classify laws into various
codes/labels, rank feature sets based on use case, and induce
best structured representation of sentences for various types of
computational analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Enhancing self-directed learning opportunities</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-enhancing-self-directed-learning-opportunities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Analyze data from one of the following library applications/systems and create visualizations that highlight the most important findings pertaining to the support of self-directed learning:  Vialogues (TC Video Discussion Application), PocketKnowledge (TC Online Archive), DocDel (E-Reserve System), Pressible (Blogging Platform), Library Website and Mobile App.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Statistical modeling for dynamic social networks</title>
      <link>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/statistical-modeling-for-dynamic-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Networked systems are ubiquitous in modern society.  In a dynamic social or biological environment, the interactions among subjects can undergo large and systematic changes. Due to the rapid advancement of technology, a lot of social networks are observed with time information. Some examples include the email communication network between users, comments on Facebook, the retweet activities on Twitter, etc.  We aim to propose new statistical models and associated methodologies for various problems including community detection, change point detection and behavior prediction. The proposed methods will be evaluated on a wide range of network datasets in different areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Healthcare data analytics internship</title>
      <link>/2018/01/project-healthcare-data-analytics-internship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/project-healthcare-data-analytics-internship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently Columbia University, Cornell, and NewYork-Presbyterian have agreed to integrate their clinical (healthcare) and business IT systems onto one shared platform called Epic. The motivating factors to move to Epic are to enhance the patient experience, improve and integrate care, and give our physicians an integrated technology platform that supports the mission of an academic medical center. The intern will assist with developing the “operational” analytics capabilities of Columbia University Medical Center including financial, healthcare operations and healthcare quality analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>