<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bayesian on Columbia DSI Scholars</title>
    <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/tags/bayesian/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bayesian on Columbia DSI Scholars</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/tags/bayesian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Advanced data science methods to improve spinal electrical stimulation for paralysis</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/01/project-advanced-data-science-methods-to-improve-spinal-electrical-stimulation-for-paralysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/01/project-advanced-data-science-methods-to-improve-spinal-electrical-stimulation-for-paralysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We aim to augment recovery in spinal cord (SC) injured patients. Electrical stimulation of the SC can facilitate recovery, but the mechanisms are not yet understood. One knowledge gap lies in the exact pathways that are recruited by stimulation. To close this gap, we have tested the effects of SC stimulation in people undergoing clinically indicated surgery. By testing the distribution and size of muscle responses to SC stimulation, we can infer which circuits are activated. We are also examining how SC injury changes those responses. We propose to use Bayesian methods to understand the  interaction between muscle responses to stimulation and the MRI indicated pattern of damage. The project will involve construction of models linking multiple data modalities that predict muscle activity, followed by the modification of these models to account for patterns of damage. Construction of such models would enable a deeper understanding of SC stimulation leading to more effective stimulation paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering latent structure in human information demand</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/01/project-discovering-latent-structure-in-human-information-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2020/01/project-discovering-latent-structure-in-human-information-demand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All complex behaviors require animals to coordinate their perception and actions. To successfully achieve a goal, a decision maker (DM; be it a human, animal, or artificial agent) must determine which action to take and, faced with much more information than she can fully process, must decide which source of information to consult to best guide that action. But in contrast with natural tasks, traditional research has focused primarily on action selection but eschewed the process of information demand. We aim to fill this gap by investigating the factors that motivate people to become curious and seek information.  We are collecting behavioral data from a large sample of participants on a battery of online tasks testing various aspects of curiosity, and seek a DSI scholar who can quantitatively analyze the data. The scholar will be supervised by two co-PIs: Jacqueline Gottlieb, in Columbia&amp;rsquo;s Neuroscience Department and Zuckerman Institute, and Vince Dorie, in the DSI. The scholar will obtain training with advanced data analytic methods and the opportunity to co-author what is expected to be a high impact paper with interdisciplinary appeal in economics, neuroscience, and psychology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project: Political attitudes and social networks</title>
      <link>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2018/01/project-political-attitudes-and-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cu-dsi-scholars.github.io/DSI-scholars/2018/01/project-political-attitudes-and-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are collecting and analyzing survey data asking people about the political attitudes and other characteristics of their family, friends, and others in their social circles. Some of this work is described &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/unpublished/penumbra_paper_11_clean.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and we are also doing polling relevant to the 2018 midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
